<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-bdd83f57-c780-4918-983f-57c78079182f" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>閭丘嬰</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="MALES OF QI" tls:concept-id="uuid-06a8072a-6fc5-4dab-b481-12f6519dc5cd" xml:id="uuid-6a653c96-f848-4ce6-9e81-5ab3264ff2bd" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4d1d694e-fc29-4b9f-ab11-e70d1b7c872b #uuid-1e24a96a-b3b4-4016-ab95-0acdb72d45d7 #uuid-79ed2be2-281e-45e3-bede-3c6bae832d28">
<orth>閭丘嬰</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">lǘ qiū yīng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡ-ra khɯ qeŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">li̯ɤ khɨu ʔiɛŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <form corresp="#uuid-b7577c05-2755-4907-8381-664b4f8f3ab3 #uuid-8263f487-9fc0-47ce-a0ba-e8611194fb33">
<orth>崔杼</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">cuī shù</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhluul ɢljaʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tshuo̝i ʑi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4aaac588-378b-414b-855f-6f0bd2f16d5e">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2020-04-18T03:04:57.802+09:00">Cuī Zhù 崔杼 (d. 546) (according to the Jingdianshiwen entry to ZUO Xuan 10 the name should be read Cui Zhu) was a dignitary in Qi, descendent of Duke Ding of Qi 齊丁公. His feof was the city of Cui 崔, hence the name. He won favour with Duke Hui of Qi 齊惠公 (r. 608-599), but after the latter’s death he fled together with a group of other proteges of Duke Hui to the state Wey 衛. Under Duke Ling of Qi 齊靈公 (r. 581-554) he became a dignitary in the state of Qi again and joined a military campaign against Zheng and Qin. Even under Duke Ling’s successor &gt;Duke Zhuang of Qi 齊莊公 (r. 553-548) Cui Zhu continued to gain military merits. On a condolence visit representing his new ruler, Duke Zhuang, he fell in love with the beautiful Tang Jiang 棠姜 and married her. Duke Zhuang fell for the beauty, too and took her in as his own wife. Understandably enraged, Cui Zhu murdered Duke Zhuang and established Duke Jing of Qi 齊景公 (r. 547 - 490) on the throne, taking for himself the position of the prime minister. ZUO Xiang 25 reports: “The grand historian wrote in his records: "Cui Zhu assassinated his ruler." Cui Zhu had him killed. The historian's younger brother succeeded to the post and wrote the same thing. He too was killed, as was another brother.When a fourth brother came forward to write, Cui Zhu finally desisted.” … Two years after this, in 546, &gt;Qing Feng 慶封, siding with the side of the deceased Duke Zhuang, exterminated Cui Zhu’s whole clan and forced Cui Zhu himself to commit suicide. [ZUO Xiang 25 and 27 have detailed elaborated narratives on Cui Zhu.] [Fang Zhaohui 2002: 487-499]　Unger no. 838</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>