<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-b8dfc90e-d8d3-4645-9fc9-0ed8d32645f8" n="11">
    <form>
        <orth>楚</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="PAIN" tls:concept-id="uuid-1babfc6a-dc73-4072-bb8a-21a58f671735" xml:id="uuid-db66fcc5-54f9-42d3-b44c-131b96d4687a" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1d54264a-5d3f-429e-891b-7e4f8b3d623c">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>suffer pain</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="FOREST" tls:concept-id="uuid-71380132-9a2c-4d60-a9c1-5dfc910069cc" xml:id="uuid-65b72bb0-2490-4422-8d0e-f2a53e6e8efb" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c199b19d-be58-420f-be60-e4392b3852fc">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>copse; bosk</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STRIKE" tls:concept-id="uuid-efb80ae1-71c6-435c-bc1b-55f2406b12ea" xml:id="uuid-3002782c-e18b-4384-ac25-e8daa69473bc" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d50ee14d-c546-4f99-a37a-22baddc87569">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>strike with a stick or whip</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="SUFFER" tls:concept-id="uuid-a199de15-31bc-4e0f-8ed9-848aa83a25a4" xml:id="uuid-bebae78f-6baa-46fc-91f6-bfddbb3f6454" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-607f27b8-8a63-4428-a006-dcc835728e7e">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-76be1df4-3d73-4e5f-bbc2-729542645bc8">nab</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>suffering 辛楚</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="TOGETHER" tls:concept-id="uuid-2f3abab6-3df8-4acf-9599-078f7b053513" xml:id="uuid-acc1dc64-85ab-473c-81dc-6485ab073c1e" n="1">
        <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-7ee024c3-2e05-45e0-8f8f-6ef90067bdbf" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-76be1df4-3d73-4e5f-bbc2-729542645bc8">nab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-4e92cef6-5753-4eed-a76b-7249c223316f">feature</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-11-13T02:41:31.37+09:00">together, in full array</def>
            </sense>
    </entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="TREE, KINDS" tls:concept-id="uuid-b5e991a9-bcc5-4224-97bc-5cd4c591d0a9" xml:id="uuid-aa09beab-0d7d-452e-a417-a59bbbe0c851" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d947c225-40cb-4db0-94f4-412a3aa73caf" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>chu-tree; thicket of trees; thorny</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="ORDERLY" tls:concept-id="uuid-e9cc1a75-2d2f-4442-9061-a1deb8ac5390" xml:id="uuid-85bdb67a-e113-4adb-93f3-bcc6bd22167d" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>

</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="BUSH" tls:concept-id="uuid-b3e14ddb-e2c7-4076-b72d-50e04512d2c4" xml:id="uuid-0f363f81-87bb-430f-b958-be269c6a603e" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-054a1f0e-c8ab-40b7-900a-586b27db6db0">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>thornbush</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STICK" tls:concept-id="uuid-c8e47163-7e21-4e28-b56f-fb2b57b9dda1" xml:id="uuid-1559f382-1278-436d-8702-0340a72a435e" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-bce6e463-410b-4909-871f-65b992287d0c">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>specialised term for a cane used as an instrument for punishment</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="COLOURFUL" tls:concept-id="uuid-18077152-effe-42f8-bc0b-a04afe162b1e" xml:id="uuid-5ca65cba-34b1-4fcf-a065-8d1c6782db14" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b164995b-2883-41cb-994f-3db5b9d118f1" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fed035db-e7bd-4d23-bd05-9698b26e38f9">vadN</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>colourful and beautiful (as customary in the state of Chu) 楚服</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-18ecfebe-2086-4de5-8793-8f3d83acd9ea" n="24">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Chǔ 楚 (also called Jīng 荊, Chǔ Jīng 楚荊, Mán Jīng 蠻荊, Jīng Yí 荊夷, Chǔ Mán 蠻楚) (CHEN PAN 1969, 197-231)

Clan: Mì 羋 (attested also by the inscriptions on the bronzes). It is not very clear what mean the component Xióng 熊 which often occurs in the names of mainly early Chǔ rulers. Some scholars have suggested that it originally it could have been also a surname, or the local title of the Chǔ rulers.

Rank: In the Zhōu hierarchy, the rulers of Chǔ were of zǐ 子 rank (the title is common in CQ). This fact is even for the early Western Zhōu period attested by one bone inscription found in the first Zhōu capital of Zhōuyuán 周原. According to the Du;s commentary to ZUO (Huan 2; 710 B.C.), since the reing of King Wǔ of Chǔ 楚武王 (740-690 B.C.) the rulers of Chǔ adopted the title of wáng 王 (this is also attested by the Chǔ shìjiā chapter of SHI). According to the Chǔ shìjiā chapter of SHI, the Chǔ ruler Xióng Qú 熊渠 adopted the title of wáng already during the reign of the Zhōu king Yí 周夷王 (ca 865-858 B.C.), but later rejected it.
In the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts, rulers of Chǔ are sometimes referred to as gōng 公, hóu 侯, or bó 伯.

Founded: According to ZUO and to SHI (Chǔ shìjiā), the first ruler of Chǔ who received the title of zǐ from the Zhōu king Chéng 周成王 was Xióng Yì 熊 in the second half of the eleventh century B.C. MOZI associates this story with Xióng Lì 熊麗 who was (according to SHI) the grandfather of Xióng Yì. Whatever the truth is, the state of Chǔ obviously existed (long?) prior to this event, as the quite reliable genealogy of the Chǔ rulers in SHI goes back to Yù Xióng 鬻熊 (the father of Xióng Lì), who is said to be contemporary with the Zhōu pre-conquest king Wén 周文王. Note that the fact that Chǔ had the some relationship with the Zhōu royal house already in the early Western Zhōu period is well-attested by the above-mentioned inscription from Zhōuyuán recording the visit of the viscount of Chǔ 楚子.
How far the history of Chǔ goes prior the Western Zhōu period is not known. Note that the poem Yīn wǔ of the Shījīng mentions the attack of the Shāng king Wǔ Dīng 武丁 on Jīng Chǔ. SHI (Chǔ shìjiā) and XUNZI goes as far back as the period of Xià and the reign of the first Shāng king Chéng Tāng 成湯, but those records do no not seem to be reliable. Note in this context that the place name Chǔ appears already in the oracle bone inscriptions, but it is problematic whether there was any relationship between this Chǔ and the later state of Chǔ.
According to the mythical tradition obviously kept in Chǔ and recorded in SHI (Chǔ shìjiā), the rulers of Chǔ were descendants of the mythical Zhù Róng 柷融.  

Destroyed: Eliminated in 223 BC by &gt;Qín 秦.

Location: Southern state located in the southern Henan, Hubei, part of Hunan, and later also controlling parts of Jiangxi, Jiangsu, Zhejiang and Shandong.
The first capital was Dānyáng 丹陽. Its location is unknown, and quite many possibilities were offered by traditional Chinese historiography, ranging from modern Anhui province (Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì) over the northern and central parts of Hubei province (Kuò dì zhì, Chūnqiū dì míng kǎo lyè) to the area of the Dān 丹 river in the southern Henan (Sòng Xiángfèng). The latter opinion seems to be the most probable one with regard to the fact that in the Warring states period there was really place called Dānyáng in that area, to the fact that the first Chǔ capital could not be located too far from the early Zhōu centers, and also with regard to the scope and area of the early Chǔ expansion. Note also the fact that the lavishly equiped tombs belonging to the members of the highest Chǔ aristocracy (and dating from the sixth century B.C.) were uncovered in Xichuan district in the southern part of Henan, approximately in this area. 
In 690 (Zhuang 4) the capital was moved to Yǐng 郢 (according to SHI Chǔ shìjiā). This is located by the Du's commentary to ZUO and Shuǐ jīng zhù to modern Jìnán 紀南 in Hubei Province, and this opinion is accepted by the most of the modern Chinese scholars; it is supposed that this Yǐng is identical with the city excavated in that area. However, this identification is by no means certain. Archaeological Jìnán was with the all probability the capital of Chǔ (called Yǐng) in the Warring states period, but there is no evidence of a substantial settlement dating from the Chunqiu period. Not improbable is the opinion (see Blakeley 19..) that in the Chunqiu period Yǐng was located in southern Henan. However, what contradicts it is the record in ZUO for 617 B.C. (Wen 10) that when the duke of Shāng 商公 went to the visit to Yǐng, he sailed down the Hàn 漢 River and then against the stream of the Jiāng 江. It is also possible that the capital moved several times, but it still bore the same name.
After 506 B.C. (Ding 4) when Yǐng was sacked by the armies of &gt;Wú , King Zhāo moved to Rùo 鄀 (or Yān ) to the north in the area of the Hàn River valley (according to the Hàn zhì and Dì míng kǎo lyè). Then the capital again shifted to Yǐng, which is for the Warring states period with great probability identical with Jìnán.
After 278 BC the capital was moved to Chén 陳(modern Huáiyáng 淮陽 in eastern Henan), in 253 BC to Jùyáng 巨陽 in Anhui, and, definitely, in 241 to modern Xúzhōu 徐州 which was also called Yǐng. 

History: The origins of Chǔ are not clear, as well as its original location. According to the Shiji, the ruler of Chǔ was given an investiture by the king Chéng of Zhōu (&gt;Zhōu Chéng wáng 周成王). This fact is partly supported by the mention of the visit of the ruler of Chǔ in a Zhōu capital in Zhōu oracle bones uncovered in Zhōuyuán 周原. It seems that Chǔ was located not far from the Zhou centers, perhaps in southern Henan (see Location). Also the early artefacts which can be associated with Chǔ are not substantially different from the Zhou art, and it seems that a distinctive Chǔ culture was not developed prior middle Chunqiu period. In the 8th and 7th centuries Chǔ grew in power, destroyed many small states located mainly in southern Henan, and became one of the leading powers in China. Chǔ ambitions to challenge the power of the declining Zhōu dynasty were manifested in 704 BC, when the ruler of Chǔ declared himself a king. In 632 BC Chǔ was seriously defeated by &gt;Jìn 晉at Chéngpú 城濮, but in 597 the &gt;king Zhuāng 楚莊王 of Chǔ won a great victory over Jìn armies at Bì 邲 and for a time became a hegemon. The struggle for a hegemony between Chǔ and Jìn thereafter lasted till 546 BC when status quo was recognized in a conference held at &gt;Sòng 宋. At the end of the sixth century Chǔ went through a serious crisis, and in 506 BC its capital was even occupied by the southeastern state of &gt;Wú 吳. In the fifth century Chǔ regained its power and expanded to the East. In the end of the fourth and beginning of the third century it received several severe defeats from the state of &gt;Qín 秦, and in 278 BC Qín occupied the capital of Chǔ. Chǔ thereafter moved its center to the East. This "Eastern Chu" was destroyed by Qín in 223 BC.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-df6c5067-da39-4458-a55a-9b7b23550faf" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-18019dfe-5655-487f-bc7b-7a1434f64ad1">npr.adV</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>in the manner of Chǔ</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-311645d2-01c9-47ce-92c4-ee1a5935337f" n="16">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-5e5f87f4-164a-44e2-93a7-240317a7f563" resp="#dsehnal" tls:created="2019-12-04T23:22:59.723+09:00" n="6">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>N</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#">npradN</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def resp="#zadrapa" updated="2021-01-25T06:24:48.57+09:00">of Chu3; belonging to Chu3;</def>
        </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-495db51e-e63e-41db-9db5-1ee63e21db06" resp="#zadrapa" tls:created="2022-02-11T21:27:32.376+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>have Chu-ish features, be Chu-ish</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
</superEntry>