<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-b9ebe8c4-c216-4fef-abe8-c4c2168fef59" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>邢</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-d2cfb277-c36d-46bc-b200-de369c57bda8" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-f94552f5-9ddf-494c-95a0-9ea05d5ac941">
<orth>邢</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xíng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡeeŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦeŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Xíng 邢 (maybe identical with Jǐng 井 in the inscriptions on the bronzes) (CHEN PAN 1969, 360-368)

Clan: Jī 姬.

Rank: Hóu 侯 (in the CQ and the ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronzes, rulers of Jǐng 井 refer to themselves as gōng 公 or bó 伯.

Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by the fourth son of the Duke of Zhōu 周公 (according to the Tōng zhì Shì zú lyè; Chūnqiū dì míng kǎolyè quotes Shǐ jì, which says that the name of the son of the Duke of Zhōu enfeoffed by the Zhōu king Chéng 周成王 as a ruler of Xíng was Jìngyuān 靖淵. The sentence is missing in the current text of the Shǐ jì).

Destroyed: In 635 B.C. (Xi 25) by Wèi 衛.

Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, the capital of Xíng was located in the modern Xíngtái 邢臺 district, southern part of Hebei province. However, other sources suggested other locations, mainly the modern Wēn 溫 district in the Henan province, where the first capital of Xíng, called Xíngqiū 邢丘 should have been located (Shuō wén jiě zì; Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì, Xù Hàn shū Jùn guó zhì). This fits quite well with the record that in 718 B.C. (Yin 5), Xíng together with Zhèng supported the Earl of Qūwò 曲沃 in his attack on Yì 翼, the capital of Jìn 晉 located in the southwestern part of Shānxī province. However, in 661 B.C. (Min 1), when Xíng was attacked by the Dí 狄 barbarians, and was given a support from Qí 齊 and Cáo 曹, the state must have been located already in their close neighborhood, apparently in the modern Xíngtái 邢臺. Then the capital of Xíng shifted to the East of the Yellow River, to the Yíyí 夷儀, probably located in the modern Liáochéng 聊城 district in the western part of the Shandong province (according to Gāo Shìqí).

History: Note that the state(s) and place(s) called Jǐng 井 and/or Xíng 邢 existed already in the Late Shāng period. Jǐng fāng 井方 is mentioned in the oracle bone inscriptions; Shǐ jì (Yīn běnjì) records that Xíng 邢 was one of the Shāng capitals (under king Zǔ Yǐ 祖乙), and Dìwáng shìjì mentions that the Marquis of Xíng 邢侯 was one of the three high officials in the court of the last Shāng king (however, one should not give much confidence to the last source). Which was the connection between those and the later Zhōu state of Xíng is difficult to decide. In this context it is interesting, that in the site of Xíngtái 邢臺, Hebei province, the continuous settlement dating from the Late Shāng to the Chunqiu period was attested. Note also the inscription on the bronze vessel belonging to the Marquis of Xíng, which can point to the fact that the Xíng was formerly quite strong state. However, in 661 B.C., it was almost exterminated by the Dí barbarians, and in the following year, its capital was shifted under the aegis of Qí to Yíyí (which was one year later fortified by the armies of Qí and Cáo). In 635 B.C., the state was annihilated by Wèi.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-605e9894-a837-4b79-ba34-a77c1f2b27a0">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Xíng 邢 (maybe identical with Jǐng 井 in the inscriptions on the bronzes) (CHEN PAN 1969, 360-368)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Hóu 侯 (in the CQ and the ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronzes, rulers of Jǐng 井 refer to themselves as gōng 公 or bó 伯. Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by the fourth son of the Duke of Zhōu 周公 (according to the Tōng zhì Shì zú lyè; Chūnqiū dì míng kǎolyè quotes Shǐ jì, which says that the name of the son of the Duke of Zhōu enfeoffed by the Zhōu king Chéng 周成王 as a ruler of Xíng was Jìngyuān 靖淵. The sentence is missing in the current text of the Shǐ jì).Destroyed: In 635 B.C. (Xi 25) by Wèi 衛. Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, the capital of Xíng was located in the modern Xíngtái 邢臺 district, southern part of Hebei province. However, other sources suggested other locations, mainly the modern Wēn 溫 district in the Henan province, where the first capital of Xíng, called Xíngqiū 邢丘 should have been located (Shuō wén jiě zì; Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì, Xù Hàn shū Jùn guó zhì). This fits quite well with the record that in 718 B.C. (Yin 5), Xíng together with Zhèng supported the Earl of Qūwò 曲沃 in his attack on Yì 翼, the capital of Jìn 晉 located in the southwestern part of Shānxī province. However, in 661 B.C. (Min 1), when Xíng was attacked by the Dí 狄 barbarians, and was given a support from Qí 齊 and Cáo 曹, the state must have been located already in their close neighborhood, apparently in the modern Xíngtái 邢臺. Then the capital of Xíng shifted to the East of the Yellow River, to the Yíyí 夷儀, probably located in the modern Liáochéng 聊城 district in the western part of the Shandong province (according to Gāo Shìqí). History: Note that the state(s) and place(s) called Jǐng 井 and/or Xíng 邢 existed already in the Late Shāng period. Jǐng fāng 井方 is mentioned in the oracle bone inscriptions; Shǐ jì (Yīn běnjì) records that Xíng 邢 was one of the Shāng capitals (under king Zǔ Yǐ 祖乙 ), and Dìwáng shìjì mentions that the Marquis of Xíng 邢侯 was one of the three high officials in the court of the last Shāng king (however, one should not give much confidence to the last source). Which was the connection between those and the later Zhōu state of Xíng is difficult to decide. In this context it is interesting, that in the site of Xíngtái 邢臺, Hebei province, the continuous settlement dating from the Late Shāng to the Chunqiu period was attested. Note also the inscription on the bronze vessel belonging to the Marquis of Xíng, which can point to the fact that the Xíng was formerly quite strong state. However, in 661 B.C., it was almost exterminated by the Dí barbarians, and in the following year, its capital was shifted under the aegis of Qí to Yíyí (which was one year later fortified by the armies of Qí and Cáo). In 635 B.C., the state was annihilated by Wèi. </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>