<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-98bedf0e-4fee-4071-bedf-0e4fee307141" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>三十二相</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="APPEARANCE" tls:concept-id="uuid-c8c50293-f8c7-4e59-be5c-c38efa72c6d7" xml:id="uuid-34166496-5f0e-45c9-a7c2-d5d4957c510a" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-3b81e026-2aee-45cd-b686-7bab8c7046b3 #uuid-0015d0e6-8187-4a1f-88d7-b60a7f04ecba #uuid-f103744f-eee5-4a48-aaa5-fec13347ad67 #uuid-237e08ce-7e96-4025-a458-126b4ea4bde1">
<orth>三十二相</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sān shí èr xiàng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">saam ɡjub njis sqaŋs</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">sɑm dʑip ȵi si̯ɐŋ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-2389c812-8053-4187-8f7a-19f6e856050f">FOGUANG</ref>
<title>佛光大辭典 Fóguāng dàcídiǎn The Foguang Dictionary of Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">507</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-80b363d9-8859-464e-b531-474775c06186">SOOTHILL</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Chinese Buddhist Terms</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"Level feet; thousand spoke wheel sign on feet, long slender fingers, pliant hands and feet; toes and fingers finely webbed, full-sized heels; arched insteps; thighs like a royal stag; hands reaching below the knees; well-retracted male organ;  height and  stretch of arms equal; every hair-root dark coloured; body hair graceful and curly; golden-hued body; a 10 foot-halo around him; soft smooth skin; the qi1 chu4 七處, i.e. two soles, two palms, two shoulders, and crown well rounded, below the armpits well-filled; lion-shaped body; erect, full shoulders; forty teeth; teeth white even  and close; the four canine teeth pure white; lion jawed; saliva improving the taste of all food; tongue long and broad; voice deep and resonant; eyes deep blue; eyelashes like a royal bull; a white uurNnaa or curl between the eyebrows emitting light, an uSsNniSsa or fleshy protuberance on the crown." (The sources of Soothill's interpretation are: Sa1n-za1ng fa3 shu4 三藏法數, jua4n 48; Da4-zhi4-fu4 lu4n 大智度論, jua4n 4; NIRVANA, jua4n 28; MIDDLE AGAMA and the Sa1n-shi2-e4r xia1ng ji1ng 三十二相經. Different lists appear in Wu2-lia4ng yi4 ji1ng 無量意經 and A1-ha2n-ji1ng  阿含經, jua4n 11)</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4d427212-b8da-4ed7-bbbc-4c6af23c467c" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-db0698e7-db2f-4ee3-9a20-0c2b2e0cebf0">NPab</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: the thirty-two major physical characterstics of a Buddha; skr. dvātriṃśadvaralakṣaṇa</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1dc16cdc-8287-4def-b26d-4b178c2d8f37" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-14b56546-32fd-4321-8d73-3e4b18316c15">NPadN</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e7204ae-4771-435b-82ff-310068296b6d">buddhist</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: equipped with the thirty-two major physical characterstics of a Buddha</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>