<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-9f67f6e1-1629-46f7-a7f6-e1162956f701" n="2">
    <form>
        <orth>杞</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="TREE, KINDS" tls:concept-id="uuid-b5e991a9-bcc5-4224-97bc-5cd4c591d0a9" xml:id="uuid-5c10c2e4-830a-4fe4-921d-ec962b325c4c" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4d8267de-ab14-4ee7-971f-cc599487401a">
<orth>杞</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">qǐ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">khɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">khɨ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c0af0365-9a83-4a5a-9d49-d5aef54d1f8a" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>kind of willow; Salix purpurea; Lycium chinense??</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-0530883e-2469-44d0-9bfa-064bc1175062" n="2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4d8267de-ab14-4ee7-971f-cc599487401a">
<orth>杞</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">qǐ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">khɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">khɨ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Qǐ 杞 (CHEN PAN 1969, 242-252)

Ruling clan: Sì 似.

Rank: In both CQ and ZUO, the rulers of Qǐ are basically referred to as bó 伯, but sometimes also as hóu 侯, and one time (CQ Xi 22; 638 B.C.) as zǐ 子. In the inscriptions on the bronze vessels, the rulers of Qǐ usually referred to themselves as bó. 

Location: There are many uncertainties concerning precise locations of the Qǐ capitals. According to the commentary to the Hàn zhì Chénliu jùn, the first capital of the state was Yōngqiū 雍丘, probably located in the modern Kāifēng 開封 district, Henan province. Later (prior to the period recorded in the CQ), the capital was shifted to the northeast of the state of Lǔ 魯 in modern Shandong. Exact location of the centre of Qǐ there is uncertain, but with regard to the fact that some bronze vessels made by Qǐ were found in the area of modern Xīn Tài 新泰 district, it is probable that the capital was in that area. ZUO records that later, in 646 B.C. (Xi 14), the capital of Qǐ was shifed by other feudal lords to Yuánlíng 緣陵.

Founded: According to the Shǐ jì, Xià běnjì, the first ruler of Qǐ was the Duke of Dōnglóu 東樓公, the descendant of the Xià 夏 dynasty, who received Qǐ as his fief from King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王.

Destroyed: Conquered by Chǔ 楚 in 445 B.C.

History: Rulers of Qǐ were supposed to be the descendants of the ruling clan of the Xià 夏 dynasty, and enjoyed special position in the Zhōu ritual system. The state for the first time appears in the CQ in the entry for 719 B.C. (Yin 4).
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b6826d19-6f66-4bda-953a-5ab8803568bd" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>