<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-9986eb1b-3941-470c-86eb-1b3941870cfb" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>楚莊王</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="RULERS OF CHU" tls:concept-id="uuid-6461352c-c806-402a-a524-4929879d25a3" xml:id="uuid-e6285219-8cd5-4335-bf93-4c10dc703187" n="2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112 #uuid-67226c6e-a457-423f-8cb2-0bb342f8afa0 #uuid-3b611bc0-1264-4fb0-b354-69ff386f2094">
<orth>楚莊王</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ zhuāng wáng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ skraŋ ɢʷaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ ʈʂi̯ɐŋ ɦi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <form corresp="#uuid-b4820c3f-32fc-401f-b158-340c14efcf29 #uuid-f007481f-6dcf-47d7-9488-e3625bd94dd3">
<orth>熊侶</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xióng lǚ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢum ɡ-raʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦuŋ li̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
            <form corresp="#uuid-ea1b1773-3d65-4902-9d58-7f5dd9bbdb06 #uuid-3b611bc0-1264-4fb0-b354-69ff386f2094">
<orth>顏王</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yán wáng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋraan ɢʷaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋɣan ɦi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <form corresp="#uuid-5b645e44-a1b9-4ba1-bd03-0a684d705f01 #uuid-67226c6e-a457-423f-8cb2-0bb342f8afa0 #uuid-3b611bc0-1264-4fb0-b354-69ff386f2094">
<orth>荊莊王</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jīng zhuāng wáng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kreŋ skraŋ ɢʷaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣaŋ ʈʂi̯ɐŋ ɦi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a9dce05d-e01b-4561-ae76-aadc5a3196f0" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e377e0e-02e8-437f-86ce-f041186bc7aa">human</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2020-04-18T00:39:37.871+09:00">Chŭ Zhuāng Wáng 楚莊王 (r. 613 -591), son of King Mu of Chu 楚穆王, was celebrated as one of the Five Hegemons of the Warring States period. [BHT 2 no 15] To begin with he had to contend with two brothers for the throne, Prince Xie 公子燮 and Zi Yi 子儀. [ZUOWen 14] In 611 Chu suffered a great famine which allowed surrounding states to make inroads into Chu territory. With time King Zhuang became an extremely powerful military leader who became famous for no less than fourteen large-scale successful military campaigns against surrounding states. Although he was never formally acknowledged as a leader of the feudal lords in his life-time, his military successes were many and astounding. It is often pointed out that he used the very capable &gt;Sunshu Ao 孫叔敖 (late 7th – early 6th centuries) as his prime minister, [HNZ 9.10b, 16.20b, 18.28a] who was said to have established a legal system for his southern state, and to have carried out a comprehensive re-organisation of the armed forces. The states of Lu, Song, Chen, and Zheng all came to pledge allegiance to Chu. HNZ is much preoccupied with this king and reports conversations of him on various matters of governance and warfare. We are informed even on his semi-barbarian habits of dressing. [HNZ 11.9a, 14.3b] Even the loss of his pet monkey is described in detail, since he had a whole forest cut down to retrieve the beast. [HNZ 16.8b] In 490 King Zhuang fell ill while engaged on a military campaign, not without passing on his throne to one of a set of ceremonially reluctant princes. [ZUO Wen 14 mentions his accession to the throne, and ZUO Xuan 18 gives an account of his death and this important early source is much less talkative about Duke Zhuang than later sources like HNZ. HSWZ 2.1 portrays him at war, HSWZ 2.4 at audience, HSWZ 3.8 his death with dramatic care, adding Confucius’s comment that Duke Zhuang deserved to become a hegemon. [Fang Zhaohui 2002: 226-242]　PARENTS: Son of &gt;ChǔMù wáng 楚穆王 WIVES:?CHILDREN: Father of &gt;Chǔ Gòngwáng 楚共王</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>