<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-0f40f2bd-babb-4263-80f2-bdbabba2639a" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>韓</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-1449d3ec-6f32-4137-b9b2-cfe742d5fb14" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-84fa6b1d-1c3e-4b0c-b26a-7b7d049f8bcd">
<orth>韓</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">hán</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡaan</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɑn</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Hán 韓 (also called Zhèng 鄭)

Clan: According to the Hán shìjiā chapter of SHI, Hán lineage was of the same surname as the Zhōu kings, i.e. Jī 姬.

Rank: In the secong half of the fifth century B.C., rulers of Zhào were still of dàfū 大夫 rank. In 403 B.C. they were raised to the rank of zhūhóu 諸侯, and were then usually referred to as hóu 侯. In 325 B.C., the ruler of Hán adopted the title of wáng 王.

Founded: Hán was founded by one of the three lineages, which after civil war in 453 B.C. divided among themselves the state of Jìn 晉. The history of the Hán lineage goes back to the first half of the seventh century B.C. when Hán Wàn 韓萬 received the fief in Hán (previously conquered by Jìn) and became Jìn dàfū. Since the beginning of the sixth century B.C., Hán became one of the most powerful lineages in Jìn which in fact usurped the power in the state.

Destroyed: Conquered in 231 B.C. by Qín 秦.

Location: The state of Hán was located in the central part of modern Henan province and in the southern part of Shānxī. The capital was since 415 BC Píngyáng 平陽 in the sothwestern part of modern Shānxī province, in the Fén 汾 River valley. In 375 B.C. (after the conquest of Zhèng 鄭), the capital shifted to Xīn Zhèng 新鄭 (modern Xīn Zhèng 新鄭 in Henan province).

History: Among the three states which emerged after the split of Jìn, Hán was the most weak one. In spite of its conquest of Zhèng in 375 B.C. and Shēn Bùhài's 申不害 reforms in the mid fourth century B.C., Hán was exposed to the pressure from the side of its most powerfull neighbors, and in the end of the fourth and the beginning of the third century it often changed alliances mainly with the states of Qín and Qí. In 231 B.C. it was conquered by Qín as the first of the seven great powers of the Warring states period.   



</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-31bf8508-c31b-4510-a225-d5ce2007d011" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>