<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-0a1c6512-6632-4b30-9c65-1266323b3065" n="2">
    <form>
        <orth>項</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="NECK" tls:concept-id="uuid-209e6066-91a9-4ab2-b0b8-7786620f4660" xml:id="uuid-55acd672-de40-44ac-b5e3-00bff0a2aa56" n="2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-acb87eb1-e18b-435f-be95-747b55476778">
<orth>項</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xiàng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡrooŋʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɣɔŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Xiàng 項 was late to become current, and the word comes to refer specifically to the back of the neck.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6d483df6-2703-4a0f-a070-0a3e972d6c17" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>back of the neck; neck generally</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-5b5ba5be-fb2f-4fc7-97d9-22b4054ade3f" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-acb87eb1-e18b-435f-be95-747b55476778">
<orth>項</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xiàng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡrooŋʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɣɔŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Xiàng 項 (CHEN PAN 1969, 626-628)

Ruling clan: Unknown. According to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, Xìng zuǎn, and Guǎng yùn, the rulers of Xiàng belonged to the Zhōu 周 royal clan Jī 姬.

Rank: Unknown. Shǐ jì Xiàng Yǔ běnj43 zhēngyì (quoting Kuò dì zhì), Huán yǔ jì, and Lù shǐ Guó míng jì suggest that the rulers of Xiàng were of zǐ 子 rank.

Founded: Unknown.

Destroyed: According to the CQ (Xi 17), the state was conquered by Qí 齊 in 643 B.C. ZUO dates the annihilation of Xiàng into the same year, but states that it was occupied by the state of Lǔ 魯. Later the area belonged to Chǔ 楚.

Location: In the modern Xiàngchéng 項城 district, Henan province (according to the Huì zuǎn).
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c7334b53-f1ea-4de4-ba15-754bb18e1296">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Xiàng 項 (CHEN PAN 1969, 626-628)Ruling clan: Unknown. According to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, Xìng zuǎn, and Guǎng yùn, the rulers of Xiàng belonged to the Zhōu 周 royal clan Jī 姬. Rank: Unknown. Shǐ jì Xiàng Yǔ běnjǐ zhēngyì (quoting Kuò dì zhì), Huán yǔ jì, and Lù shǐ Guó míng jǐ suggest that the rulers of Xiàng were of zǐ 子 rank. Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: According to the CQ (Xi 17), the state was conquered by Qí 齊 in 643 B.C. ZUO dates the annihilation of Xiàng into the same year, but states that it was occupied by the state of Lǔ 魯. Later the area belonged to Chǔ 楚. Location: In the modern Xiàngchéng 項城 district, Henan province (according to the Huì zuǎn). </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>