<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-080f8fab-329a-4709-8f8f-ab329a67093b" n="2">
    <form>
        <orth>莒</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="PLANTS" tls:concept-id="uuid-46af35a4-b831-4eba-a0ba-3b4bbbd1c1f8" xml:id="uuid-12d2c7b4-0bb7-4d2b-b917-e060ae692c7c" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-d41a011b-349c-408a-94dd-4806ee5ca811">
<orth>莒</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">klaʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ki̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-283c7094-1300-458f-82f7-aa0b24ac923c">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>kind of plant</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-7699351a-2fab-41c2-a11b-c9b3b80f256a" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-d41a011b-349c-408a-94dd-4806ee5ca811">
<orth>莒</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jǔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">klaʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ki̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Jǔ 莒 (CHEN PAN 1969, 271-280)

Clan: Jǐ 己 (according to the Shì běn and the ZUO). According to the Shǐ jì (Qín běnjǐ4, the rulers of Jǔ had the surname Yíng 盈/嬴. According to the Guó yǔ (Zhèng yǔ), their surname was Cáo 曹.

Rank: Zǐ 子 (usual in both CQ and ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronze vessels, rulers of Jǔ sometimes refer to themselves as hóu 侯.

Founded: According to the Shìzú pǔ (and also to the Tōngzhì Shìzú lyè), the founder of Jǔ (the descendant of the mythical ruler Shǎo Hào 少昊) was Cíyù 茲與, who received his fief from King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王.

Destroyed: According to the Gǔ běn Zhúshū jìnián and to the Shǐ jì (Chǔ shìjiā and Liù guó nián biaǒ), Jǔ was destroyed by Chǔ 楚 in 431 B.C.  

Location: According to the Zhēngyì, Shìzú pu, and Lùshǐ Guó míng jì, the first capital of Jǔ was Jiègēn 介根 (also called Jìjīn 計斤), located probably in the southwestern part of the modern Jiāo 膲 district, Shandong province. Later, the capital shifted to Jǔ 莒 in the modern Jǔ 莒 district, southwestern Shandong province.

History: Jǔ was one of the states of the Eastern barbarian (Dōng Yí 東夷) origin. Although it did not belong to the strongest states it can be seen as the power of second order. Sometimes, it intervened into inner struggles of its more powerful neighbors, such as Qí 齊 or Lǔ 魯 (Lord Huán of Qí 齊桓公 fled during the struggle for power in Qí to Jǔ, and was introduced to the throne from that state). Particularly since the 20ties of the 6th century B.C., Jǔ was exposed to the attacks from Qí, and was forced to become its dependent state.
The large tomb uncovered in Dàdiàn 大店, Jǔ district, dating from the end of the 6th century B.C., and containing remains of over twenty human sacrifices, probably belonged to one of the rulers of Jǔ.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-9199601d-0a71-42e7-9e07-5284de3f4770" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>