<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-6d3e3a63-bd89-440d-a52a-2d2bf564890a" subtype="PC">
  <head>傷寒狐惑</head>
  <div type="definition">harm caused by cold with fox and delusion</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="shanghanhuhuo-98346" n="shanghanhuhuo傷寒狐惑">
      <form>
        <orth>傷寒狐惑</orth>
        <pron>Shang han hu huo</pron>
        <usg n="3">[3]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>harm caused by cold with fox and delusion</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Pathological Condition identical with hu huo 狐惑 , fox and delusion. Zhu bing yuan hou lun 諸病源候論 8: 傷寒狐惑候 , “Signs of harm caused by cold with fox and delusion :” 夫狐惑二病者，是 喉、陰之為病也。初得狀如傷寒，或因傷寒而變成斯病。其狀，默默欲 眠，目瞑不得眠，臥起不安。蟲食於喉咽為惑，食於陰肛為狐。惡飲 食，不欲聞食臭，其人面目翕赤翕黑翕白。食於上部其聲嗄，食於下部 其咽乾。此皆由濕毒氣所為也 , “Now, the two diseases ‘fox’ and ‘delusion’ are affecting the throat and the genital region respectively. At first they appear to be harm caused by cold, or there is harm caused by cold which gradually changes to become the present disease. The signs are sleepiness. [Patients] close their eyes but cannot sleep. They cannot calm down, neither while lying down nor when up. When bugs/worms gnaw on their throat, this is ‘delusion’; when they gnaw on the genital or anal region, this is ‘fox’. [Patients] have an aversion to beverages and food, and they cannot even stand the odors of food. Their face and eyes are at times red, at times dark, at times white. When [the bugs/worms] gnaw on [the patient’s] upper body parts, their voice is exclamatory. When they gnaw on the lower body parts, their throat is dry. All of this is brought forth by the qi of moisture poison”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>