<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-e92d2431-e3d7-4f3a-94b2-4cb6801f8a12" subtype="PC">
  <head>疝氣</head>
  <div type="definition">elevation-illness qi</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="shanqi-57792" n="shanqi疝氣">
      <form>
        <orth>疝氣</orth>
        <pron>Shan qi</pron>
        <usg n="92">[92]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>elevation-illness qi</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Pathological Condition</def>
        <def>a) of an item having entered the scrotum, with pain, sometimes ascending, sometimes descending. Jin gui yao lue 金匱要略 Mj: 陰狐疝氣者，偏有小大，時時上下，蜘蛛 散主之 , “In the case of yin-fox-type elevation-illness qi , with one side being small and the other being enlarged, and an alternating movement up- and downward, the powder with zhi zhu will control this”.</def>
        <def>b) Of a condition affecting the scrotum or a testicle. Wai tai mi yao 外台秘要 10: 療腎虛疝氣，腰膝冷疼，陰囊腫癢，狐陰 丸方 , “To cure kidney depletion and elevation-illness qi , swelling and itching of the scrotum, [use] the recipe for pills [to cure] ‘fox in the yin ’”.</def>
        <def>c) Identical with shan 疝 , elevation-illness. Shen nong ben cao jing 神農本草經 Substance Entry wu jia pi 五加皮：主心腹疝氣，腹 痛 , “It controls the heart and abdomen with elevation-illness qi , and abdominal pain”. In the Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 the first two meanings dominate. The image of a “fox” implies an item moving erratically inside the body – in this case in the scrotum. Ru men shi qin 儒門事親 explains: “The item [in the scrotum] is shaped like a tile. When [the patient] lies down to sleep, it enters the lower abdomen. When he walks and stands it leaves the lower abdomen and enters the scrotum. A fox leaves its den in the morning to urinate. It enters its den at night and will not urinate there. This elevation-illness comes out and withdraws, moves upward and downward, just like a fox”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>