<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-250a434c-34f3-4a2e-8a43-4c34f38a2eaa" n="6">
    <form>
        <orth>似</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="SEEM" tls:concept-id="uuid-4a314030-6c75-45c6-b793-c685a0b6f31c" xml:id="uuid-ba1581d1-08ce-4cb6-9b40-546cbf8f1c57" n="8">
            <form corresp="#uuid-b711b069-2680-4033-9f72-302d8ddc4c34">
<orth>似</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sì</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sɢlɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">zɨ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Sì 似 "apparently" always refers quite generally and colourlessly to things that are apparent only and not real, but the word also means "as if".
[GENERAL]
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-2b8d2cb0-ecc7-490c-9916-a8a9991e1e2d">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-3eaef22c-6bef-4126-93dd-a81945be2058">vt+S</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>give an impression that S; seem to indicate that S</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-01940dc6-0ced-48cf-90ad-28fd9a1f6d75" n="7">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-dd717b3f-0c98-4de8-bac6-2e4085805ef1">vt+V[0]</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>seem to V 似是而非 "be apparently this but not really it"</def>
            </sense>

<sense xml:id="uuid-14b2244a-1f8f-40dd-b224-4a1f8f70dd93" resp="#CH" tls:created="2021-03-02T00:08:38.177+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-2a0ded86-3b04-4488-bb7a-3efccfa35844">vadV</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>apparently</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="RELATION" tls:concept-id="uuid-87a0729f-0c38-4ded-950b-0cb39f37e6f9" xml:id="uuid-1b151641-00ab-472e-9516-4100ab972ee2" n="4">
        <form corresp="#uuid-b711b069-2680-4033-9f72-302d8ddc4c34">
            <orth>似</orth>
            <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sì</pron>
            <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc" resp="rec:baxter">ziX</pron>
            <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc" resp="rec:pan-wuyun">sɢlɯʔ</pron>
        </form>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-d44b2ef6-e02a-4a56-8b2e-f6e02aba5685" resp="#CH" tls:created="2022-04-12T01:12:02.65+09:00" n="4">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2a66fc1c-6671-47d2-bd04-cfd6ccae64b8">stative</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>be related to; correspond to</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="GIVE" tls:concept-id="uuid-ed1aeb49-abff-4167-a18e-60c0f2202d63" xml:id="uuid-b97153bf-e877-4f21-a76e-1e6299c2e0d8" n="8">
            <form corresp="#uuid-b711b069-2680-4033-9f72-302d8ddc4c34">
<orth>似</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sì</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sɢlɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">zɨ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-91cce1db-78cb-4b26-80cc-55ad3d26b0cf">ANDERL 2004B</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zǔtáng jí 祖堂集</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">320-324</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>In the Recorded Sayings literature of the Tang and Song periods the preposition si4 似 is attached between transitive verbs and their objects.931 The number of these verbs is quite restricted.</p>
<p/>
<p>There are three semantic groups of the main verb: (JIANG LANSHENG 2001: 266)</p>
<p>(a) V{give}, V{send}: e.g. so4ng 送  'to send',  ji4 寄  'to send',  we3i 委 'to entrust; delegate to',  fe1n 分 'distribute to'</p>
<p>(b) V{speak}: e.g. ju3 舉 (VTT) 'cite; bring up something to somebody', shuo1 說 'to speak to', hua4 話 'to speak to'</p>
<p>(c) V{show/guide}: Verbs expressing 'to guide; to show; to reveal';  e.g. zhi3 指 'indicate/show something to somebody', xia4n 現 'reveal something to somebody'.</p>
<p/>
<p>The object after si4 似 is usually indirect but there are also rare occurrences of a direct object (which makes a clear analysis of this preposition difficult). Only one object can follow the preposition. </p>
<p>There are several syntactic patterns in constructions with the preposition si4. </p>
<p>If the verb has two objects the direct object has to be 'disposed of' (with ba3 or jia1ng). The object after si4 can also function as a pivot and be the subject of a succeeding verb. Only rarely can the object after si4 be deleted. (JIANG LANSHENG 2001: 269)</p>
<p/>
<p>According to Jiang Lansheng the meaning/function of si4 differs according to the verb it is attached to:</p>
<p>(1) Corresponding to preposition yu3 與 (with verbs meaning 'to give'. In this case si4 also preserves some of its original meaning 'to give' while at the same time it introduces the recipient of the act of giving.</p>
<p/>
<p>(2) Corresponding to prepositions xia4ng 向 and dui4 對 with verbs indicating a speech act or expressing 'to show; to reveal' (however in the same function xia4ng and dui4 are preverbal!). In this usage Jiang Lansheng regards si4 as more grammaticalized  since it is emptied of its original meaning.</p>
<p/>
<p>(3.1) Occasionally V + si4 is followed by yu2 於 (PREP.OBJ.INDIR) or yu3 與 (PREP.OBJ.INDIR). In this case Jiang Lansheng regards si4 as a verbal suffix and not as a preposition. (only two examples of this usage in ZTJ)</p>
<p>709) ZTJ 3.057; WU: 229</p>
<p>“如何舉似於人？”</p>
<p>ru2-he2 ju3-si4 yu2 re2n</p>
<p>NPRO.QUESTlike what/cite/V.SUFF/PREP/person</p>
<p>"How shall [one] cite this to people?"</p>
<p>However, the interpretation as a disyllabic preposition is also possible.</p>
<p/>
<p>(3.2) V + si4 is not followed by an object but by the verb we4i 謂 'to address'. Also in this pattern Jiang Lansheng does not regard si4 as a preposition. [fn. 935:  Jiang Lansheng 2001: 27 gives two examples from He4-li2n yu4 lu4 鶴林玉露: 趙李仁舉似謂余曰：“此非論脈，乃是論學。”(jua4n 2) 公嘗舉似所作絕句示學者云。。。(jua4n 6)]</p>
<p/>
<p>(3.3) Also in the following example Jiang Lansheng regards si4 as a verbal suffix and the following noun a direct object 說似一物 saying a thing:</p>
<p>710) ZTJ 1.143; WU: 87</p>
<p>祖曰：The Patriarch said:</p>
<p>“什摩物與摩來?”"Which thing/being comes like that?"</p>
<p>對曰：[He] answered:</p>
<p>“說似一物即不中。” 936</p>
<p>I think that si4 in the above example is a main verb and the sentence should be translated: 'Saying it resembles a thing (being) won't be appropriate'.</p>
<p/>
<p>The other example cited by Jiang is also no illustration for si4 being followed by a direct object:</p>
<p>711) ZTJ 2.110; WU: 169</p>
<p>師示眾云：The master instructed the assembly, saying:</p>
<p>“明鏡相似，"It resembles a bright mirror;</p>
<p>胡來胡現，if a barbarian comes, a barbarian appears [in the mirror] </p>
<p>漢來漢現。”if a Chinese comes, a Chinese appears [in the mirror]."937</p>
<p>有人舉似玄沙，There was a person citing this to Xua2nsha1</p>
<p>玄沙云：and Xua2nsha1 said:</p>
<p>“明鏡來時作摩生？”"How about when a bright mirror comes?"</p>
<p>Here, the noun following si4 is clearly an indirect object (the NPR Xua2nsha1 玄沙). [fn. 938: However, Jiang Lansheng: 271 gives two examples where si4 seems to be a verbal suffix and not a preposition: 今日偶題題似著，不知題後更誰題 (杜荀鶴，題瓦棺寺真上人院矮檜寺)  空檐知與階何故，須把青苔滴穿。(楊萬里，三月三日雨作遣悶十絕句之三).]</p>
<p/>
<p>Occasionally si4 is seperated from the main verb by the direct object and appear proposed to the indirect object:</p>
<p/>
<p>V + OBJ.DIR + si4 似 + OBJ.INDIR [fn. 939: In this pattern it very much resembles yu3 與. Jiang cites two examples:...舉前話似之 ('cite the previous stament to him/them' 大慧普說) and 撒手似君無一物，徒勞漫說數千般。(CHUANXIN FAYAO).]</p>
<p/>
<p>According to Jiang Lansheng si4 can function as the main verb meaning 'to give'; however, there are only few examples of this usage.940 Jiang thinks that this usage as a main verb was was triggered by the usage as a preposition in which it resembles the preposition yu3 與. This would be a 'reverse' process of grammaticalization, in which a function word develops into a full verb by analogy. The original meaning as a main verb is 'to resemble'. What kind of connection is there between yu3 and si4? According to Jiang yu3 also had the meaning ru2 如 'be like' (GUANGYA) and si4 also had the meaning ru2. Since both words shared this meaning si4 also eventually developed the meaning 'to give'. This process took a long time, from the Han to the Tang period. By the same mechanism the question word he2-si4 何似 developed (from he2-yu3 何與, he2-ru2 何如, he2-ruo4 何若).941 This kind of development can be regarded as some kind of analogy, in this case not a very long lasting one since si4 in the meaning 'to give' was only short-lived.</p>
<p/>
<p>The usage of si4 似 in ZTJ:</p>
<p/>
<p>In ZTJ si4 似 is commonly used as a main verb in the meaing 'to resemble': </p>
<p>[fn. 942: si4 似 'be like; resemble' there are a few examples where si4 is followed by PREP yu2 於 (si4-yu2 似於). In the pattern X + si4 似 + Y, X and Y can be NP or VP. If understood X can be deleted. Occasionally si4 似 (VT+V)  has a verbal or sentential object (si4 似 VT+SENT) and in these cases can be translated with 'it seems that...' (ZTJ 4.090; WU: 338: “和尚太似不知。” "The preceptor really does not seem to know." ZTJ 1.167,09; WU: 102: “你從南岳來，似未見石頭曹溪心要耳。”"You come from Na2nyue4, it seems like you have not understood the mind-essential of Shi2to2u and Ca2oxi1." Si4 is also commonly used in the compound qia4-si4 恰似 (VT) 'be exactly like; be just like' often used in a rhetorical context and occasionally in the pattern qia4-si4 恰似 + X + xia1ng-si4 相似 'be exactly like X; be nothing else than X'.</p>
<p>ZTJ 5.058; WU: 403“什摩念經，恰似唱曲唱歌相似，得與摩不解念經。” "What about 'reciting the scripture', it is exactly like singing a drama or singing a song, if you do it like this you do not know how to recite the scriptures."]</p>
<p/>
<p>712) ZTJ 3.088; WU: 246</p>
<p>此事似個什摩? </p>
<p>ci3 shi4 si4 ge4 shi2-mo2</p>
<p>NPRO.DEMthis/matter/resemble/CLASS-NPRO.QUESTwhat</p>
<p>"What does this matter resemble?</p>
<p/>
<p>xia1ng-si4 相似 'be alike'. [fn. 943: Often in the pattern yo2u-ru2 猶如 + X + xia1ng-si4 相似 or ru2 如 + X + xia1ng-si4 相似 'resemble X; be like X' (X can be a VP or NP). Also used in the coverbal pattern X + yu3 與 (COV.OBJ.INDIR) + Y + xia1ng-si4 相似 偛 resembles Y; X is like Y'.]</p>
<p>713) ZTJ 2.049; WU: 138</p>
<p>“個個与他相似。”</p>
<p>ge4-ge4 yu3 ta1 xia1ng-si4</p>
<p>CLASS.REDUP&gt;QUANT/COV.OBJ.INDIR/NPRO3SG/mutually-resemble</p>
<p>"Everything resembles it."</p>
<p/>
<p>si4 似 (PREPOSITION)</p>
<p/>
<p>In ZTJ the preposition si4 connects only three verbs to their indirect objects: ju3 舉 'to lift &gt; to bring up; to cite'944, shuo1 說 'say; speak', and che2ng 呈 'to present; to submit (to a superior)'. [fn. 945: che2ng 呈 can also connect directly to the following object: ZTJ 1.084; WU: 54:“行者未知，第一座造偈呈師，。。。”"Does the postulant not know that the head monk made this stanza and presented it to the master,...". More often che2ng is followed by the direct object: ZTJ 3.144; WU: 284:“送書呈書了退身。”"Send the letter, and after submitting the letter withdraw/return."  By far the highest frequency has ju3-si4 舉似 (F: 119!) [fn. 946: ju3 舉 is also used in its original meaning 'to lift; to rais' and as quantifier before nouns (ju3 舉 (QUANT) + N (X) 'the whole of N(X)' as in ju3 she1n 舉身 'the whole body'. Ju3 舉 in the meaning 'to bring up; to cite' can also be directly followed by an object. In the following examples it is followed by a direct object: ZTJ 1.129; WU: 78: 國師頓世後，帝乃詔耽源，舉此因緣，問： 'After the National master had suddenly departed from the world the emperor then summoned Da1nyua2n and cited this case to him, asking:'. ZTJ 2.019; WU: 121: 其僧舉兩三則因緣， 'The monk cited several cases' The object after ju3 can also be deleted: ZTJ 1.179; WU: 107: 真覺大師舉問玄晤大師：'Grand Master Zhe1njue2 cited [this] and asked Grand Master Xua2nwu4:'   Occasionally the object of ju3 舉 (VT+SENT) can be a whole sentence: ZTJ 2.058; WU: 142: 師舉鹽官法會有一僧知有佛法，。。。 'the master brought up [the case] where in the dharma assembly of Ya2ngua1n there was a monk who knew the Buddha-dharma,...' Occasionally the indirect object is  not introduced by PREP si4 but preposed and marked by COV yu3 與 ZTJ 2.064; WU: 145: “..請上座與某舉看。”"I ask you, the head monk, to try to cite [a case] to me."  whereas si4 似 with the other two verbs is rather rare (see table). If ju3 舉 is directly followed by an object it is usually a direct object,  rarely an indirect object. Indirect objects are regularly introduced by si4 似:</p>
<p>714) ZTJ 2.088; WU: 157</p>
<p>其僧卻歸，舉似師，師云：</p>
<p>qi2 se1ng que4-gui1 ju3-si4 shi1 shi1 yu2n</p>
<p>NPRO.DEMthis/monk/retreat-return/cite/PREP.OBJ.INDIR/master/master/say</p>
<p>The monk returned, cited this to the master and the master said:</p>
<p/>
<p>There are only a few examples where ju3-si4 is followed by a direct object:</p>
<p>715) ZTJ 2.104; WU: 165</p>
<p>其僧卻歸雪峰，舉似前話。</p>
<p>qi2 se1ng que4-gui1 Xue3fe1ng ju3-si4 qia2n hua4</p>
<p>NPRO.DEMthis/monk/retreat-return/NPR/cite/PREP.OBJ.DIR/former/spech</p>
<p>The monk returned to Xue3fe1ng and cited [to him] the above speech/phrase.</p>
<p/>
<p>In sentences with multiple objects the direct object can be 'disposed of', marked by chi2 持 (COV.DISP), jia1ng 將 (COV.DISP), or ba3 把 (COV.DISP):</p>
<p>716) ZTJ 2.106; WU: 167</p>
<p>翠嵒持師語舉似T山</p>
<p>Cui4ya2n chi2 shi1 yu3 ju3-si4 Ca4nsha1n</p>
<p>NPR/COV.DISP/master/word/cite/PREP.OBJ.INDIR/NPR</p>
<p>Cui4ya2n cited the words of the master to Ca4nsha1n.</p>
<p/>
<p>Occasionally the object after ju3-si4 can be deleted. In contrast to Jiang Lansheng I do not think that in constructions V + si4 似 without the object si4 necessarily is a verbal suffix but that the object is deleted since it is easily understood from the context:</p>
<p>717) ZTJ 3.136,04; WU: 279</p>
<p>“莫錯舉似。”</p>
<p>mo4 cuo4 ju3-si4</p>
<p>NEG.IMP/ADVmistakenly/cite/PREP.OBJ?</p>
<p>"Do not cite [this/this to him] in a wrong way."</p>
<p/>
<p>In the following example ju3-si4 is followed by yu2 於 (PREP.OBJ.INDIR):</p>
<p>718) ZTJ 4.008; WU: 290</p>
<p>“與摩則終不錯舉似於人。”</p>
<p>yu3-mo2 ze2 zho1ng bu4 cuo4 ju3-si4 yu2 re2n</p>
<p>be like/CONJthen/in the end/NEG/ADVfalsely/cite/-V.SUFF(PREP)?/RREP.OBJ.INDIR/person</p>
<p>"If it is like this in the end do not erroneously cite [this] to people."</p>
<p/>
<p>In the following example the object is deleted:</p>
<p>719) ZTJ 2.017; WU: 120</p>
<p>有人舉問雲居：There was a person citing this to Yu2nju1:</p>
<p>“洞山與摩道，"Do4ngsha1n talking like this,</p>
<p>意作摩生？”what does he mean?"</p>
<p>居云：Ju1 said:</p>
<p>“說似也。”"I have already told [this to you]."</p>
<p/>
<p/>
<p>TABLE WITH FREQUENCIES SEE p.324</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3c9dd412-fdde-4828-bcb7-ea44cac5d45f" n="8">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-97424691-5023-4a2e-b90f-d60a1e3b5673">vt[0]oN.postadV</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>vernacular preposition introducing the recipient of a speech act (most commonly in 舉似 'cite (something) to N') (rarely the main verb can also belong to the semantic group 'to give'); also: talk about; say something about</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="AS IF" tls:concept-id="uuid-b019dfb7-1d6d-4e8d-9b24-7947c71824ff" xml:id="uuid-2a8e2021-1082-4501-8e20-21108255016f" n="11">
        <form corresp="#uuid-b711b069-2680-4033-9f72-302d8ddc4c34">
            <orth>似</orth>
            <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sì</pron>
            <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc" resp="rec:baxter">ziX</pron>
            <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc" resp="rec:pan-wuyun">sɢlɯʔ</pron>
        </form>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-8d15a56e-e5ce-47f5-95a5-6ee5ce87f50c" resp="#CH" tls:created="2022-04-10T18:20:25.103+09:00" n="4">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-97424691-5023-4a2e-b90f-d60a1e3b5673">vt[0]oV1.postadV2</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-04-10T18:45:34.835+09:00">嗒焉似喪其耦"feel lost as if one had lost one's counterpart": to V2 as if V1-ing</def>
        </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-8319c345-35c7-45df-9aef-9c0aec7831f4" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-97424691-5023-4a2e-b90f-d60a1e3b5673">vt[0]oN.postadV</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-9a78c504-5bbc-4d23-b8c5-045bbcfd239d">subjects compared</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-04-10T18:50:14.993+09:00">屏氣似不息者"block the air as if one was not breathing": like; as if</def>
            </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-93bf014e-7328-479f-bf01-4e7328179fb1" resp="#CH" tls:created="2022-04-10T19:00:57.53+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-db89cde9-dc4f-4735-9383-e285c6a94876">vt0oV(0)</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>而似不自己"It is as if it does not originate in oneself": it is as if it does not V</def>
        </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-c5f47b9c-1082-4ec6-b47b-9c10820ec619" resp="#CH" tls:created="2022-04-11T03:02:21.971+09:00" n="2">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c2215d92-0f3d-4b46-a15d-920f3d9b4618">vtoV[0]</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>look as if it was V-ing</def>
        </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-65d4375e-8a77-4c28-94ec-ee7f438187e2" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-812d11f1-9567-49dc-b3f6-bfe890cd7ed9">vtoS.postadV</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>as if</def>
            </sense>
    </entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="CORRECT" tls:concept-id="uuid-9ab78015-0fad-44a9-a51a-a870f5602d88" xml:id="uuid-7d2648ac-a59c-4078-84ac-164c17d8a150" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-b711b069-2680-4033-9f72-302d8ddc4c34">
<orth>似</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sì</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sɢlɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">zɨ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e6976757-5188-4caf-903b-17802a1f08e1" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>be plausible???</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="RESEMBLE" tls:concept-id="uuid-031779e4-5e29-4947-9e9f-b5edc803c7be" xml:id="uuid-1c4683fe-d5bb-4b19-b4bb-54f84fd4fb53" n="119">
            <form corresp="#uuid-b711b069-2680-4033-9f72-302d8ddc4c34">
<orth>似</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sì</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sɢlɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">zɨ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Sì 似 and the later and rarer xiàng 像 are ungrammaticalised full verbs meaning typically "to resemble in appearance only".
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-35311e48-96b2-42b5-a1cf-09771d76925a" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-76be1df4-3d73-4e5f-bbc2-729542645bc8">nab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-4e92cef6-5753-4eed-a76b-7249c223316f">feature</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>similarity 有似於</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-70e63050-75cb-438f-812b-86c117bf142f" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-9fda0181-1777-4402-a30f-1a136ab5fde1">npost-N</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>what resembles N, the likes of N</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-da404155-9694-4765-853f-800268fd97ff" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fed035db-e7bd-4d23-bd05-9698b26e38f9">vadN</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>similar</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ce0a0ad5-25cf-41c1-89d8-f9980fdfbd75">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-e64a7a95-b54b-4c94-9d6d-f55dbf079701">vt(oN)</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-04-11T23:22:48.658+09:00">resemble something contextually determinate</def>
            </sense>

<sense xml:id="uuid-61f64602-b12d-4bed-9545-95c250549013" n="6">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-739c24ae-d585-4fff-9ac2-2547b1050f16">vt+prep+N</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-be3974c6-dfc8-4fa3-b974-c6dfc88fa3f5">in appearance</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
  <def>resemble</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-398d2a3a-06b8-4e29-ae3d-96fa756f2f3f" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-7cd0c6a6-f273-4571-8b9a-4677eb46175b">vt+V1.postadV2</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>V2 as if V1-ing</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6416086c-c743-44fb-9f06-b36137f9f5eb">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-9e8c327b-579d-4514-8c83-481fa450974a">vtoN.adV</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>like</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-63f2395c-2ab2-4371-9729-3896cceea78d" n="18">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-bda34220-297f-474c-a342-20297fe74cd0">figurative, act</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-04-10T18:34:49.404+09:00">function like; behave like, act like; resemble [be simliar in one's actions, effects and/or achievements]</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-87370f3d-fcd7-41fd-ba7b-79918eac3000">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-b110bae1-02d5-4c66-ad13-7c04b3ee3ad9">mathematical term</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>CHEMLA 2003:</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c346aa63-dc92-44f9-a8ac-480cfcb782bd" n="60">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-be3974c6-dfc8-4fa3-b974-c6dfc88fa3f5">in appearance</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-04-12T00:52:46.906+09:00">子期似王"Ziqi resembled the king": look like; be similar in appearance</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b30194e5-2418-437c-9667-a8bac3a3bd73" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a7e8eabf-866e-42db-88f2-b8f753ab74be">v[adN]</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>similar things</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-96ea0b93-be3a-4257-aa0b-93be3a92571f" resp="#CH" tls:created="2020-04-10T01:06:48.81+09:00" n="6">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-6fe4438e-50e1-4c1f-8b7a-c24a0f417fb5">vtoNab</tls:syn-func>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-7579a42d-5694-455f-917c-626d5918a255">relational</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
            <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-04-11T03:18:14.796+09:00">似不之也"is like not understanding it": resemble</def>
        </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-1e9da9ef-72e7-484f-9da9-ef72e7a84f2d" resp="#CH" tls:created="2022-04-10T18:52:46.859+09:00" n="4">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-6cdc4c68-0873-43f8-b26f-64dc135ee58c">vt[0]oN.adV</tls:syn-func>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-9a78c504-5bbc-4d23-b8c5-045bbcfd239d">subjects compared</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>V resembling in so doing the N</def>
        </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-766482b3-a2a8-49d7-a482-b3a2a8d9d7ee" resp="#CH" tls:created="2022-04-11T23:11:55.328+09:00" n="14">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-30c297df-62db-42f6-8297-df62dbd2f639">in essence</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
            <def resp="#CH" updated="2022-09-25T00:36:05.538+09:00">resemble (in essence), be like, have the qualities of</def>
        </sense>
        <sense xml:id="uuid-b6ccdf39-ea26-4f64-8cdf-39ea263f649f" resp="#CH" tls:created="2022-04-12T01:39:31.146+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-739c24ae-d585-4fff-9ac2-2547b1050f16">vt+prep+N</tls:syn-func>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-30c297df-62db-42f6-8297-df62dbd2f639">in essence</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>resemble</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
</superEntry>