<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-221cd20a-d91c-4726-9cd2-0ad91c97263e" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>三衣</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="BUDDHIST GARMENT" tls:concept-id="uuid-811258cf-a100-4c80-ac25-2dea8ef6182b" xml:id="uuid-6fe125da-2073-45d1-9f2b-11ee727ffb3b" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-3b81e026-2aee-45cd-b686-7bab8c7046b3 #uuid-28e4431a-02b5-45a4-82d2-9f49e5f3b29e">
<orth>三衣</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sān yī</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">saam qɯl</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">sɑm ʔɨi</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-2389c812-8053-4187-8f7a-19f6e856050f">FOGUANG</ref>
<title>佛光大辭典 Fóguāng dàcídiǎn The Foguang Dictionary of Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">551a-c</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-9d1f23b7-b94b-41d4-97fb-9ed2d214e466">KIESCHNICK 2003</ref>
<title>The Impact of Buddhim on Chinese Material Culture</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">89ff</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-31a7c534-8774-40c9-8ce8-b6a25ac625cd">YANG WEIZHONG 2000</ref>
<title>中國佛教百科全書 Zhōngguó fójiào bǎikē quánshū Encyclopedic Book Collection on Chinese Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">236-238</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-293d7298-39ea-40d5-8f4d-4735fd3b5249" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: the three monks' robes (typical for an Indian monk); skr. trīni cīvarāṇi; pali tīni cīvarāṇi (already in Indian Buddhist texts the typical garment for monks was described of consisting of three items: a rectangular piece of cloth which was wrapped around the waist, covering the lower part of the body (this inner robe, skr. antarvāsa, āntuóhuì 安陀會) was always worn, also during periods of work; another piece of cloth was draped over the left shoulder (upper garment, skr. uttarāsaṇga, yùduōluósēng 鬱多羅僧), covering the upper part of the body; the third robe, the outer garment (skr. saṃgāṭi, sēngqiélí 僧伽梨) was usually worn when the monk was in the public, for examples on begging tours; although the basic design of this outfit is quite simple, there were many complex variations concerning these robes and the outer robe could be made several strips (tiáo 條) of cloth (usually 5, 7, 9, 13, 15, or even more; each stip consists of several patches, gé 隔); there were also careful descriptions how to sew a robe, using different  kinds of stiching technics; in China there were many controversies concerning the proper style of monks' robes; in the course of time the robe was highly charged with symbolism the the three robes sometimes represented different sets of Buddhist terms (e.g. the three poisons greed, anger, and ignorance and their respective elimination; another symbolic connection were the three realms 三界 or the three assemblis 三會). There is evidence that the original Indian style of robe was brought to China, but underwent changes in the course of time, and there was an adaption to Chinese customs, climate, etc. Gradually, there deveoped the sleeved robe, typical of East-Asian Buddhism, usually combined with trousers; at the end of the Tang - after having been criticised for long periods of time - this style of robe seems to have been firmly established; the outer robe - originally also a rectangular piece of cloth - became heavily charged with symbolism and were still made of a number a patches; however, although originally symbolizing the poverty of a monk, often the outer robe is China (and later Japan) was eventually made of especially fine and colorful materials, becoming a status symbol for high-ranking priests. In order to hold the robe in place, eventually a ring and ribbon (gouniu 鉤紐) was attached to it. In medieval China there was also an extended discussion about the use of silk for monks' robes since the production of silk involved the taking of life; however, eventually the use of silk was firmly established since it also was the easiest obtainable material)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>