<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-2787e10b-4910-4f47-87e1-0b49105f4748" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>南燕</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-7f272262-d8f6-41af-bc9f-555dc8ddc837" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-b420baa9-4b24-4965-9a08-7ef933d10f54 #uuid-469a7f78-1e03-4675-bb6f-535f87df6708">
<orth>南燕</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">nán yān</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">noom qeen</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">nəm ʔen</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Nán Yān 南燕 (usually called only Yān 燕; distinguish from the Běi Yān , which was originally written as 郾) (CHEN PAN 1969, 375-378)

Clan: Jí 姞 (according to the Jìn yǔ section of the Guó yǔ; Yān Jí 燕姞, the wife of Duke Wén of Zhèng 鄭文公, is mentioned in the ZUO, Xuan 3).

Rank: Bó 伯 (occurs in the ZUO).

Founded: According to the legendary tradition (recorded in the Jìn yǔ chapter of the Guó yǔ and in the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì), the lineages with Jí surname were descendants of the mythical Yellow Emperor 黃帝. In the ZUO (Xuan 3; 606 B.C.), the legendary ancestor of Nán Yàn is called Bóyōu 伯 (or Bóshū 伯儵).

Destroyed: Unknown. The state is mentioned in the ZUO in 674 B.C. (Zhuang 20) and in 500 B.C. (Ding 10). By that period, it was still in existence.

Location: In the northeastern part of the modern Yánjīn 延津 area, Henan province (CHEN PAN locates it into the Henan province, Wèihuī fǔ 衛輝府, Zuòchéng 胙城 district; is it identical????). 

History: Nán Yàn was a small and weak state, which relied mainly on alliances with its more powerful neighbors. In the beginning of the period recorded in the CQ, we find Nán Yàn participating in the struggles among the eastern and central states, which resulted into a defeat of the armies of Qí 齊, Sòng 宋, Wèi 衛, and Nán Yàn by the coalition of Zhèng 鄭, Lǔ 魯, and Jǐ 紀 in 699 B.C. (Huan 13). Later, Nán Yàn several times appears in the ZUO; for instance, in 675 B.C. (Zhuang 19), it intervened into the struggle in the Zhōu 周 royal court.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-985adc4b-7953-4907-ad63-b26140d00016">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Nán Yàn 南燕 (usually called only Yàn 燕; distinguish from the Běi Yàn, which was originally written as 郾 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 375-378)Clan: Jí 姞 (according to the Jìn yǔ section of the Guó yǔ; Yàn Jí 燕姞, the wife of Duke Wén of Zhèng 鄭文公, is mentioned in the ZUO, Xuan 3).Rank: Bó 伯 (occurs in the ZUO). Founded: According to the legendary tradition (recorded in the Jìn yǔ chapter of the Guó yǔ and in the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì), the lineages with Jí surname were descendants of the mythical Yellow Emperor 黃帝. In the ZUO (Xuan 3; 606 B.C.), the legendary ancestor of Nán Yàn is called Bóyōu 伯 (or Bóshū 伯儵 ). Destroyed: Unknown. The state is mentioned in the ZUO in 674 B.C. (Zhuang 20) and in 500 B.C. (Ding 10). By that period, it was still in existence. Location: In the northeastern part of the modern Yánjīn 延津 area, Henan province (CHEN PAN locates it into the Henan province, Wèihuī fǔ 衛輝府, Zuòchéng 胙城 district; is it identical????). History: Nán Yàn was a small and weak state, which relied mainly on alliances with its more powerful neighbors. In the beginning of the period recorded in the CQ, we find Nán Yàn participating in the struggles among the eastern and central states, which resulted into a defeat of the armies of Qí 齊, Sòng 宋, Wèi 衛, and Nán Yàn by the coalition of Zhèng 鄭, Lǔ 魯, and Jǐ 紀 in 699 B.C. (Huan 13). Later, Nán Yàn several times appears in the ZUO; for instance, in 675 B.C. (Zhuang 19), it intervened into the struggle in the Zhōu 周 royal court. </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>