<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-2e8d32c0-7e75-4d5f-8d32-c07e754d5f65" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>鳥窠</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="ZEN MONKS" tls:concept-id="uuid-9c34821d-5c94-4128-96d8-9a46f9471f92" xml:id="uuid-c2d14561-7c0c-4b0b-bb8e-98dba66a9e59" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-5d692988-1db7-4739-817c-1ad0a8824a32 #uuid-1e555654-682c-4a06-a38c-4c659d8bbb0e">
<orth>鳥窠</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">niǎo kē</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ntɯɯwʔ khlool</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">teu khʷɑ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-91cce1db-78cb-4b26-80cc-55ad3d26b0cf">ANDERL 2004B</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zǔtáng jí 祖堂集</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">584</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>Preceptor Nia3oke4鳥窠 (NPR) lived from 741-824. His original family name was Da4oli2n 道林 (NPR) but he was also called To1ngxi2ng 通行 (NPR). In SGSZ there is a record of the monk Yua2nxiu1 圓修 (736-833) who was also called Nia3oke1 鳥窠 (SGSZ, T.50/2061: 774c18). He was a successor in the line of Ba3izha4ng 百杖 and does not have any connection to Da4oli2n.  Da4oli2n derives his fame from a dialogue he had with the poet Ba2iju1yi4 白居易 (772-846) (see FENG ZUOMIN 1981, vol.2: 595).</p>
<p/>
<p>According to JINGDECHUANDENGLU  he was a person from Fu2ya2ng in Ha2ng province. His family name was Pa1n 潘. At the age of nine he renounced home and at the age of twenty-one he took the precepts in the Guo3yua4n 果願 monastery in Xing province. In the Xi1mi2ng 西明 monastery in Cha2ng'a1n he studied under Dharma-master Fu4li3 復禮 the AVATAMSAKA and the QIXINLUN. Later on he visited Cha2n master Ji4ngsha1n Guo2yi1 徑山國一 and became a successor in the lineage of Niu2to2u 牛頭. Afterwards he returned to the south.</p>
<p/>
<p>JINGDECHUANDENGLU, T.51/2076: 230b3-7: 杭州鳥窠道林禪師。本郡富陽人也。姓潘氏。母朱氏夢日光入口。因而有娠。及誕異香滿室。遂名香光焉。九歲出家。二十一於v州果願寺受戒。後詣長安西明寺復禮法師。學華嚴經起信論。復禮示以真妄頌俾修禪那。</p>
<p>WUDENG:  杭州鳥窠道林禪師,本郡富陽人也.姓潘氏.母朱氏,夢日光入囗,因而有娠.及誕,異香滿室,遂名香光.九歲出家,二十一於荊州果願寺受戒.後詣長安西明寺復禮法師學華嚴經、起信論禮示以真妄頌,俾修禪那。</p>
<p/>
<p>The name Nia3oke1 鳥窠 'Bird Burrow' derives from the following story which is recorded in JDCDL, T.51/2076:230b13-15:  'Afterwards he saw that there was a tall pine on Mt. Ta4iwa4ng. Its branches and leaves were luxuriant and covering [the tree] like a plate [?]. He then dwelled (lit. perched) on top [of the tree]. Therefore his comtemporaries called him Cha2n Master 'Bird Burrow' (後見秦望山有長松，枝葉繁茂盤屈如蓋。遂棲止其上。故時人謂之鳥窠禪師。).</p>
<p/>
<p>According to a note in JINGDECHUANDENGLU: 53a his canonical name (shi4 諡) was Yua2nxiu1 圓修 (NPR) ('Perfected Cultivation'. </p>
<p/>
<p>In SGSZ, T.50/2061: 774c9-28 there is a 'Record on Yua2nxiu1 of Mt. Ta4iwa4ng in Ha2ngzho1u of the Ta2ng' (唐杭州秦望山圓脩傳). Also in this biograhical entry  there is a similar story on the background of his name being Nia3oke1 (見秦望山峻極之勢有長松枝繁結蓋。遂棲止于松巔。時感鵲復巢於橫枝。物我都忘。羽族馴狎。由玆不下近四十秋。每一太守到任。則就瞻仰。號鳥窠禪師焉。).  However the remaining biographic information on this monk differs from the entries in ZTJ and JDCDL (according to SGSZ this monk lived from 735-833, took his precepts in the So1ngya2ng Hui4sha4n 嵩陽會善 monastery and was a dharma-heir of Ba3izha4ng Hua2iha3i 百丈懷海). It is therefore doubtful whether the two monks are identical or not (possibly the biograhical data of two monks were mixed up). See Matsubara/Koromogawa/Ogawa 2002: 61-61 and Ui 1935, vol.2: 362).</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d6f2b7f1-06c7-4d31-80a0-eada25a15248" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: Niǎokē (741-824) is a Chán master in the lineage of Niúoú 牛頭 - Jìngshān Guóyī 徑山國一</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>