<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-2209755d-8113-4d46-8975-5d81134d46c3" n="3">
    <form>
        <orth>巴</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="BARBARIAN" tls:concept-id="uuid-7886441a-3747-4a31-9432-28601e29f941" xml:id="uuid-9da8dae5-2518-4ebf-8788-02595c5e0cb6" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-fe234715-d0db-48e2-8bda-e382d4a20ea8">
<orth>巴</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">bā</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">praa</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">pɣɛ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Bā 巴 is a name of an ancient ethnic group and polity in the area of modern Chongqing. According to the historical texts, the leader of Bā was enfeooffed by the king Wu of Zhōu (&gt;Zhōu Wǔ wáng 周武王) when this had defeated the &gt;Shāng 商. When &gt;Qín 秦 conquered this area, it established there the commandery of Bā 巴君.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-abdc861f-d1dc-41f3-98fd-e536938c3b41">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>ancient people in Sichuan Province.</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="SNAKE" tls:concept-id="uuid-92a331ef-692c-4ff2-b974-dc1d6c57c485" xml:id="uuid-27acae9e-ba41-44f5-a40a-e4bef37790c0" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-fe234715-d0db-48e2-8bda-e382d4a20ea8">
<orth>巴</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">bā</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">praa</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">pɣɛ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-5cf41a68-4f12-48a2-90b0-331151878257">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>giant snake; 4.3</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-107b36ce-3ea0-435a-89a9-391d295feb25" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-fe234715-d0db-48e2-8bda-e382d4a20ea8">
<orth>巴</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">bā</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">praa</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">pɣɛ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Bā 巴 (CHEN PAN 1969, 436-446)

Clan: Jī 姬 (the wife of the Chǔ king Gōng 楚恭王, which is mentioned in the ZUO, Zhao 13, was called Bā Jī 巴姬). In the traditional Chinese historiography, there appear also other opinions concerning the surname of the Bā rulers. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì, the rulers of Bā had Yíng 嬴 surname; in the same text, there is mentioned another Bā with Fēng 風 surname. Yú dì guǎng jì states that Bā was of the same surname as Shāng 商 kings, i.e. Zǐ 子. The matter is complicated, and it is possible that there were more states of that name. Nonetheless, the main Bā in Sichuan should have been of Jī 姬 surname. 

Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the Huáyáng guó zhì).

Founded: Again, there are different opinions concerning the origins of Bā. According to the Huáyáng guó zhì, Bā of Jī surname was established by King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王.

Destroyed: In 316 B.C. by Qín 秦 (according to the Shǐ jì - Qín běnjì, Liù guó niánbiǎo, and Zhāng Yí zhuàn chapters - and to the Huáyáng guó zhì). According to the Zhànguó cè (Qín cè), it was conquered in 329 B.C.

Location: There are some problems concerning the precise location of Bā, and it is quite probable that its center shifted several times (what is also stated in the Huáyáng guó zhì). Hàn shū dì lǐ zhì and Du's commentary to the ZUO locate the state of Bā into the area of the modern Bā 巴 district in the eastern part of Sichuan province. Lù shǐ Guó míng jì suggested that it was located in the modern Nánchōng 南充 district in Sichuan. According to Mēng Wéntōng, Bā was located in the Lǎngzhōng 閬中 district of the same province. Tóng Shūyè on the basis of the records in the ZUO and Zhànguó cè (which suggest that Bā could not have been too far from the capital of Chǔ 楚 and from the states of Dèng 鄧 and Yōng 庸) supposed that the center of Bā was located somewhere in the area of the Hàn 漢 River valley in the southeastern part of Shǎnxī province. This view seems to be quite reasonable; however, we probably should locate a broader area of the Bā activities somewhere between the southeastern Shǎnxī, southwestern Henan, northwestern Hubei, and northeastern Sichuan.    

History: Bā played not an unimportant role in the history of the Chunqiu and Zhanguo periods, particularly as a rival of the neighboring powerful state of Chǔ 楚. In 676 B.C. (Zhuang 18), armies of Bā even reached the gates of the Chǔ capital, but were defeated in the following year. Another great siege was laid on Chǔ by Bā in 477 B.C., but the result was again the defeat of Bā. In the 4th century B.C., Bā became an ally of the state of Qín against the states of Shǔ 蜀 and Chǔ. However, after the conquest of Shǔ, Qín also annexed Bā in 316 B.C. (or 329 B.C.).
 Bā was known as a semi-barbarian or even barbarian state, which differed from the states of Huá Xià 華夏, or Zhū Xià 諸夏 (in spite of its proclaimed Jī姬 - i.e. Zhōu 周 - origins). It probably had quite distinctive culture and customs, and some archaeological finds from the eastern part of Sichuan are mainly by Chinese archaeologists labeled under the general term of the Bā culture.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c598c2d1-474e-4943-95ee-fe61324c50f1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Bā 巴 (CHEN PAN 1969, 436-446) Clan: Jī 姬  </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>