<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-2db2603d-b513-4305-b260-3db51353050c" n="3">
    <form>
        <orth>晉</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="RISE" tls:concept-id="uuid-a7f925e3-d34f-475e-8f70-05c476625af7" xml:id="uuid-d1a78119-1843-4efe-a669-fcfe401769b0" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4b0e1c9a-44d5-48ef-a7dd-0700e314df76">
<orth>晉</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jìn</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tsins</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tsin</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Jìn 晉 is a very formal term referring to the rising of something in the ranks of a hierarchy.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6047283e-66ad-4f61-8dc4-f8f39c70654f">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-3d95d354-0c16-419f-9baf-f1f6cb6fbd07">change</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>formal: rise in rank</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="CHINESE LANGUAGE" tls:concept-id="uuid-f101e14d-9b02-4646-8a6d-135c509b55cd" xml:id="uuid-ac6fc5a1-8516-4ada-91a2-bbef1b6bdc05" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4b0e1c9a-44d5-48ef-a7dd-0700e314df76">
<orth>晉</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jìn</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tsins</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tsin</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-77856124-81c2-4e7b-ad60-788f717faa70">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-76be1df4-3d73-4e5f-bbc2-729542645bc8">nab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2ef405b2-627b-4f29-940b-848d5428e30e">social</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>(language of) the Jìn (dynasty)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-2f68521c-09b5-4bb1-b45b-01f3c1a2ee61" n="4">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4b0e1c9a-44d5-48ef-a7dd-0700e314df76">
<orth>晉</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jìn</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tsins</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tsin</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Jìn 晉 (also called Táng 唐 - this designation sometimes appears in the inscriptions on the bronzes - or - after capital - Yì 翼) (CHEN PAN 1969, 68-98) 

Clan: Jī 姬.

Rank: Hóu 侯 (common designation in CQ and ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronzes, rulers of Jìn are sometimes referred to as gōng 公.

Founded: The first ruler of Jìn was &gt;Tángshū Yú 唐叔虞, the son of &gt;Zhōu Wǔ wáng 周武王.

Destroyed: The power of the rulers of Jìn was gradually declining during the 6th century B.C. in a favor of important aristocratic families. In 453 B.C. the families of &gt;Zhào 趙, &gt;Wèi 魏 and &gt;Hán 韓 in fact divided the state. To the dukes of Jìn was left only small territory in the neighbourhood of a capital, which was definitely eliminated in 376 B.C.  　

Location: Located in the southwestern part of the modern Shanxi province, also controlled the part of northeastern and northwestern Henan and southwestern Hebei.
The first capital ruled by Tángshū was Jìn 晉 or Dà Xià 大夏(according to ZUO - Zhao 1). Within the traditional Chinese historiography, there were different opinions as one regards its location. According to the Jìn shìjiā zhēngyì (quoting Kuò dì zhì) and to the Máo shī Táng fēng pǔ, it was located in the area of the modern Tàiyuán 太原 in Shānxī province. However, it seems to be highly improbable with regard to the fact that that area was conquered by Jìn just in the 6th century B.C. Much more reasonable seems seems to be the opinion (expressed by Gù Yánwǔ on the basis of the Jìn shìjiā chapter of SHI) locating the first centers into the are of the southwestern part of Shānxī province, mainly to the modern Linfen district. It is also the area, where important cemeteries belonging to the Jìn aristocracy of the western Zhōu and early Chunqiu periods were uncovered.
According to the Current Zhúshū jìnián, in 812 B.C. (11th year of the reign of the Zhōu King Xuān 周宣王), Marquis Xiàn of Jìn 晉獻侯 shifted its capital to Jiàng 絳 (also called Yì 翼, to the southeast of the modern Yìchéng 翼城 in the Shanxi province). After 679 B.C. the capital was moved to Qūwò 曲沃 (to the east of the modern Wénxǐ 聞喜 in the Shanxi province), then - during the reign of Lord Xiàn 晉獻公 (675-653 B.C.) - again to Jiàng 絳. In 584 B.C. (Cheng 7), the capital of Jìn shifted to Xīntián 新田 (sometimes also called also Jiàng 絳; modern Hóumǎ 侯馬 in Shānxī). For the history of the capitals see also Qū 1991: 353-377.

5. Jìn became a powerful state in the end of the 9th and in the beginning of the 8th century B.C., after its victories over neighboring barbarians. Marquis Wén of Jìn 晉文侯 (780-746 B.C.; do not confuse with the later hegemon) even successfully intervened into the struggles for the Zhōu royal throne after 770 B.C. After the civil war which lasted from 739 B.C. to 679 B.C. the power in the state was seized by the branch lineage of the ruling clan ruling in Qūwò. Thanks to the large expansion, Jìn quickly became one of the most powerful states of the Chunqiu period. In 632 B.C. the duke Wen (&gt;Jìn Wén gōng 晉文公) defeated the powerful southern state of &gt;Chǔ 楚 and was enfeoffed a hegemon (bà 霸) by the Zhou king. The struggle for the hegemony between Chǔ and Jìn then lasted without final decision till 546 B.C. when status quo was recognized at the famous conference held at Sòng 宋. The power of the rulers of Jìn was gradually declining during the 6th century B.C. in a favor of important aristocratic families. In 453 B.C. the families of &gt;Zhào 趙, &gt;Wèi 魏 and &gt;Hán 韓 in fact divided the state. To the dukes of Jìn was left only small territory in the neighbourhood of a capital, which was definitely eliminated in 376 B.C.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-058a748a-e331-43f4-a856-3bede0eacb6e" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>