<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="del-notes-2022-07-crypt">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Recorded items for month 2022-07</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by members of the TLS project</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Initially created: <date>2022-07-19T17:26:32.24+09:00</date>.</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Items</head>
                <p xml:id="del-2022-07-start">
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-f3219f5d-2da3-4e80-88bc-cdb6f2957a65" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-19T17:26:32.24+09:00">
<p>1. The notion of hospitality to strangers in need and to travellers passing through which is so important in ancient Greece is not as prominent in China as it was in Greece. The closest one can come is hòu 厚 "meet with polite respect and generous hospitality" (ant. báo 薄 "fail to treat with generous hospitality and proper respect").</p>
<p>2. Lǐ 禮 "show polite respect to" (ant. màn 慢 "treat without proper respect") refers to ritualised respect which is the Chinese Way of hospitality and does connote conviviality. See also RESPECT.</p>
        </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-47b2ee40-362a-4b33-8fe8-d9c0520eca15" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-19T17:31:30.46+09:00">
<p>1. The current general term for everything relating to the system of ritual propriety is lǐ 禮. However the term can also be used to refer to individual prescribed rituals.</p>
<p>2. Yí 儀 refers to prescribed concrete ritual procedures, as typically described in Yí lǐ 儀禮.</p>
        </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-47b2ee40-362a-4b33-8fe8-d9c0520eca15" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-19T17:33:42.825+09:00">
                        <p>1. The current general term for everything relating to the system of ritual propriety is lǐ 禮. The term refers concretely to ritual ceremonies, to ritual decorum more generally, and also to any ritual propriety in social behaviour</p>
                        <p>2. Yí 儀 refers to prescribed concrete ritual procedures, as typically described in Yí lǐ 儀禮.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-04ab421a-05e3-4379-8782-3b7022ec584b" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-19T18:39:34.508+09:00">
<p>1. The general term for positive appraisal of any kind in Chinese is shàn 善 (ant. è 惡 "bad").</p>
<p>2. Rén 仁 (ant. cán 殘 "unfeeling") refers to kind-heartedness as an attitude directed towards moral behaviour. See BENEVOLENCE</p>
<p>3. Lián 廉 (ant. tān 貪 "greedy for bribery gifts") refers to moral probity and impeccability.</p>
<p>4. Zhí 直 (ant. qǔ 曲 "devious") refers to moral straightforwardness and uprightness.</p>
<p>5. Zhōng 衷 (ant. xié 邪 "wicked") refers to devoted uprightness of character. See also EARNEST</p>
<p>6. Qīng 清 (ant. zhuó 濁 "defiled and corrupt") can be used to refer to moral purity.</p>
<p>7. Shú 淑 is a highly poetic word referring to admirable moral qualities in general, typically in women.</p>
<p>8. Jūn zǐ 君子 (ant. xiǎo rén 小人 "petty man") refers to high moral qualities, especially in men.</p>
<p>9. Zāng 臧 (pí 否 "good-for-nothing") is a neutral unemotional objective term for goodness.</p>
        </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-04ab421a-05e3-4379-8782-3b7022ec584b" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-19T18:42:24.814+09:00">
                        <p>1. The general term for positive appraisal of capacities of any kind is shàn 善 (ant. è 惡 "bad").</p>
                        <p>2. Rén 仁 (ant. cán 殘 "unfeeling") refers to kind-heartedness as an attitude directed towards moral behaviour. See BENEVOLENCE</p>
                        <p>3. Lián 廉 (ant. tān 貪 "greedy for bribery gifts") refers to moral probity and impeccability.</p>
                        <p>4. Zhí 直 (ant. qǔ 曲 "devious") refers to moral straightforwardness and uprightness.</p>
                        <p>5. Zhōng 衷 (ant. xié 邪 "wicked") refers to devoted uprightness of character. See also EARNEST</p>
                        <p>6. Qīng 清 (ant. zhuó 濁 "defiled and corrupt") can be used to refer to moral purity.</p>
                        <p>7. Shú 淑 is a highly poetic word referring to admirable moral qualities in general, typically in women.</p>
                        <p>8. Jūn zǐ 君子 (ant. xiǎo rén 小人 "petty man") refers to high moral qualities, especially in men.</p>
                        <p>&lt;div&gt;9. Zāng 臧 (pí 否 "good-for-nothing") is a neutral unemotional objective term for goodness.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;10. Rén yì 仁義, when it is not simply listing benevolence and righteousness, often refers quite generally (by synecdoche) to moral goodness or the moral virtues LIKE benevolence and righteousness and not in fact to just two virtues.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="old-chinese-criteria" tls:created="2022-07-20T18:47:11.082+09:00" concept="uuid-42b36b25-735c-42c0-9644-15df57265a2f" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-20T18:48:56.755+09:00">
                        <p>The most general term for discarding something reluctantly, abandoning what one would have liked to keep, is qì 棄.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-42b36b25-735c-42c0-9644-15df57265a2f" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-20T18:51:11.995+09:00">
                        <p>1. The most general term for discarding something reluctantly, abandoning what one would have liked to keep, is qì 棄.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-42b36b25-735c-42c0-9644-15df57265a2f" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-20T18:53:04.154+09:00">
                        <p>&lt;div&gt;1. The most general term for discarding something reluctantly, abandoning what one would have liked to keep or continue to do, is qì 棄.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-42b36b25-735c-42c0-9644-15df57265a2f" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-20T18:53:14.082+09:00">
                        <p>&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;1. The most general term for discarding something reluctantly, abandoning what one would have liked to keep or continue to do, is qì 棄.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-9700afcb-142a-4626-a4b8-d809156fb76e" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-22T17:24:46.109+09:00">
<p>1. The current general term for salient features and principles of charismatic moral integrity and generosity is dé 德, when used as a term of ethical evalutation; but this word has many other philosophically important meanings.</p>
<p>2. Other general terms for subjectively construed general moral commendation include měi 美 "point of moral distinction" (ant. è 惡 "point of moral decrepitude"), and occasionally gāo 高 "elevated points, elevated spirit" (ant. jiàn 賤 "point of vulgar decrepitude"). NB that shàn 善 "excellent" is not used as a general term of positive moral appreciation in pre-Buddhist texts.</p>
<p>3. The most current dé 德 "virtues" recognised in pre-Buddhist China are rén 仁 "kind-heartedness", yì 義 "rectitude", lǐ 禮 "propriety", zhì 智 "wisdom", and xìn 信 "good faith".</p>
<p>4. Further important virtues are xiào 孝 "filial piety", zhōng 忠 "loyal diligence", tì 悌 / 弟 "brotherly affection", lián 廉 "impeccable probity", jié 節 "moderation", and perhaps yǒng 勇 "the courage of one's moral convictions". ( 說苑 : 百行 (xìng) 孝為先 )</p>
<p>5. Zhōng yōng 中庸 "the mean in action" may be mentioned as a a central Confucian virtue, jiān ài 兼愛 "unIversal love" as a Mohist virtue, wú wéi 無為 "unobtrusive action" as a non-moralistic Taoist virtue.</p>
        </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-48817188-ab53-44fb-8065-9692355be291" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-23T19:30:26.175+09:00">
<p>1. The most current general marker of the passive is jiàn 見 which means literally "be exposed to, face".</p>
<p>2. Wéi 為 and yú 於 are structural particles which abstractly indicate that certain verbs in their environment are passive.</p>
<p>3. Bèi 被 typically refers to the suffering of something undesirable.</p>
<p>4. Qǔ 取 typically refers to the suffering of something undesirable by one's own fault.</p>
<p>5. Zāo 遭 and yù 遇 refer to running into what tend to be undesirable situations.</p>
<p>6. Shòu 受 refers to an agent being the recipient of some impact from the outside.</p>
<p>NB: Note that the notion of the passive is notoriously ill-defined for a language like classical Chinese, and what some grammarians view as passive constructions will be construed by others as periphrastic ways of expressing with various transitive verbs and prepositions what other other languages express with passive forms.</p>
        </div>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>