<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="del-notes-2024-02-crypt">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Recorded items for month 2024-02</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</ab>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by members of the TLS project</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Initially created: <date>2024-02-25T18:30:17.205+09:00</date>.</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Items</head>
                <p xml:id="del-2024-02-start">
                    <div xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="old-chinese-criteria" tls:created="2024-02-25T18:26:58.533+09:00" concept="uuid-748e6226-c1ae-42f3-802b-792082fcccb9" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-25T18:30:17.205+09:00">
                        <p>1. 故 is by far the most general Chinese word for THEREFORE, and in the interpretation of the word it is always important to find the semantic scope of the word, i.e. the "reason" or "cause" the particle refers back to. [It is important to distinguish between the pregnant use of 故 THEREFORE from the "bleached" use of  故 THUS "along these lines".　2. 是故 is the most common compound word in this synonym group (for which 故 alone may be regarded to be a short form). But 是故 has no "bleached" uses and must always refer to either subjective motivation or objective causation.然則 "given this, then" is explicitly argumentative and limited to abstract discussion contexts.2. 是以 is also frequent but the word seems to refer to subjective motivations and purposes in especially many important cases.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-748e6226-c1ae-42f3-802b-792082fcccb9" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-25T18:45:55.4+09:00">
                        <p>&lt;div&gt;1. 故 is by far the most general Chinese word for THEREFORE, and in the interpretation of the word it is always important to find the semantic scope of the word, i.e. the "reason" or "cause" the particle refers back to. [It is important to distinguish between the pregnant use of 故 THEREFORE from the "bleached" use of  故 THUS "along these lines".　&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;2. 是故 is the most common compound word in this synonym group (for which 故 alone may be regarded to be a short form). But 是故 rarely has "bleached" uses and must generally refer to either subjective motivation or objective causation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;3. 然則 "given this, then" is explicitly argumentative and limited to abstract discussion contexts.2. 是以 is also frequent but the word seems to refer to subjective motivations and purposes in especially many important cases.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-748e6226-c1ae-42f3-802b-792082fcccb9" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-25T18:51:09.301+09:00">
                        <p>&lt;div&gt;1. 故 is by far the most general Chinese word for THEREFORE, and in the interpretation of the word it is always important to find the semantic scope of the word, i.e. the "reason" or "cause" the particle refers back to. [It is important to distinguish between the pregnant use of 故 THEREFORE from the "bleached" use of  故 THUS "along these lines".　&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;2. 是故 is the most common compound word in this synonym group (for which 故 alone may be regarded to be a short form). But 是故 rarely has "bleached" uses and must generally refer to either subjective motivation or objective causation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;3. 然則 "given this, then" is argumentative and limited to abstract discussion contexts.2. 是以 is also frequent but the word seems to refer to subjective motivations and purposes in especially many important cases.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;4.以此觀之 and 由是觀之 "viewed against this background" are explicitly theoretical in a paedagogical mode.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;5. 故曰 "therefore it is said" typically refers to a helpful relevant and explanatory  quotation independently known, but can also refer to the author's expressed opinion elsewhere.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;6. 因此 "for this reason" typically refers to a broad background explaining what is to follow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-748e6226-c1ae-42f3-802b-792082fcccb9" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-25T19:13:47.812+09:00">
                        <p>&lt;div&gt;1. 故 is by far the most general Chinese word for THEREFORE, and in the interpretation of the word it is always important to find the semantic scope of the word, i.e. the "reason" or "cause" the particle refers back to. [It is important to distinguish between the pregnant use of 故 THEREFORE from the "bleached" use of  故 THUS "along these lines".　&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;2. 是故 is the most common compound word in this synonym group (for which 故 alone may be regarded to be a short form). But 是故 rarely has "bleached" uses and must generally refer to either subjective motivation or objective causation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;3. 是以 "because of this" almost as common, and seems to me more common as indicating a subjective cause than  a concrete causal relation. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;4. 然則 "given this, then" is argumentative and limited to abstract discussion contexts.2. 是以 is also frequent but the word seems to refer to subjective motivations and purposes in especially many important cases.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;5.以此觀之 and 由是觀之 "viewed against this background" are explicitly theoretical in an almost didactic mode.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;6. 故曰 "therefore it is said" typically refers to a helpful relevant and explanatory  quotation, often independently known, but it can also refer to the author's expressed opinion elsewhere in the context, and to an emphatic conclusion drawn in an argument.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;7. 因此 "for this reason" typically refers to a broad background explaining what is to follow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-4e6d6168-ef29-4b00-8ae1-bdb23e84ed4f" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-27T05:34:36.045+09:00">
<p>1. Bēi 杯 in Warring States and Han times referred to a shallow oval bowl with two ears used for wine, soup, broth etc.; it was made of lacquered wood, bronze, earthenware, jade, silver, and even glass. According to HUANG (1995: 951 - 952), the term was in that period also used for the deep beaker on a foot to drink wine from, which is known from archaeological finds; in textual evidence, there is no firm proof of it, but as regards the shape of the vessel which could only be used for drinking, it is highly probable.</p>
<p>2. Shāng 觴 is in late Warring States and Han times general term for a wine cup. It can often refer to bēi 杯. HUANG 1995: 955 - 956.</p>
<p>3. Y3ǔ shāng 羽觴 (?? in HANYU DACIDIAN as hù shāng: see vol. 9, pp. 641) is mentioned as a wine cup in the texts of the late Warring States and Han periods; perhaps another term for bēi 杯 with two ears.</p>
<p>4. Zhī (I cannot find the character in the list) refers to the round cylindrical wine cup made of wood, lacquare, bronze, silver, or pottery:</p>
<p>5. Zhǎn 醆 / 盞 is in Han times rare term for small bēi 杯 (mentioned in FANGYAN).</p>
<p>6. Zhuó 酌 is a general term for a wine cup.</p>
<p>7. Jué 爵 is the term for Shang and Western Zhou bronze tripod with long spout to drink wine from, which was used on ceremonial occasions. Shape of the character read now as jué 爵 in the oracle bone and bronze inscriptions obviously refers to this kind of cup. There are also pottery vessels of this shape known from the Shang period. In late Western Zhou times, this type of vessel came out of use. Jué 爵 mentioned in the Eastern Zhou and Han texts can refer to each type of wine cup; according to Han sources jué 爵 should have room for one shēng 升 of wine[??? it seems to me that jué 爵 in the Eastern Zhou sometimes refers to the certain amount of wine drunk at once rather than to the concrete wine vessel???.</p>
<p>8. Jiǎ 斝 is generally used as a term for a bronze vessel with three legs and round opening which was used to heat and serve wine. This type of vessel was common in the Shang and Western Zhou periods and came out of use in the late Western Zhou. Attribution of the name to this kind of vessel is not certain, but probable. In the Eastern Zhou and Han texts, jiǎ 斝 refers to the wine vessel, the content of which should be greater than in the case of jué 爵. [???The word seems to be rather rare in the Eastern Zhou and Han, and it occurs (except one mention in ZUO] in texts like YILI, SHUOWEN, as well as in commentaries; it cannot be thus excluded that its usage is some kind of archaization.</p>
<p>9. Sǎn 散 refers to the same kind of vessel as jiǎ 斝.</p>
<p>10. Jiǎo 角 occurs rarely in the Eastern Zhou and Han texts, and it should refer to some kind of cup made originally of an animal horn or resembling it in a shape. Identification of this vessel remains uncertain, although there are horn-like vessels known from the Shang down to the Han. In archaeology, jiǎo 角 is used for the bronze wine tripod similar in a shape to jué 爵 but with two identical spouts on the opposite sides of an opening; this vessel was in use from the Shang down to the Western Zhou period.</p>
<p>11. Gū 觚 in the Eastern Zhou and Han texts refers to some kind of vessel with edges. Its identification is uncertain. In archeology, the term is used for the trumpet-like bronze cup which is known from the Shang and Western Zhou periods. There are also lacquered and pottery vessels of this type.</p>
<p>12. Gōng or guāng 觥 in SHIJING obviously refers to the drinking cup made of the rhinoceros horn or shaped like it. Later, it can be used for a large cup. In archaeology, the term traditionally refers to the large animal-like shaped bronze vessel known from the Shang and Western Zhou periods; but this attribution is probably mistaken.</p>
<p>13. Kē 搕 is a kind of (probably ordinary) cup to drink from referred to in ZUO.</p>
        </div>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>