<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="del-notes-2024-03-crypt">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Recorded items for month 2024-03</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</ab>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by members of the TLS project</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Initially created: <date>2024-03-08T02:18:12.859+09:00</date>.</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Items</head>
                <p xml:id="del-2024-03-start">
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-1aa78248-5868-4414-a9c4-97ccdb47c021" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-08T02:18:12.859+09:00">
<p>1. The most current general word for an entertainer is jì 妓, and this word refers to any entertainer including artists, dancers, and clowns of any kind.</p>
<p>2. Chàng 倡 refers occasionally to an entertainer specialised in singing, especially the main singer.</p>
<p>3. Lìng 伶 refers specifically to a musician-entertainer who accompanies the main singers chàng 倡.</p>
<p>4. Yōu 優 and yōu rén 優人 refers to dwarf-clowns who perform through comic talk, comic action and slapstick comedy.</p>
<p>5. Pái 俳 and more often pái yōu 俳優 refer to a superior specialist in comic talk.</p>
<p>6. Zhū rú 侏儒 is a general word for a dwarf, and since the dwarf at court typically acted as a clown, the term came also to refer generally to clowns.</p>
<p>7. Nu# yuè 女樂 is a standard general term for female musical entertainers or female musicians.</p>
        </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-07855030-3463-472d-bd01-1c7ceebbfb3d" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-13T19:00:23.219+09:00">
                        <p>1. The most colourless and general way of referring to any act of saying attributed to any subject, no matter whether animate or inanimate, something is yuē 曰, and the verb introduces direct speech.</p>
                        <p>2. Yán 言 is to speak up, propose, typically in public, and on one's own initiative, to maintain something, and the word can indroduce direct speech as well as occasionally very limited indirect speech.</p>
                        <p>3. Yǔ 語 is to say something as part of typically informal conversation. Contrast yù 語 "tell, inform" in REPORT.</p>
                        <p>4. Tán 談 refers to informal communicative talk, sometimes but not always with some pejorative connotation.</p>
                        <p>5. Yún 云 is used of books as well as persons and tends to refer to what are typically construed as authoritative acts of saying, and the word often has to be taken figuratively as "run as follows". (Note the perfectly regular contrast 曰 / 云 in MOUZI.)</p>
                        <p>6. Wèi 謂 is to say or predicate something of someone. See also MEAN.</p>
                        <p>7. Cí 辭 is primarily an act of careful articulation and rhetorical formulation.</p>
                        <p>8. Dào 道 "speak of with authority, speak of adequately; quote" often involves quotation or especially serious discussion of important points, or the relating of important evidence.</p>
                        <p>9. Jǔ 舉 is a technical term referring to the bringing up of a subject, and the subject of this verb is always a person, not a text.</p>
                        <p>10. Chēng 稱 refers in a rather formal historian's style to the making of statements and the applying of terminology. See also NAME.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-3d43f68e-3945-471c-8f28-42b152565baa" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-13T22:36:58.818+09:00">
<p>[ASCENDING/DESCENDING]</p>
<p>[[COMMON/RARE]]</p>
<p>[GENERAL/SPECIFIC]</p>
<p>[INFORMAL/OFFICIAL]</p>
<p>1. The general word is wèn 問 "open a dialogue by consulting someone with a question" (ant. duì 對 "reply to a superior") which typically refers to the consultation of a person who is supposed to know something. When the adressee is explicit, the questioner is typically of higher status than the addressee, and the reply is correspondingly often phrased politely as duì yuē 對曰. When there is no explicit addressee (X asked about Y), the addressee often is of higher status (e.g. a teacher).</p>
<p>[SPECIFIC]; [[COMMOM+]]</p>
<p>2. Qǐng 請 is occasionally used to refer to polite requests for information.</p>
<p>[[RARE]]</p>
<p>3. Nàn 難 is to ask intellectually hostile questions regarding something which the person questioned has said or maintains as true, to make objections. See DISAGREE and REFUTE which are difficult to distinguish from each other and from this.</p>
<p>[SPECIFIC], [HORIZONTAL]</p>
<p>4. Fǎng 訪 typically refers to questioning addressed to superiors.</p>
<p>[ASCENDING]</p>
<p>5. Xún 詢 typically refers to rather formal questions addressed to inferiors.</p>
<p>[DESCENDING], [OFFICIAL]</p>
<p>6. Zī 諮／咨 refers to questions addressed to a specialist.</p>
<p>[SPECIFIC]</p>
<p>7. Zōu 諏 all refer to some kind of official soliciting of formal opinions.</p>
<p>[OFFICIAL]; [[RARE]]</p>
<p>8. Yuē 曰 is regularly used to introduce related questions as reactions within an ongoing dialogue.</p>
<p>9. Wèi 謂 may introduce what are in fact questions rather than statements.</p>
        </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-3d43f68e-3945-471c-8f28-42b152565baa" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-13T22:37:50.115+09:00">
                        <p>[ASCENDING/DESCENDING]</p>
                        <p>[[COMMON/RARE]]</p>
                        <p>[GENERAL/SPECIFIC]</p>
                        <p>[INFORMAL/OFFICIAL]</p>
                        <p>1. The general word is wèn 問 "open a dialogue by consulting someone with a question" (ant. duì 對 "reply to a superior") which typically refers to the consultation of a person who is supposed to know something. When the adressee is explicit, the questioner is typically of higher status than the addressee, and the reply is correspondingly often phrased politely as duì yuē 對曰. When there is no explicit addressee (X asked about Y), the addressee often is of higher status (e.g. a teacher).</p>
                        <p>[SPECIFIC]; [[COMMOM+]]</p>
                        <p>2. Qǐng 請 is occasionally used to refer to polite requests for information.</p>
                        <p>[[RARE]]</p>
                        <p>3. Nàn 難 is to ask intellectually hostile questions regarding something which the person questioned has said or maintains as true, to make objections. See DISAGREE and REFUTE which are difficult to distinguish from each other and from this.</p>
                        <p>[SPECIFIC], [HORIZONTAL]</p>
                        <p>4. Fǎng 訪 typically refers to questioning addressed to superiors.</p>
                        <p>[ASCENDING]</p>
                        <p>5. Xún 詢 typically refers to rather formal questions addressed to inferiors.</p>
                        <p>[DESCENDING], [OFFICIAL]</p>
                        <p>6. Zī 諮／咨 refers to questions addressed to a specialist.</p>
                        <p>[SPECIFIC]</p>
                        <p>7. Zōu 諏 all refer to some kind of official soliciting of formal opinions.</p>
                        <p>[OFFICIAL]; [[RARE]]</p>
                        <p>8. Yuē 曰 is regularly used to introduce related questions as reactions within an ongoing dialogue.</p>
                        <p>&lt;div&gt;9. Wèi 謂 may introduce what are in fact questions rather than statements.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;10. Wèn yuē 問曰 introduces a a question that opens a new dialogue or a discrete new phase in a dialogue.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;NB: ASKing in Chinese us always dialogic: one cannot ask oneself any question, and one cannot abstractly just raise an abstract question as an intellectual issue worthy of discussion. There seems to be no word in classical Chinese for "asking a question" without addressing this question to an audience.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
                    </div>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>