<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="del-notes-2021-03-crypt">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Recorded items for month 2021-03</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by members of the TLS project</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>Initially created: <date>2021-03-23T17:54:11.251+09:00</date>.</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Items</head>
                <p xml:id="del-2021-03-start">
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-3eb2c600-e234-4c6b-bb79-40e8eff9ee14" resp="#chris" modified="2021-03-23T17:54:11.251+09:00">
<p>[ABSOLUTE/GRADED]</p>
<p>[ARCHAIC/CURRENT]</p>
<p>[DIFFICULT/EASY]</p>
<p>[ENDOGENIC/EXOGENIC]</p>
<p>[EMOTIONAL/UNEMOTIONAL]</p>
<p>[INCIDENTAL/INHERENT]</p>
<p>[INNATE/ACQUIRED]</p>
<p>[LASTING!/TEMPORARY]</p>
<p>[PHYSICAL/PSYCHOLOGICAL]</p>
<p>[PRACTICAL/THEORETICAL]</p>
<p>1. The commonest word is néng 能 "have an inherent capacity for, have the personal ability to".</p>
<p>[CURRENT], [ENDOGENIC], [GRADED], [LASTING]</p>
<p>2. Kě yǐ 可以 "be in an objective position to, have the possibility to".</p>
<p>[ABSOLUTE], [CURRENT], [EXOGENIC], [TEMPORARY!]</p>
<p>3. Zú yǐ 足以 emphasises sufficiency of conditions necessary to get something done.</p>
<p>[CURRENT], [GRADED], [INHERENT], [PHYSICAL]</p>
<p>4. Kè 克 typically comes to emphasise the ability to do something difficult in post-archaic times, but the word was equivalent to néng 能 in early texts.</p>
<p>[ABSOLUTE], [ARCHAIC], [INCIDENTAL], [TEMPORARY], [PHYSICAL]</p>
<p>5. Rén 任 emphasises a general qualification to achieve something worth achieving and not obviously easy to achieve.</p>
<p>[ABSOLUTE], [CURRENT], [DIFFICULT], [ENDOGENIC], [TEMPORARY]</p>
<p>6. Kān 堪 typically refers to the ability to do something others might not be willing or psychologically able to do.</p>
<p>[ABSOLUTE], [CURRENT], [DIFFICULT], [EMOTIONAL], [ENDOGENIC], [PSYCHOLOGICAL]</p>
<p>7. Jì 技 "expertise, know-how" refers to the talents for crafts and the like, and the word is not normally used as a verb. See SKILL.</p>
<p>[ACQUIRED], [CURRENT], [DIFFICULT], [GRADED], [LASTING], [PRACTICAL]</p>
<p>8. Lì 力 "strength" is sometimes used to refer to an ability to do someting which in some sense requires strength.</p>
<p>9. Zhī 知 refers to the intellectual ability to do something, especially to do something that is not intellectually trivial.</p>
<p>10. Jì néng 技能 refers to a lasting acquired skill.</p>
<p>NB: Dé 得 "cope, show an ability to do something by actually doing it" is an achievement verb and does not belong in this group. See COPE.</p>
        </div>
                    <div type="old-chinese-criteria" concept="uuid-5dfd2084-459d-4bd3-9a20-ca0f2f78db51" resp="#CH" modified="2021-03-30T00:11:54.099+09:00">
<p>1. The most current word for propositional truth is rán 然 "it is so" (ant. fǒu 否 "be untrue").</p>
<p>2. Kě 可 refers to logical or ethical acceptability.</p>
<p>3. Xìn 信 (ant. zhà 詐 "fraudulent and not reliable") refers prototypically to reliablity as information.</p>
<p>4. Shì 是 (ant. fēi 非 "wrong") refers prototypically to what invites assent or approval.</p>
<p>5. Zhēn 真 (ant. jiǎ 假 "fake") typically refers to what contains nothing faked or unreal and is genuinely true.</p>
<p>6. Dāng 當 (ant. guò 過 "wrong") refers prototypically to what fits the facts and does not deviate.</p>
<p>7. Yǒu 有 (ant. wú 無 "there is no such fact")refers abstractly to the occurrence of an event or the truth of an abstract proposition.</p>
<p>8. Chéng 誠 (ant. wěi 偽 "faked") refers to honest truth. (Note that chéng 誠 normally means "earnest" in early texts and has nothing to do with this meaning.)</p>
<p>9. Shí 實 "real and true" (ant. xū 虛 "only apparently") refers to something not being a figment of the imagination. See REAL.</p>
        </div>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>