<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-e8f4ea8a-3401-442e-b4ea-8a3401542ec7" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>三身</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="BUDDHAS" tls:concept-id="uuid-d99d127f-9d36-4e32-8d3a-46c19bd6151b" xml:id="uuid-f2e74e93-ab45-43a5-9f12-62952b9ad7cc" n="5">
            <form corresp="#uuid-3b81e026-2aee-45cd-b686-7bab8c7046b3 #uuid-3fea944e-3a8d-4a16-a19d-850444d49e0c">
<orth>三身</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sān shēn</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">saam qhjin</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">sɑm ɕin</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-2389c812-8053-4187-8f7a-19f6e856050f">FOGUANG</ref>
<title>佛光大辭典 Fóguāng dàcídiǎn The Foguang Dictionary of Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">555b-557b</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-a8099af3-8899-4cb8-9f19-ae2f6cecb3b6">TAKASAKI 1987</ref>
<title>An Introduction to Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">68-69</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"The Theory of Three Bodies</p>
<p>In contradistinctionto the above Dharma-body. those who have personally realized the Dharma, namely, the Tathaagatas (=those who have arrived at thusness), correspond to the Buddhas mentioned previously who have their individual pure lands. Theirs is known as the 'enjoyment-body' (saMmbhoga-kaaya) since they enjoy the fruits of enlightenment, although in Chinese this term was also rendered as 'recompense-body' (報身, 應身), implying that they have now received the fruits of the their past practices. In this respect, they are self-benefitting and theirs in the standpoint of 'self-enjoyment' (自受用). However, since the very existence of a pure land presupposes the altruistic aim of receiving sentient beings there and having them enjoy the same enlightenment, these Buddhas are in this respect homogeneous (niSsyanda) with the Dharma-body (等流身: homogeneous body), and they are Buddhas who have appeared in other worlds for the weal of sentient beings. In this sense, the enjoyment-body is  'body for  causing others to enjoy the realization of the Dharma' or 'other-enjoyment body' (他受用身). Although these Buddhas of the pure lands are endowed with material bodies, they cannot be seen by ordinary beings in this defiled world of ours, and are said to be visible to bodhisattvas only. SSaakyamuni, on the other hand, not only possesses a material body for altruistic purposes but is also visible to ordinary beings; this is the 'transformation-body' (nirmaaNna-kaaya, 化身, 應身), expressly manifested by the Dharma-body for our sakes. This transformation-body is a Tathaagata in the sense that he is 'one who has come from thusness'.</p>
<p>Thus was established the theory of the three bodies of the Buddha (with the Dharma-body sometimes referred to as 'own-nature body' (svabhaava-kaaya, 自性身). and this became the basis of all further Mahaayaana speculation on the nature of the Buddha's body. In later times this theory of three bodies underwent further developments: these include the theory of four bodies, which arose from the division of enjoyment-body into the 'self-enjoyment body' (自受用身) and 'other-enjoyment body' (他受用身);  [...]."</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-06ee6678-9716-4169-8164-cc9676431d83" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8e2b4b11-ecda-4d61-864f-20e28f6cabe5">NPab.adN</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>three-Buddha-bodied</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6e317c3c-45fa-47bb-b763-70728b1e0f36" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-db0698e7-db2f-4ee3-9a20-0c2b2e0cebf0">NPab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-887fdec5-f18d-4faf-8602-f5c5c2f99a1d">metaphysical</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: the three 'bodies' of the Buddha, skr. trayaḥ kāyāḥ (consisting of the 法身 (dharma-kāya), the 報身 (saṃbhoga-kāya; sometimes referred to as 'enjoyment-body', 'wisdom-body' or 'retribution-body'), and the 應身 (nirmāṇa-kāya; sometimes translated with 'merit-body' or 'transformation-body'); there are countless terms, theories, and interpretations related to 三身</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>