<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-e6485024-a375-4e0f-8850-24a375de0fe9" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>涅盤</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="SALVATION" tls:concept-id="uuid-10ca3dbe-56f7-4aee-9149-b2dc07143a67" xml:id="uuid-12ada19e-85f1-4a2e-8e7d-3443719bf538" n="15">
            <form corresp="#uuid-2b680e78-8d29-453b-8a7f-88d4148724f4 #uuid-74e14eea-3c99-47bc-846d-98b57844cc03">
<orth>涅盤</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">niè pán</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">m-liiɡ baan</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">net bʷɑn</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-2389c812-8053-4187-8f7a-19f6e856050f">FOGUANG</ref>
<title>佛光大辭典 Fóguāng dàcídiǎn The Foguang Dictionary of Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">4149</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-a8099af3-8899-4cb8-9f19-ae2f6cecb3b6">TAKASAKI 1987</ref>
<title>An Introduction to Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">163ff</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"It was earlier explained the third of the Four Noble Truths, the truth of cessation, meant the cessation of suffering or the cessation of the origination of suffering, and that it was identical with NirvaaNna. This term nirvaaNna (PALI nibbaana, 涅槃) refers to that state of peace which accompanies tranquillity, as was reflected in the statements that 'NirvaaNna is tranquillity' and 'cessation is happiness.' That this state is the ultimate goal or ideal state after which Buddhism aspires was the import of the third Noble Truth, the truth of the cessation of suffering. The Buddha SSaakyamuni was in fact one who had attained such a state.</p>
<p>However, the appellation 'Buddha' itself is not a term which directly denotes this state. NirvaaNna may be said to be alluded to be the epithets such a tathaagat (thus-come/-gone one) and sugata (one who has reached happiness), implying the attainment of the ideal state, but even these are not directly related to the term nirvaaNna itself. The one exception is jina (victor) which, meaning here one who has overcome suffering, exhibits an affinity in its connotations with the cessation of suffering of NirvaaNna. All the other appellations of the Buddha either inidicate, as in the term buddha (awakened one) itself, a state of intellectual perfection, or, as with puruSsa-damya-saarathi (one who controls men to be tamed) and sSaastaa deva-manuSsyaaNnaam (teacher of gods and men), hint at this role as spiritual guide or saviour. In the other words, the aspect of wisdom and compassion are emphasized at the expense of allusion to the state of NirvaaNna, which would appear to have been pushed in the background.</p>
<p>This state of affairs derives from the fact that Buddhism would seek its point of origin in the very fact of the Buddha's enlightenment, as is indeed reflected in the designation 'Buddhism' itself. The experience of enlightenment or bodhi (菩提) represents nothing other than the 'Buddha's essence' (buddhatva, 佛體) and is that which makes a Buddha what he is. It is therefore only to be expected that the attainment of enlightenment should have been regarded as the supreme goal of the Buddhist path of spiritual cultivation.</p>
<p>This being so, what then is the relationship between this enlightenment and nirvaaNna, the latter as being defined as the cessation of suffering? When considered in the context of the life of SSaakyamuni, bodhi corresponds to his attainment of enlightenment and nirvaaNna to this death. This would give the impression that Buddha did not experience NirvaaNna while alive. The identification of NirvaaNna with SSaakyamuni's death is probably related to the fact that the word nirvaaNna signified death in the sense of the extinction of the flame of life. But on the other hand, the terms used to denote the ideal state also included the word 'immortality' (amRrta, PALI amata 不死), and this was employed as synonym of NrivaaNna. On the occasion of his enlightenment, SSaakyamuni declared that he had realized that he had overcome suffering, had been liberated from defilement, and would undergo no further rebirth, and he also stated that, although possessed by a physical body characterized by birth, old age, sickness and death, through having awoken to the misfortune attendant thereon, he had obtained NirvaaNna, the unsurpassed state of peace free old age, sickness and death. This state is known as 'NirvaaNn in the visible world (=present life)' (dRrSsTta-dharma-nirvaaNna, PALI diTtTtha-dhamma-nibbaana, 現法涅槃).</p>
<p>If this be the case, it would suggest then that SSaakyamuni's initial goal had not been enlightenment but the state of immortality or NirvaaNna. Contemporary ascetics and other religious practicioners were seeking liberation from the cycle of transmigratory existence and were all groping for methods to that end. Through proper observation, knowledge, and realization of the truth of the human condition, transient and without self, and by producing within himself a state of mind free of any attachment to life, SSaakyamuni succeeded in achieving that goal. It was probably because SSaakyamuni's distinctive characteristic was to be found in this method which he had discovered that he came to be known in particular by the name of 'Buddha' in order to distinguish him from other religious leaders. This being so, enlightenment must be regarded as having been a means in relation to the attainment of nirvaaNna. But as the distinguishing feature of Buddhism came to be sought in enlightenment, this latter would have come to be considered the ultimate goal. In particular, the emphasis on the enlightenment would appear to be due in large part to the universalization of enlightenment in Mahaayaana Buddhism.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-12b11a82-9578-4f65-b24a-8771acbbf629" n="14">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-db0698e7-db2f-4ee3-9a20-0c2b2e0cebf0">NPab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e7204ae-4771-435b-82ff-310068296b6d">buddhist</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: skr. nirvāṇa (tranquility; the cessation of suffering)</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-871f1bdf-bdce-4a3b-852b-26f637e5ad76" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-091af450-64e0-4b82-98a2-84d0444b6d19">VPi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e7204ae-4771-435b-82ff-310068296b6d">buddhist</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: enter nirvāṇa</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>