<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" ID="uuid-07b188ce-2c42-4cb8-866a-a7cf4873c5b2" version="3.6" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://cluster-schemas.uni-hd.de/modsCluster.xsd">
<titleInfo lang="chi" script="Hant">
<title>六祖壇經</title>
    </titleInfo>
<titleInfo type="translated" lang="chi" transliteration="chinese/ala-lc" script="Latn">
<title>Liùzǔ tánjīng</title>
    </titleInfo>
<titleInfo type="translated" lang="eng" script="Latn">
<title>Platform Sūtra of the Sixth Patriarch on the Dharma-treasure</title>
    </titleInfo>
<relatedItem type="series">
<titleInfo script="Latn">
<title>Taishō</title>
        </titleInfo>
<part>
<detail type="volume">
<number>48/2007: 237a-345b</number>
            </detail>
        </part>
    </relatedItem>
<note type="general">This is the earliest extant version of the PLATFORM SUTRA (dating ca. 830-860) discovered among the Dūnhuáng manuscripts; since the manuscript is full of mistakes and corrupt Chinese graphs, it is possibly a copy of an even earlier version of the text. Some scholars assume that the original text was written ca. 714 shortly after Huìnéng's death. This text was expanded until it got its present from (ca. 820).  Other scholars (like Hú Shì) also assume the existence of an earlier version but contribute the scripture to the circle around Shénhuì 神會, and claim that the relation to Huìnéng is fictive. The contents of the Platform scripture (including a biographic part, the famous verses by Shénxiù and Huìnéng, attacks on the Northern School, and a doctrinal part dealing with prajNNaapaaramitaa thought, sudden awakening, seeing one's own nature, No-thought, No-mind, etc.) together with Shénhuì's writtings are representative for the Chán thought in the middle and late 8th century. These concepts were eventually elaborated on and adjusted by later masters (as can be seen in some Song editions of the PLATFORM SUTRA); there is not much reference to the text in the 9th century, however, there is much reference to Huìnéng as the Sixth Patriarch. The next edition dates from 967, compiled by Huìxīn 惠昕 (d.u.), this edition is not preserved.  Other editions include the Japanese edition Kooshooji bon Rokuso dankyoo 興聖寺本六祖壇經, ed. in SUZUKI/KUDA 1934; Kaga Daijooji shozoo Shooshuu Sookeizan Roku soshi dankyoo 加賀大乘寺所藏韶州曹溪山六祖師壇經, ed. in: Komazawa Daigaku Bukkyoo gakkai gakuhoo 駒澤大學佛教學會學報 8 (1938): 1-56. The information on the text is based on YAMPOLSKY 1967: 89-110; for a survey over the editions see ibid.: 191. The Kooshooji version was found after the second world-war at the Kooshooji temple (a Rinzai 臨濟 temple on Horikawa Street in North Kyooto).</note>

<note type="information-basis">CA</note>
<typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
<genre authority="marcgt">book</genre>
<note type="bibliographic-reference">PLATFORM SUTRA(A)</note>
<subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="platform sutra">Platform sutra</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="sixth patriarch">Sixth Patriarch</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="huineng">Huineng</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="惠能">惠能</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="early chan texts">early Chan texts</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="early zen texts">early Zen texts</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="zen doctrine">Zen doctrine</topic>
    </subject>
    <subject xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0">
        <topic tls:sort="lineage">lineage</topic>
    </subject>
    <note type="ref-usage">0</note>
</mods>