<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-4adb5603-a5bf-40ee-9b56-03a5bf10eee0" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>優填王</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="INDIAN PROPER NAMES" tls:concept-id="uuid-d27ead49-10a3-439c-8bcd-ac8233cd3211" xml:id="uuid-10f03eb4-951c-4c60-bb7f-ae6e7a8f876e" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-77cd1664-b9e4-43dc-bfea-2d29189f7605 #uuid-5f264c3c-6417-4b9f-9c6d-a93ab9a01770 #uuid-3b611bc0-1264-4fb0-b354-69ff386f2094">
<orth>優填王</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yōu tián wáng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qu diin ɢʷaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔɨu den ɦi̯ɐŋ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-2389c812-8053-4187-8f7a-19f6e856050f">FOGUANG</ref>
<title>佛光大辭典 Fóguāng dàcídiǎn The Foguang Dictionary of Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">6411a-b</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>According to s$utra literature the wife of the king was an ardent believer in the teaching of the Buddha. However, her husband was not yet following the Buddha's teaching and he was struck by misfortune and illness. This was at the time when the Buddha had ascended to a heaven in order to preach to his mother there. His ministers thereupon used the 栴檀 wood (sandal-wood) from a mountain called Niu2to2u 牛頭 and fabricated a small Buddha-statue five 尺. Thereupon the king recovered from his illness. It is said that this event initiated the construction of small Buddha-statues in India, a habit which was eventually transmitted to China.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-2e1f1e8c-5fd3-44f1-8f30-977400274b6a" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e7204ae-4771-435b-82ff-310068296b6d">buddhist</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: King Udayana (said to have ruled over Kauśāmbī 憍賞彌國 at the time of the Buddha) (According to sūtra literature the wife of the king was an ardent believer in the teaching of the Buddha. However, her husband was not yet following the Buddha's teaching and he was struck by misfortune and illness. This was at the time when the Buddha had ascended to a heaven in order to preach to his mother there. His ministers thereupon used the 栴檀 wood (sandal-wood) from a mountain called Niútóu 牛頭 and fabricated a small Buddha-statue five 尺. Thereupon the king recovered from his illness. It is said that this event initiated the construction of small Buddha-statues in India, a habit which was eventually transmitted to China.)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>