<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-82791310-ed36-4369-b7c4-c65d05a57955" subtype="AN">
  <head>烏癩</head>
  <div type="definition">black repudiation-illness</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="wulai-59192" n="wulai烏癩">
      <form>
        <orth>烏癩</orth>
        <pron>Wu lai</pron>
        <usg n="3">[3]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>black repudiation-illness</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Alternative Names chi lai 赤癩 , red repudiation-illness. Pathological Condition of lai 癩 , repudiation-illness where the skin itches as if bugs/worms were crawling in it. Also, lumps the size of peach or plum kernels rise from the skin, with red and black papules. In front of their eyes patients perceive items as if there were drooping silk threads. The heart is shocked and fearful. The hands and feet are numb and feel no pain if pierced with a needle. The elbows are as if tied with a string. Patients are unable to walk. Zhu bing yuan hou lun 諸病源候論 2: 凡癩病，皆是惡風及犯觸 忌害所得。初覺皮毛變異，或淫淫苦癢如蟲行，或眼前見物如垂絲，言 語無定，心常驚恐。皮肉中或如桃李子，隱疹赤黑，手足頑痹，針刺不 痛，脚下不得踏地。凡食之時，開口而鳴，語亦如是，身體瘡痛，兩肘 如繩縛，此名黑癩 , “All types of repudiation-illness are brought forth by malign wind and the encounter with something forbidden and harmful. In the beginning [patients] notice changes in the skin and hair. In some cases they feel an extreme itch as if there were insects crawling. Or in front of their eyes they see items like silk threads. Their language is not stable, their heart if repeatedly affected by fright and fear. In their skin and flesh there is something like peaches and plums, with minute red and black pimples. Hands and feet are affected by a stubborn blockage. When pierced with a needle, they do not feel pain. With their legs they cannot walk. When it is time to eat they open the mouth and make the cries of birds. Their language is of the same type. The body has sores and is painful. The two elbows feel as if tied with a rope. This is called black repudiation-illness ”.</def>
      </sense>
      <pb n="539"/>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>