<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-88476c3c-3111-4661-a01d-b313a9e9f93f" subtype="AN">
  <head>痔瘺</head>
  <div type="definition">piles fistula; piles and fistula</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="zhilou-60430" n="zhilou痔瘺">
      <form>
        <orth>痔瘺</orth>
        <pron>Zhi lou</pron>
        <usg n="72">[72]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>piles fistula; piles and fistula</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>Alternative Names lou zhi 瘺痔. Mentioned in Shen nong ben cao jing 神農本草經 Xu li 序例：夫大病之主，有…癰腫、惡瘡，痔瘺、癭瘤 , “Now, the most important massive diseases include … obstruction-illness with swelling, malign sores, piles fistula , and goiters with tumors of the neck”. Pathological Condition a) in the vicinity of the anus with the muscles and flesh being pierced with holes, the sores failing to close and at times releasing pus and blood. Sheng ji zong lu 聖濟總錄 143 ：毒氣浸漬，肌肉穿穴，瘡口不合，時有膿血，故成痔瘺 , “When soaked with poison qi the muscles and flesh are pierced with holes, the openings of the sores fail to close and at times there is pus and blood. Hence this develops into piles fistula ”.b) Identical with zhi lou 痔漏 a) piles with leakage. Ri hua zi zhu jia ben cao 日華子諸家本草 Substance Entry bai lian 白斂：止驚邪，發背，瘰癧，腸風痔瘺 , “It ends fright evil, effusion of the back, scrofula with pervasion-illness, intestinal wind and piles fistula ”.c) Combined Designation of zhi 痔 , piles, and lou 瘺 , fistula. Zhu bing yuan hou lun 諸病源候論 18: 甚者則能成痔瘺 疥癬，癩癰疽瘑諸瘡 , “In severe cases this may generate sores such as piles, fistula , jie -illness, xuan -illness, repudiation-illness, obstruction-illness, impediment-illness, and lair-illness”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>