<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-84dc5a6c-d74f-43ee-979f-c4597a418cee" subtype="AN">
  <head>盤腸產</head>
  <div type="definition">birth with a twisted intestine</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="panchangchan-93566" n="panchangchan盤腸產">
      <form>
        <orth>盤腸產</orth>
        <pron>Pan chang chan</pron>
        <usg n="2">[2]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>birth with a twisted intestine</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Alternative Names pan chang sheng chan 盤腸生產; zi chang xian chu 子腸先出 , prior appearance of the infant‘s intestine; zi chang xian xia 子腸先下 , prior descent of the infant‘s intestine. Pathological Condition at the time of birth with the vaginal wall or rectum appearing first and, after the child was born, being unable to retreat by themselves. Fu ren da quan liang Gynecological book. Southern Song fang era, 1237. 婦人大全良方 17: 趙都運恭 人，每臨產則子腸先出，然後產子。產子之後，其腸不收，甚以為苦， 名曰盤腸產。醫不能療。偶在建昌，得一坐婆施之一法而收之。其法遇 產後子腸不收之時，以醋半盞，新汲冷水七分，碗調停，噀產婦面，每 噀一縮，三噀收盡。此良法也，後學不可不知 , “Whenever the wife of the official Zhao Duyun approached the moment of delivery, the ‘infant’s intestine’ (i.e. uterus) appeared first, and only then did she give birth to a child. After the child was born, her intestine failed to recede. This caused her extreme suffering. It is called ‘ birth with a twisted intestine ’. The physicians were unable to cure this. It so happened that in Jianchang eventually she was treated by a midwife with a therapeutic approach that caused [the intestine] to recede. This approach is as follows. When she encounters a woman whose ‘infant’s intestine’, following delivery, fails to recede, she mixes in a bowl half a cup of vinegar with 7 parts of cold water freshly drawn from a well, and spits it out of her mouth into the face of the delivering woman. After each spitting [the intestine] withdraws a bit. After three spirtings it has completely receded. This is a good approach. It must be known by students in the future”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>