<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-bf8a55ed-5fe8-4985-b1bd-83e0a3950fb9" subtype="PC">
  <head>木蛭瘡</head>
  <div type="definition">, wood-leech sores</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="muzhichuang-91190" n="muzhichuang木蛭瘡">
      <form>
        <orth>木蛭瘡</orth>
        <pron>Mu zhi chuang</pron>
        <usg n="1">[1]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>, wood-leech sores</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Pathological Condition of chuang 瘡 , sores, conditions resulting from bodily contact with socalled ‘wood-leech’ insects found in the forests in South China. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry dan sha 丹砂 quoting Yi shuo 醫說 : 南方多雨，有物曰木癡，其大概類鼻涕，積陰而生 於古木之上，聞人氣則閃閃而動。人過其下，有墮於人體間者，即立成 瘡，久則遍其肌體。有客患其木癡之瘡，遇一道士謂曰：以硃砂、麝香 塗之即愈 , “In the South it often rains, and there is a thing called ‘wood simple’. It is as small as [a drop of] nasal snivel. It is an accumulation of yin, and lives up in old trees. When it smells human qi it flickers and begins to move. When that person passes by underneath it, it may drop on that person, and this immediately generates sores. After a long time, they will cover the entire body, and one suffers from ‘wooden simple sores’. I once met a Daoist who told me that smearing [a medication with the ingredients] zhu sha and she xian will cure it”, writes: 木蛭 瘡毒：南方多雨，有物曰木蛭，大類鼻涕，生於古木之上，聞人氣則閃 閃而動。人過其下，墮人體間，即立成瘡，久則遍體。惟以硃砂、麝香 塗之，即愈 , “The poison of wood-leech sores . In the South it often rains, and there is a thing called ‘wood leech’. It is as small as [a drop of] nasal snivel. It lives up in old trees. When it smells human qi it flickers and begins to move. When that person passes by underneath it, it may drop on that person, and this immediately generates sores. After a long time, they will cover the entire body. One only needs to smear [a medication with the ingredients] zhu sha and she xian on them, and this will bring the cure”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>