<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-c88781a8-5b43-4efd-b2a3-97b12f7426bc" subtype="EA">
  <head>飲</head>
  <div type="definition">rheum</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="yin-39154" n="yin飲">
      <form>
        <orth>飲</orth>
        <pron>Yin</pron>
        <usg n="p">[p]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>rheum</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>① Etiological Agent. of a clear, thin liquid that is excreted in the course of pathological changes affecting the depots and palaces and that accumulates in the body’s cavities and passageways. It may block the passage of qi and blood and thereby become a pathogenic factor. San yin ji yi bing zheng fang lun 三因極一病證方論 Mj: 喜怒憂思，致臟氣不行，鬱而生涎，涎結 為飲，隨氣上厥，伏留陽經，亦使人眩暈嘔吐 , “When joy, anger, grief, and pondering block the passage of the qi of the depots, it will be pent-up and generate saliva. The saliva congeals and forms rheum . It follows the qi upwards and abides deep inside the yang conduits. It may also cause dizziness and vomiting”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>② Pathological Condition Combined Designation of pathological conditions brought forth by rheum. Zhu bing yuan hou lun 諸病源候論 20: 其 為病也，或兩脅脹滿，或心胸煩悶，或眼暗口乾，或嘔逆短氣，諸候非 一，故云諸飲 , “Its pathology is such that in some cases both flanks experience a feeling of distension and fullness, or the region of heart and chest experiences vexation and pressure, or vision is dim and the mouth is dry, or one vomits with [qi] counterflow and experiences shortness of qi. The signs are many. Hence one speaks of ‘all types of rheum ’”. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Bai bing zhu zhi yao 百病主治藥： 飲有五：支、留、伏、溢、懸也 , “There are five types of rheum : propping [rheum], abiding [rheum], deep-lying [rheum], spillage [rheum], and suspended [rheum]”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>