<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-8500551a-c06f-4d8f-8055-1ac06f0d8f08" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>范蠡</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="MALES OF CHU" tls:concept-id="uuid-b7b55df5-1a0d-4d85-9dd5-62349744453b" xml:id="uuid-d371554d-9de8-4e60-bb92-26241d240459" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-651615a0-d362-4391-b7fa-1d6d286bf652 #uuid-84515989-6abd-46c2-800e-84502eaccf54">
<orth>范蠡</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">fàn lí</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">bomʔ rel</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">bi̯ɐm liɛ</pron>
            </form>
            <form corresp="#uuid-9f3eae93-cad4-41ec-966d-665e9ba7131f #uuid-db3012d1-670a-4989-8e8c-0e0d86c567ee">
<orth>少伯</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shào bó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">hmljews praaɡ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕiɛu pɣɛk</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-58f165e0-3787-4e1b-abea-e60ed5086250">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2020-04-18T21:12:31.918+09:00">Fàn Lí 范蠡 (5th century) from Chu is mentioned in HF 22.12 as a person in the service of &gt;Tian Chang 田常. But he served first under &gt;King Goujian of Yue 越王勾踐 (r. 496-465), where he had gone together with his friend &gt;Wen Zhong 文種, and he rose to the rank of a generalissimo after the important victory over the state of Wu 吳 in 473. Later, after a bitter defeat of Goujian at the hands of Wu, Fan Li spent three years as a hostage in Wu. When Yue had destroyed Wu, Fan Li fled by ship to the state of Qi 齊, where he took on the new name Chīyí Zĭpí 鴟夷子皮 under which he is mentioned in HF. In the rich state of Qi he accumulated legendary fortunes. According to GY Yueyu 2 he held a political theory of Yin and Yang turning into each other upon reaching an extreme degree. A work in two scrolls, bearing his name, is attributed to him in YIWENZHI. Fan Li died in Tao 陶, where he had acquired yet another name, Tai Zhugong 陶朱公. Under this name he is commonly referred to as a Croisus of ancient China. His remarkable story is told in SJ 129 and also, together with that of  his friend Wen Zhong 文種, many episodes of his life are presented in exquisite narrative detail in SJ 41.1741-47. [LSCQ 14.5] Unger no. 140 Personal Name: Shào Bó 少伯</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>