<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-86c226b6-d1f3-4d7b-8226-b6d1f34d7b9d" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>神會</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="ZEN MONKS" tls:concept-id="uuid-9c34821d-5c94-4128-96d8-9a46f9471f92" xml:id="uuid-3a5e0e7a-f798-40c2-8e1a-be13b4950bc8" n="2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-016736ec-dc49-4380-949d-4b154ea76807 #uuid-5cd2073a-6f30-434c-bf49-acee1f8e5bd7">
<orth>神會</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shén huì</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢljin ɡloobs</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʑin ɦɑi</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-4692d956-0479-4a55-afc9-b2ec15d7e873">GERNET 1977</ref>
<title>Entretiens du Maître de Dhyāna Chen-houei du Ho-tso (668-760)</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-44d6277e-65a4-4b01-bd68-d8ddaf7da930">LIEBENTHAL 1952</ref>
<title>The Sermon of Shen-hui Asia Major</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-392f9c5a-fe79-4c47-85a9-4be7cb9b6dc0">MCRAE 1986</ref>
<title>The Northern School and the Formation of Early Ch'an Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">240</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-fe337d45-bc91-4260-8024-5e94248f39a3">MCRAE 1987</ref>
<title>Shen-hui and the Teaching of Sudden Enlightenment in Early Ch'an Buddhism Sudden and Gradual</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-8e43c50b-dfe8-44b3-9c3a-bde37fdc5369">YANG ZENGWEN 1996</ref>
<title>神會和尚禪話錄 Shénhuì héshàng Chán huàlù The Recorded Sayings of Preceptor Shenhui</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-88fdbb45-165e-4aeb-ad52-678fa42ad69b" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: Hézé Shénhuí (Huize Shenhui) 荷澤神會 (684-758) was one of the most influential Zen monks of the 8th century, promoting Huìnéng 惠能 as the 'Sixth Patriarch'. In Chán history he is known for having caused a serious crisis within the early Chán movement. In 730 he initiated vigorous polemic attacks on members of the so-called 'Northern School' (an appellation he actually termed himself) and claimed to be the successor of the Sixth Patriarch Huìnéng. He was a very gifted rhetorician and was able to gather large audiences for his sermons. His popularity was possibly seen as a potential political threat and he was consequently banished from Cháng'ān in 753. During the following Ān Lǔshān rebellion he was rehabilitated due to his efforts to collect money for the Táng army by selling ordination certificates (on this issue see also CH'EN 1956B). According to the interpretation of MCRAE, Shénhuì contributed to the development of the Chán School mainly through his negative impact of splitting the Chán movement and the subsequent creative attempts by various factions to overcome the crisis. MCRAE thinks that the appearance of the Recorded Sayings genre in the Hóngzhōu 洪州 School of Mǎzǔ Dàoyī 馬祖道一 was one of the consquences of the deep crisis in the middle of the 8th century.</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>