<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-85194060-fa7e-44b1-9940-60fa7ea4b139" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>郜</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-59441e44-4a4d-44a5-aff5-ade686cc480d" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-8a5310e9-d5ae-4861-a79b-9b75432f34fe">
<orth>郜</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">gào</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kuuɡs</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɑu</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Gào 郜 (also written as 告) (CHEN PAN 1969, 391-397)

Clan: Jī 姬.

Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the CQ).

Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by one of the sons of the Zhōu King Wén 周文王 (according to the Shì běn).

Destroyed: Unknown. There are only three references to Gào in the CQ. In 713 B.C. (Yin 10), Lǔ 魯 conquered a city of Gào 郜, which belonged to Sòng 宋. Record for 710 B.C. (Huan 2) says that Lǔ 魯 received a bronze tripod of Gào (Gào dǐng 郜鼎) from the state of Sòng. Record for 640 B.C. (Xi 20) refers to the formal visit of the viscount of Gào 郜子 in the court of Lǔ. On the basis of this records, traditional Chinese scholars basically divided into two camps, as one regards the extermination of Gào: one suggested that Gào was conquered by Sòng already prior to the period recorded in the CQ (and Sòng thus got its ritual artifacts), and that its ruler who paid a visit to the Lǔ court was a ruler who lost his state (note a long time which passed between these events); the second propose that the cauldron got to Sòng not by conquest, and that the state of Gào was still in existence by 640 B.C. The record for 713 B.C. would support the first probability, but only if the city of Gào taken by Lǔ was identical with the former capital of the state of Gào, what is not certain (Du's commentary supposes it. On the contrary, Fàn zhì states that later, there were two places of this name distant one from the other about 20 miles; according to the text, one was formerly the capital of Gào and another belonged to Sòng). Generally, it seems to me more probable, that there were two places of this name, and that by 640 B.C., the state of Gào was still in existence.

Location: According to the Du's commentary and to the Fàn zhì, the capital of Gào was located in the modern Chéngwǔ 城武 district, Shandong province.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4391c6d2-ca0d-47e0-a5f3-efa3cf68f714">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Gào 郜 (also written as 告 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 391-397)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the CQ).Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by one of the sons of the Zhōu King Wén 周文王 (according to the Shì běn).Destroyed: Unknown. There are only three references to Gào in the CQ. In 713 B.C. (Yin 10), Lǔ 魯 conquered a city of Gào 郜, which belonged to Sòng 宋. Record for 710 B.C. (Huan 2) says that Lǔ 魯 received a bronze tripod of Gào (Gào dǐng 郜鼎 ) from the state of Sòng. Record for 640 B.C. (Xi 20) refers to the formal visit of the viscount of Gào 郜子 in the court of Lǔ. On the basis of this records, traditional Chinese scholars basically divided into two camps, as one regards the extermination of Gào: one suggested that Gào was conquered by Sòng already prior to the period recorded in the CQ (and Sòng thus got its ritual artifacts), and that its ruler who paid a visit to the Lǔ court was a ruler who lost his state (note a long time which passed between these events); the second propose that the cauldron got to Sòng not by conquest, and that the state of Gào was still in existence by 640 B.C. The record for 713 B.C. would support the first probability, but only if the city of Gào taken by Lǔ was identical with the former capital of the state of Gào, what is not certain (Du's commentary supposes it. On the contrary, Fàn zhì states that later, there were two places of this name distant one from the other about 20 miles; according to the text, one was formerly the capital of Gào and another belonged to Sòng). Generally, it seems to me more probable, that there were two places of this name, and that by 640 B.C., the state of Gào was still in existence. Location: According to the Du's commentary and to the Fàn zhì, the capital of Gào was located in the modern Chéngwǔ 城武 district, Shandong province. </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>