<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-d2dbdaf2-d670-432a-9568-e216c6b42cf7" subtype="PC">
  <head>邪魘</head>
  <div type="definition">evil nightmare</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="xieyan-76802" n="xieyan邪魘">
      <form>
        <orth>邪魘</orth>
        <pron>Xie yan</pron>
        <usg n="1">[1]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>evil nightmare</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Pathological Condition identical with yan mei 魘寐 . Sheng ji zong lu 聖濟總錄 5: 鬼氣、邪魘、屍厥、暴亡不省 人事等疾，至聖太一散方 , “For ailments such as demon qi, evil nightmares , corpse[-like condition because of qi] recession, sudden loss of consciousness with an inability to recognize people, resort to the recipe for the ’ powder to reach sagehood and great unity ’”. Xie yu 邪郁 , pent-up evil [qi] [1]</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Etiological Agent. identical with BCGM 郁①, yu pent-up [qi]. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry shui yin fen 水銀粉： 水銀乃至陰毒物，因火煅丹砂而出，加以鹽、礬煉而為輕粉，加以硫黃 升而為銀硃，輕飛靈變，化純陰為燥烈。其性走而不守，善劫痰涎，消 積滯。故水腫風痰、濕熱毒瘡被劫，涎從齒齦而出，邪郁為之暫開，而 疾因之亦愈 , “ Shui yin is a poisonous substance of extreme yin-quality. It is produced by means of a fire refinement process from cinnabar, another refinement with salt and fan creating qing fen , then sublimation with liu huang to generate yin zhu , then another modification by means of sublimation to create a pure yin-substance of extreme ferocity. Its nature is to move; it cannot be guarded. It is good in removing phlegm and saliva, and in dissolving accumulations of sluggish [qi]. Hence when it removes water swelling and wind phlegm, moisture heat and poison sores, if saliva emerges from the gums and pent-up evil [qi] is given a temporary opening there, then the cause of the ailment is cured too”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>