<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-d8e54a4b-27c0-4973-b8ee-b91c9c1f7633" subtype="PC">
  <head>傷寒壞證</head>
  <div type="definition">harm caused by cold with worsened signs</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="shanghanhuaizheng-102576" n="shanghanhuaizheng傷寒壞證">
      <form>
        <orth>傷寒壞證</orth>
        <pron>Shang han huai zheng</pron>
        <usg n="1">[1]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>harm caused by cold with worsened signs</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>Pathological Condition resulting from a mistaken treatment of shang han 傷寒 , harm caused by cold, with the result of an uncontrolled intermingling of yin and yang qi that is most difficult to cure. Pu ji fang 普濟方 140: 一法治傷寒壞證，時或發消渴，燥煩。用新 羅參不拘多少，煎湯，浸令水冷後，盛渴之時與之，頓服，熱則隨去。 大抵傷寒渴者，不可多與之水，水積胸中，便為結胸。然亦須濡沫之可 也 , “Another therapy pattern to cure harm caused by cold with worsened conditions . It may be that [patients] develop melting with thirst, restlessness and vexation. In this case take any amount of Korean ginseng and put it into boiling water to let it soak until the water is cold again. This is to be given [to the patient] at the moment when his thirst has reached a peak, to be ingested immediately. It will take away the heat. Generally speaking, patients with harm caused by cold must not be given much water when they are thirsty. The water would accumulate in their chest, resulting in a bound chest. It is quite possible, though, to [quench their thirst] by moistening [their mouth] with foam”. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry ren shen 人參：傷寒壞證：凡傷寒時疫，不問陰陽，老幼妊婦，誤服藥餌， 因重垂死，脈沉伏，不省人事，七日以後，皆可服之，百不失一 , “ Harm caused by cold with worsened conditions : Whenever in a time of epidemic harm caused by cold [a treatment is initiated] regardless of whether yin or yang [conduits are affected], and regardless of whether [patients] are old or young, or perhaps pregnant women, and if as a result the wrong medication is ingested, [the disease] will worsen so much that [the patient] may die. The movement in the vessels is deep inside and hidden; he fails to recognize people or things. After seven days any [patient] can ingest this. There will be not a single loss in a hundred cases”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>