<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-9dca34b5-1695-4d91-b9a7-77049d850fe2" subtype="PC">
  <head>陰毒</head>
  <div type="definition">yin poison</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="yindu-66114" n="yindu陰毒">
      <form>
        <orth>陰毒</orth>
        <pron>Yin du</pron>
        <usg n="80">[80]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>yin poison</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>① Pathological Condition</def>
        <def>a) of shang han 傷寒 , harm caused by cold, resulting in a flourishing of only yang qi and a diminution of yin qi, with cold extremities and a greenish facial complexion, pain in the abdomen and affecting the entire body, as well as a deep-lying and fine movement in the vessels. Jin gui yao lue 金匱要略 Fj: 陰毒之為病，面目青， 身痛如被杖，咽喉痛 , “The disease of yin poison is as follows: the face and eyes are greenish. The body aches as if flogged with a stick. The throat aches”.</def>
        <def>b) Brought forth by being struck by xi du 溪毒 , rivulet poison, with ulcers in the body’s lower parts as if caused by the insect stingers or fish. Zhou hou bei ji fang 肘後備急方 7: 若瘡如 蠡魚齒者為陰毒 , “If there are ulcers that appear to result from insect [stingers] or fish teeth, then this is yin poison ”.</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>② Etiological Agent. identical with du qi 毒氣 , poison qi, with a cold quality. Qian jin bei ji fang 千金備急方 19: 陰毒 內行，臟腑受客邪之氣，則病生矣 , “When yin poison moves inside and the depots and palaces receive visitor evil qi, a disease is generated”. ③ Pharmacological Quality of pharmaceutical substances with a poisonous nature of massive cold”. Zheng lei ben cao 證類本草 Substance Entry qian 鉛 quotes Tai qing fu lian ling sha fa 太清服煉靈砂法 : 錫鉛…服之而多陰毒，傷人心胃 , “Tin and lead, if one consumes them one ingests much yin poison , and this will harm the heart and stomach”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>