<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-997db914-7664-4587-9487-c73a959597f2" subtype="IS">
  <head>身顫</head>
  <div type="definition">the body shivers</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="shenchan-75542" n="shenchan身顫">
      <form>
        <orth>身顫</orth>
        <pron>Shen chan</pron>
        <usg n="2">[2]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>the body shivers</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Illness Sign of the entire body displaying an uncontrolled trembling movement. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry lu 驢 quotes Shi yi xin jing 食醫心鏡 : 主中風頭眩，心肺浮熱，手足無力，筋骨煩疼，言 語似澀，一身動搖。烏驢頭一枚，燖洗如法，蒸令極熟，細切，更於豉 汁內煮，著五味調，點少酥食， ”To master wind stroke with a dizzy head: the [movement in the vessels of] the heart and lung is at the surface, associated with heat. Hands and feet lack strength. The sinews and bones are vexed and painful. Language appears rough, and the entire body sways. Wash and prepare with fire 1 head of a black donkey according to the rules. Steam it until it is very well done. Cut it into fine slices and boil them in the juice of salted, fermented beans. Regulate with the five flavors, heat until crisp, and eat”, writes: 中風頭 眩：心肺浮熱，肢軟骨疼，語蹇身顫。用烏驢頭一枚，如食法，豉汁煮 食 , “Wind stroke with a dizzy head: the [movement in the vessels of] heart and lung is at the surface, associated with heat. The limbs are soft and the bones ache. Speech is impaired, and the body shivers . Take 1 head of a black donkey and prepare as if it were for a meal. Then boil with salted, fermented beans, and eat this”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>