<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-93864d3d-e248-470e-85c6-ae5c2b92d247" subtype="IS">
  <head>四肢厥急</head>
  <div type="definition">recession with tension in the four limbs</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="sizhijueji-101191" n="sizhijueji四肢厥急">
      <form>
        <orth>四肢厥急</orth>
        <pron>Si zhi jue ji</pron>
        <usg n="1">[1]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>recession with tension in the four limbs</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Illness Sign identical with si zhi ju ji 四肢拘急 , cramps and tension of the four limbs. Possibly a writing error in the Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry zhu dan 豕膽 quoting from the Zhu jie shang han lun 註解傷寒論 7  : 吐已下斷，汗出而厥，四肢拘急不解，脈微欲絕者，通脈四逆加豬膽 汁湯主之 , “When the vomiting has ended and the discharge has been halted, while [the patient continues] to sweat [in a manner] associated with recession, so that the four limbs are cramped with tension, and the [movement in the] vessels is so weak that it is at the brink of being cut off, then the ‘decoction to penetrate the vessels in the case of counterflow in the four [limbs]’ with added hog bile will control this”, writes: 霍亂病吐下已斷，汗出而厥，四肢厥急，脈微欲絶 者，通脈四逆湯加豬膽汁主之 , “When in the treatment of cholera, the vomiting and the discharge have been halted, while [the patient continues] to sweat [in a manner] associated with recession, so that the four limbs have recession with tension , and the [movement in the] vessels is so weak that it is at the brink of being cut off, then the ‘decoction to penetrate the vessels in the case of counterflow in the four [limbs] with added hog bile’ will master this”. Si zhi jue leng 四肢厥冷 , recession with cold in the four limbs [4]</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Illness Sign identical with si zhi ni leng 四肢逆冷 , counterflow with cold in the four limbs. Qian jin bei ji fang 千金備急方 9: 唇青面黑，四肢厥冷，其脈沉細緊數 , “The lips are greenish-blue, the face is black. There is recession with cold in the four limbs . The [movement in the] vessels is in the depth, fine, tight, and frequent”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>