<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-9b4e0cf3-bc32-4e6e-896f-9ec1ac1d899d" subtype="PC">
  <head>赤火丹毒</head>
  <div type="definition">red fire cinnabar poison</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="chihuodandu-112602" n="chihuodandu赤火丹毒">
      <form>
        <orth>赤火丹毒</orth>
        <pron>Chi huo dan du</pron>
        <usg n="1">[1]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>red fire cinnabar poison</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Pathological Condition identical with chi you dan du 赤游丹毒 , red roaming cinnabar poison. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry yun tai 芸薹 quotes SSM : 貞觀七年三月，予在內江縣飲多，至夜 覺四體骨肉疼痛。至曉頭痛，額角有丹如彈丸，腫痛。至午通腫，目不 能開。經日幾斃。予思本草芸薹治風游丹腫，遂取葉搗傅，隨手即消， 其驗如神也。亦可搗汁服之 , “During the zhen guan reign period I was in Neijian country where I drank a lot. At night I felt pain in the bones and flesh of all four extremities. At dawn my head ached. On one of my temples I had a cinnabar [poisoning] resembling a bullet. It was swollen and painful. At noon the entire region was swollen, and I could no longer open my eyes. After several days I came close to dying. Then I recalled that the Ben cao lists yun tai to cure wind roaming cinnabar [poison] swelling. I took its leaves, ground them and smeared [the pulp onto the affected region. The swelling] disappeared immediately. A miraculous effect, indeed. It is also possible to pound it to a juice for internal ingestion”. The term feng you dan zhong 風游丹腫 , wind roaming cinnabar swelling, appears in the subsequent section Fu fang 附方 , Additional Recipes, modified to: chi you dan du 赤火丹毒 , red fire cinnabar poison .</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>