<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-6d27b9c5-5698-47e6-a7b9-c5569827e67b" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>芮</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-05d3d9ee-3369-4436-8a5f-b2f1bcf26a0e" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4553d2aa-5d96-44fc-8b18-c4158c427118">
<orth>芮</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">ruì</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">njobs</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ȵiɛi</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Ruī 芮 (also written as 汭; in the bronze inscriptions, it appears as Nèi 內) (CHEN PAN 1969, 399-407)

Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the Shì běn; in the inscription on the Ly wáng hú is mentioned the woman called Nèi Jī內姬).

Rank: Bó 伯 (usual in the ZUO).

Founded: The state was obviously established quite early in the Western Zhōu period, as in the Gùmìng chapter of the Shū jīng the Earl of Rùi 芮伯 is listed among the persons which attended the Zhōu King Chéng 周成王 in his deathbed.

Destroyed: In 640 B.C. (Xi 20) by Qín 秦 (according to the Shǐ jì, Shíèr zhūhóu niánbiǎo and Qín běnjì chapters).

Location: According to the Hàn zhì, the state of Ruī was located in the modern Dàlì 大荔 district, Shǎnxī province. Dì míng kǎolyè locates it into the modern Cháoyì 朝邑 district, neighboring with Dàlì district.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-69537f24-6170-49d4-b5c4-c32aa2fa87d7">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Ruī 芮 (also written as 汭; in the bronze inscriptions, it appears as Nèi 內 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 399-407)Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the Shì běn; in the inscription on the Ly wáng hú is mentioned the woman called Nèi Jī 內姬 ).Rank: Bó 伯 (usual in the ZUO).Founded: The state was obviously established quite early in the Western Zhōu period, as in the Gùmìng chapter of the Shū jīng the Earl of Rùi 芮伯 is listed among the persons which attended the Zhōu King Chéng 周成王 in his deathbed. Destroyed: In 640 B.C. (Xi 20) by Qín 秦 (according to the Shǐ jì, Shíèr zhūhóu niánbiǎo and Qín běnjì chapters).Location: According to the Hàn zhì, the state of Ruī was located in the modern Dàlì 大荔 district, Shǎnxī province. Dì míng kǎolyè locates it into the modern Cháoyì 朝邑 district, neighboring with Dàlì district. </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>