<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-6fc5a0b6-a167-4ee1-85a0-b6a1674ee1cd" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>重疊</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="RELATION" tls:concept-id="uuid-87a0729f-0c38-4ded-950b-0cb39f37e6f9" xml:id="uuid-4b30264a-2fab-49ea-b445-827b8bdcde3c" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-8c55346f-af41-4abc-98c3-f226ec45a221 #uuid-424919fe-127c-4e37-ad92-ef6be7854f85">
<orth>重疊</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chóng dié</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">doŋ dɯɯb</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖi̯oŋ dep</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-bab1bc49-42c5-4a77-bf9d-a8520c4c11a0">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-091af450-64e0-4b82-98a2-84d0444b6d19">VPi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-b110bae1-02d5-4c66-ad13-7c04b3ee3ad9">mathematical term</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>CHEMLA 2003: have a common divisor (first occurs in Liu Hui's commentary to JZ)Background: Number theory was developed in ancient Greece, and little elaborated in ancient China. An example being that you have no concept of a prime number in ancient Chinese sources, whereas the Greek concept of a prime number played a significant part in Euclid's book 7. Chóng dié is important because it does constitute one of the rare examples of number theory concepts in ancient China.The concept of chóng dié is approached through a geometrical representation of a number. Thus the number six can be represented as a series******or as piled-up (dié) diads:* ** ** *The number four will be* ** *Now the use of repeated elements in this representation is called chóng dié, and this method constitutes a visual approach to the concept of one concept of a common divisor number theory. Chóng dié occurs when two numbers are considered in relation with each other, and if both are reiterations with the same base layer, then simplification takes the form of dividing by the number of shared elements in one horizontal row.JZ 1.6, Liu Hui's comm: 其所以相減者皆等數之重疊 "The reason why they are subtracted from each other is that they all are reiterated "pilings-up" of the equal number (i.e. the common divisor)"JZ 1.18, Liu Hui's comm: 分重疊則約也 "if the parts are reiteration "pilings up", then one simplifies (scil. by dividing by the number of shared elements in one horizontal row)."</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>