<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-63dcc180-bd9d-4bff-9cc1-80bd9d2bff82" n="6">
    <form>
        <orth>商</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="TONE" tls:concept-id="uuid-3b0e1fc6-f5ab-4fc2-9b4a-cb3039c44f17" xml:id="uuid-b1def313-e8a7-4cdc-855f-e9177d8ddaf0" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-ce5dfd21-7d74-4fe9-9abb-f28f250a6144">
<orth>商</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shāng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-8b0edd39-0c22-4c9d-8a75-e4b07920b89e">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>tone shāng</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="MERCHANT" tls:concept-id="uuid-b3fe42b5-03c3-4bd8-bc21-ebb16e6f50f8" xml:id="uuid-db60e95f-3c53-4d60-af08-fc88af78a196" n="10">
            <form corresp="#uuid-ce5dfd21-7d74-4fe9-9abb-f28f250a6144">
<orth>商</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shāng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>The general term for an itinerant trader is shāng 商; the general term for a sedatory trader or merchant is gǔ 賈.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d2c6ed11-6528-4235-bf9c-05e01ffcfa8b" n="9">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos/>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-20a87134-926d-4be7-8815-246c1f7a9ca7">n[adN]</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-1ddeb9e4-67de-4466-b517-24cfd829f3de">N=hum</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>(itinerant) trader; generally: person engaged in trading</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e7a439ef-cc27-4b96-9828-2d3e7b08bde4" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-f55cff2f-f0e3-4f08-a89c-5d08fcf3fe89">act</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>act as a merchant is expected to</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="DISCUSS" tls:concept-id="uuid-c5280909-0367-44d7-b6e2-5a9280a661f6" xml:id="uuid-2367ef1e-ec04-427c-b1e1-9241c152bad4" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-ce5dfd21-7d74-4fe9-9abb-f28f250a6144">
<orth>商</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shāng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-201f35d2-21db-4fa3-bae4-38d6a5295567">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-b110bae1-02d5-4c66-ad13-7c04b3ee3ad9">mathematical term</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>CHEMLA 2003:</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="ASSESS" tls:concept-id="uuid-61b7cc2a-3b06-462f-88f7-4f1c0ca92e64" xml:id="uuid-76d64576-5af7-49e6-9096-36f44f3840ad" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-ce5dfd21-7d74-4fe9-9abb-f28f250a6144">
<orth>商</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shāng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1e683846-f702-4358-abbf-a8ec8c81f30a">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>assess relative profitability of</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="TRADE" tls:concept-id="uuid-801e68eb-2926-4317-85ca-549e109b72d8" xml:id="uuid-279227fc-70db-440a-8b2e-d0bb767ae4a8" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-ce5dfd21-7d74-4fe9-9abb-f28f250a6144">
<orth>商</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shāng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-47b3d89e-ce0d-411c-b344-9c379af14af8" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-76be1df4-3d73-4e5f-bbc2-729542645bc8">nab</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>trade</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-e0b9c167-acda-4852-8e3d-4e814c2f9d07" n="2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-ce5dfd21-7d74-4fe9-9abb-f28f250a6144">
<orth>商</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shāng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Shāng 商 (also called Yīn 殷)

Clan: Zǐ 子.

Rank: Wáng 王.

Founded: The mythical story about the origin of the Shāng is described in the Yīn běnjì chapter of SJ and in the poem Xuán niǎo of the Shī jīng. According to these accounts, the first ancestor of the Shāng was Xiè 契, whose mother conceived when she swallowed an egg dropped by a black bird. SJ then records the names of the fourteen predynastic ancestors, and then thirty dynastic kings starting with Chéng Tāng 成湯, who was supposed to defeat the legendary Xià 夏 dynasty (according to the traditional dates, it should happen either in 1766 BC or about 1550 BC). The list of kings in SJ bassically matches the list of Shāng ancestors in the oracle bone inscriptions.

Destroyed: In 1045 BC (according to the most reliable chronology) the Shāng was defeated and conquered by the Zhōu 周. Zhōu king then gave the former area of Shāng to Wǔ Gēng 武庚, the son of the last Shāng ruler. This later revolted and was defeated and killed.

Location: There are different opinions concerning the former homeland of the Shāng people, the locations of which range from the southwestern Hebei, over the eastern Henan to the western Shandong. This question can be hardly answered.
According to the Yīn bějì chapter of SHI, the Shāng capital shifted five times. The first capital of Chéng Tāng was called Bó 亳, then it shifted to Ao, then to Xiāng 相 and Xíng 邢, and eventually (under the king Pán Gēng 盤庚) to the last capital, called Yīn 殷, fromwhere the last twelve Shāng kings ruled. In Chinese traditional historiography as well as in the modern hstoriography and archaeology, there has been large discussion about the location of these capitals. It is quite accepted that the last capital was in modern Ānyáng 安陽, northeastern Henan, where the large late Shāng center dating at least from the period of the reign of the last nine Shāng kings was excavated. However, the name Yīn does not appear in the oracle bone inscriptions where the capital of Shāng is referred to as the Great (or Heavenly) city Shāng, Dà yì Shāng 大邑商 (it is even not certain whether this capital was identical with th Shāng city in Ānyáng).
Some of the previous capitals are often (mainly by Chinese archaeologists) identified with some of the major sites of the Bronze Age, but this identification is far from being certain. Thus the first capital of Bó is identified either with the huge city excavated in Zhèngzhōu 鄭州 or with the even earlier site of Èrlǐtóu 二里頭 in the modern Yǎnshī 偃師 district, central Henan. Zhèngzhōu is sometimes also identified with the second capital of Ao. Note that just recenty, another large walled city (called by the archaeologists the Shāng city of Huánběi) was excavated just to the north of the Late Shāng settlement in Ānyáng. The city is later than the occupation of Zhèngzhōu, but antedates the Late Shāng occupation in Ānyáng.

History: Besides the traditional accounts in the later texts (mainly the Yīn běnjì chapter of SJ), Shāng history is mainly known from the oracle bone inscriptions uncovered in Ānyáng and dating from the reign of the last nine Shāng kings (beginning with Wǔ Dīng 武丁; the inscriptions cover approximately the period 1200-1045 BC). As have been mentioned above, the list of the Shāng predynastic rulers and kings given in SJ is considerably in accordance with the lists of Shāng ancestors in the oracle bone inscriptions. In the later accounts, the Shāng state is said to grow to power when the king Chéng Tāng (called Dà Yǐ 大乙 in the inscriptions) defeated the last ruler of the rather legendary Xià dynasty. However, this tradition is not attested in the inscriptions. The first period of the existence of the Shāng state is often identified with the period of existence of the so-called Èrlǐgǎng 二里崗 culture (ca 16th-14th century BC), when the main centre of northern China was the walled city in Zhèngzhōu. Many characteristic features of the later Shāng culture developed at that period, mainly the large-scale production of bronze ritual vessels and weapons. On the basis of the archaeological investigations it seems that Zhèngzhōu was a centre of a quite centralized state controlling large areas spanning over the most of the area of central China and as far to the south as the middle reaches of the Chángjiāng 長江 River.
After the end of the Èrlǐgāng period, it seems that there was some crisis leading to the fragmentation of the centralized control and to the diminishion of the territory under the Shāng control. The Shāng kings ruling from Ānyáng (the period ca between 1200-1045 BC; the archaeological culture of the period is called Yīnxū 殷墟) controlled much smaller area (basically northeastern Henan) and relied heavily on the very unstable system of political, ritual and kin alliances with smaller polities. In the beginning of the period, there was quite a large expansion under the King Wǔ Dīng, but later the Shāng lost some allies mainly in the area of western Shānxī. During that time, the Zhōu state in Shǎnxī province grew to the power, and in 1045 BC Zhōu defeated the last Shāng king Dì Xīn 帝辛 (or Zhòu 紂, who is depicted as a wicked and cruel despot in the later texts) and put an end to the existance of the Shāng state.
Shāng culture was extremely important in the formation of the Chinese culture, as any basic elements of the latter emerged in the Shāng period (including the writing system).
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ec91cdff-6ef5-4743-b8a7-8b8ddff98881" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a dynasty and of a tribe</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>