<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-6d84da03-0a22-4917-84da-030a2259172b" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>滕</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-f0307ddd-444b-4554-b287-9c2c5cd0356d" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-a2031609-27ec-4759-9770-99d3b4649cfb">
<orth>滕</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">téng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lɯɯŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dəŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Téng 滕 (CHEN PAN 1969, 63-67)

Clan: Jī姬.

Rank: Hóu 侯 (usual in the CQ and ZUO).

Founded: In the early Western Zhou period by Shūxiù 叔繡, the son of King Wén of Zhōu 周文王 (according to the Shì běn; also ZUO mentions that the founder of Téng was the son of King Wén).

Location: In the modern Téng 滕 district, Shandong province. One of the small walled cities excavated in the area and dating from the end of Shāng to Eastern Zhōu times was probably the capital of Téng (see Li Xueqin, DONG ZHOU QIN WENMING).

Destroyed: Uncertain. The state was still in existence by the end of the period recorded in CQ. It was preserved till the end of the 4th century, when its ruler is mentioned in the Mèngzǐ. Later, it was probably conquered by Qí 齊 (according to the Shì běn and Hàn zhì). Other sources state that Téng was destroyed either by Yuè 越 (Gǔ běn Zhúshū jìnián) or by Sòng 宋 (Zhàn guó cè). Sòng was in 286 B.C. conquered by Qí, and it is possible that Téng was actually destroyed by Sòng and the area later came under the control of Qí.

History: Téng was a small petty state dependant mainly on Qí. In the CQ, it appears for the first time in 716 B.C. (Yin 7). The state is remarkable for the stay of Mencius in the court of the Duke Wén of Téng 滕文公.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-96111bd5-67b6-41d2-ae6c-1fdc48652f65" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a minor state</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>