<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-6a381b3c-a4e1-445d-b81b-3ca4e1845db3" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>舍利</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="ASH" tls:concept-id="uuid-a4082d41-8d5a-49e4-8fae-a2728c892bec" xml:id="uuid-56e0b9c8-8f31-4d0f-8333-81922badc29a" n="10">
            <form corresp="#uuid-3c1879b8-3bd0-413a-95b5-69d2f36731e5 #uuid-deb30ca3-b3e5-4954-b5fa-b8a95d259fc4">
<orth>舍利</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shě lì</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lʰaʔ rids</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕɣɛ li</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-9d1f23b7-b94b-41d4-97fb-9ed2d214e466">KIESCHNICK 2003</ref>
<title>The Impact of Buddhim on Chinese Material Culture</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">29-52</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"This is an excellent introduction to the important role which relics played in the history of Chinese Buddhism. Kieschnick concludes: "In the case of relic pellets (sheli), sacred power was vague and impersonal, a living source of light that could appear from nowhere and at times reproduce itself. Devotees occasionally perceived other objects such as particular Buddhist scriptures, rosaries, or other belongings of holy figures as having this same power, but these objects were not accorded sacred power as consistently as relics were. This perception of the power of relics did not spring from a more general belief in a sacred man-like force present in all things; only a very limited number of objects were conceived in this way." (p.80)</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-ac37309d-3f15-4508-ba8d-edce6a5a115f">PRZYLUSKI 1936</ref>
<title>Le Partage des reliques du Buddha Mélange chinois et bouddhiques</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-cc798cad-c363-435c-bc36-727d84578220">SGSZ</ref>
<title>宋高僧傳 Sòng gāosēng zhuàn The Song Dynasty Record of Eminent Monks Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">830c</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"There is even an account of a parrot that left behind grains of crystalline sSariira because it had been taught to repeat the name of a buddha." (KIESCHNICK 2003: 35)</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-3e8cbf98-2456-44a3-aaae-251a7b2f9bfb">STRONG 1983</ref>
<title>The Legend of King Asoka</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">109-118</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>According to Buddhist tradition, several hundred years after the death of Buddha King AsSoka collected his remains and distributed them among 84,000 stuupas.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-a6776185-23ed-401a-85a3-2116f86c90e3">THOMAS 1975</ref>
<title>The Life of Buddha as Legend and History</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">160-161</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-64d2e9f4-1306-45bf-8d0b-64702410f4c0">XUGAOSENGZHUAN</ref>
<title>續高僧傳 Xù gāosēng zhuàn Continued Records of Eminent Monks Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">510a</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>Story about the monk Huihai (550-606), dealing with the miraculous powers of Buddist remains, in this case healing a deseased who repented in front of the relics (see KIESCHNICK 2003: 35).</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e2e1e667-68f5-4a78-8183-33a6a9aa5254" n="10">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-ebc1516d-e718-4b5b-ba40-aa8f43bd0e86">NPm</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: relics of the Buddha or occasionally of another famous Buddhist monk; relic pellets (referring to the crystalline remains left over after cremation) SANSKRIT Śarīra</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>