<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-afef0495-05ea-4377-b526-822dd509173c">
<head>ACCOMPANY</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>TRAVEL WITH</item>
<item>PARTNER</item>
<item>ESCORT</item>
<item>CHAPERONE</item>
<item>ATTEND</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">陪伴</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">伴</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>FOLLOW AND be TOGETHER with, TYPICALLY so as to SERVE.</p>
    <div type="definition" resp="#CH" modified="2022-07-20T19:00:38.303+09:00">
            <p>FOLLOW AND be TOGETHER with, TYPICALLY so as to SERVE or HELP.</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>[ASCENDING/DESCENDING]</p>
<p>[GENERAL or SPECIALISED]</p>
<p>[GRAMMATICALISED/LEXICAL]</p>
<p>[HIERARCHICAL/NON-HIERARCHICAL]</p>
<p>[MOVING/STATIONARY]</p>
<p>1. The general word for accompanying someone of superior status is probably shì 侍 refers to polite attendance upon a master or leader, typically while in residence, but occasionally also on journeys. See SERVE.</p>
<p>[ASCENDING], [STATIONARY]</p>
<p>2. Péi 陪 typically refers to accompanying someone who is moving, and it adds to the literal meaning of accompaniment of a superior that of general support.</p>
<p>[ASCENDING], [MOVING]</p>
<p>3. Jù 俱 and xié 偕 refer to a symmetric relation of togetherness rather than the transitive action of accompaniment of a superior. See TOGETHER.</p>
<p>[GENERAL], [NON-HIERARCHICAL]</p>
<p>4. Yǔ 與 adds to the notion of accompaniment that of tactical association, the siding with someone, and occasionally the latter nuance is stronger than the meaning "to accompany" so that the word comes to mean purely "to side with".</p>
<p>[DESCENDING!]</p>
<p>5. Ba4n 伴 is to keep company as a friend.</p>
<p>6. Co2ng 從 is to keep company as a follower.</p>
<p>7. So4ng 送 is to keep company with someone who is leaving.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>陪伴 is a current modern word for accompaniment.</p>
<p>陪 is a more informal word for accompanying a person.</p>
<p>陪同 focusses on the subservient status of the accompanying person.</p>
<p>隨同 focusses on the very low status of the accompanying person.</p>
<p>伴隨 refers to a more than very short-term spell of accompanying.</p>
<p>奉陪 refers to exceedingly polite accompanying of a guest etc..</p>
<p>伴</p>
<p>first rough draft to identify synonym group members for future analysis, based on CL. 18.11.2003. CH</p>
        </div>
<div type="old-chinese-contrasts">
<p>1. The person accompanied may be obligatorily of distinctly higher status (péi 陪, shì 侍 ), or that person may be of any status (jiē 偕, jù 俱, yǔ 與 )</p>
<p>2. The togetherness may be primarily in terms of physical vicinity (shì 侍, jiē 偕, péi 陪 ) or it may be in terms of forms of forms of collaborative togetherness that are not essentially spatial (yǔ 與 ).</p>
<p>3. The togetherness may include the notion of support (yǔ 與, péi 陪, shì 侍 ), or it may be more simply a matter of intentional spatial proximity (all others [JP]).</p>
<p>4. The notion of togetherness may be typically grammaticalised and adverbial (jiē 偕, jù 俱 ), or it may be ungrammaticalised and fully verbal (all others).</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="wordnet">
            <item>202025550</item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c43f4c45-617b-4e09-8cb1-17917eb759fb">FOLLOW</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>ACCOMPANY</p>
<p>comitari refers to the autonomous act of accompanying someone out of one's own perceived best interests.</p>
<p>deducere refers to the accompanying someone out of a sense of friendship duty, often in an officious way.</p>
<p>prosequi refers to the decision to follow someone as a demonstrative deep respect and even reverence.</p>
<p/>
<p>MOVE TO DOEDERLEIN</p>
<p>SELF-INTERESTED or ALTRUISTIC</p>
<p>INCONSPICUOUS or DEMONSTRATIVE</p>
<p>comitari refers to the autonomous act of accompanying someone out of one's own perceived best interests. SELF-INTERESTED</p>
<p>deducere refers to the accompanying someone out of a sense of friendship duty, often in an officious way. ALTRUISTIC</p>
<p>prosequi refers to the decision to follow and accompany someone as a demonstrative act of deep respect and even reverence. DEMONSTRATIVE</p>
<p/>
<p>LW</p>
<p/>
<p>comitor, comitari, comitatus sum  V     1 1  DEP   [XXXAO]  </p>
<p>join as an attendant, guard/escort; accompany, follow; attend (funeral);</p>
<p/>
<p/>
<p>secor, seci, secutus sum  V     3 1  DEP   [XXXAO]  </p>
<p>follow; escort/attend/accompany; aim at/reach after/strive for/make for/seek;</p>
<p/>
<p/>
<p>sequor, sequi, secutus sum  V     3 1  DEP   [XXXAO]  </p>
<p>follow; escort/attend/accompany; aim at/reach after/strive for/make for/seek;</p>
<p/>
<p/>
<p>cingo, cingere, cinxi, cinctus  V     3 1  TRANS   [XXXAO]  </p>
<p>surround/encircle/ring; enclose; beleaguer; accompany; gird, equip; ring (tree);</p>
<p/>
<p>adsector, adsectari, adsectatus sum  V     1 1  DEP   [XXXCO]  </p>
<p>accompany, attend, escort; support, be an adherent, follow; court (fame);</p>
<p/>
<p/>
<p>assector, assectari, assectatus sum  V     1 1  DEP   [XXXCO]  </p>
<p>accompany, attend, escort; support, be an adherent, follow; court (fame);</p>
<p/>
<p>*</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">104</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>comitari is the general word, and the person accompanied is the most important person.</p>
<p>prosequi is an elevated word referring to a accompanying a person as a sign of politeness and reverence.</p>
<p>stipare  refers to protective accompaniment by a group, typically of soldiers and the like.</p>
<p>sectari is intensitive and refers to a permanent habit or practice of accompanying someone everywhere.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">

















    </div>
</div>