<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-97483661-3867-4186-8773-6c838831ab4f">
<head>APOLOGISE</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">道歉</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">謝</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">

    <p resp="#CH" modified="2020-11-06T19:37:17.542+09:00">ADMIT that one has in the PAST been GUILTY of BAD ACT AND DECLARE that one REGRETS this. </p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>NB: There is, so far, no sufficient basis to distinguish between the meanings of these words, which are rare in this meaning.</p>
<p>1. Xiè 謝 is the standard word to use, but, surprisingly, the word is quite rare.</p>
<p>2. Cí 辭 can perhaps be taken to emphasise the explanations made on the occasion of apologising, but examples are too few to be sure.</p>
<p>3. Qǐng 請 emphasises, perhaps, the implicit request for the apology to be accepted, but examples are too few to be sure.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>道歉 is the standard word referring to an apology.</p>
<p>致歉 refers in a formal way to the offer of an apology.</p>
<p>賠罪 refers in a formal way to an apology for a serious transgression involving guilt.</p>
<p>賠禮 refers in a formal way to an apology for a transgression involving impropriety.</p>
<p>陪禮</p>
<p>賠話 focusses on the linguistic form of an apology.</p>
<p>賠不是 focusses on the action of asking forgiveness for a wrong-doing.</p>
<p>賠小心 focusses on the action of asking forgiveness, typically for an error of reprehensible thoughtlessness.</p>
<p>賠禮道歉</p>
<p>賠</p>
<p>對不起</p>
<p>對不住</p>
<p>勞駕</p>
<p>first rough draft to identify synonym group members for future analysis 18.11.2003. CH/</p>
        </div>
<div type="old-chinese-contrasts">
<p>Surprisingly, all the usages are not very common and therefore it is hard to be sure of the nuances expressed.</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-cb7c9367-3450-498c-abd8-0214184d6428">BOAST</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-5a62b4b0-8b8c-43fd-87d2-bc767d5a2000">ADMIT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>APOLOGIZE</p>
<p>purgatio consists, like justification, in clearing oneself of a suspicion or accusation by proving it to be groundless.</p>
<p>exusatio "excuse", refes to acknowledging that one has done somethng wrong, but asserting subjective innocence, i.e. claiming that the wrong was committed by mistake.</p>
<p>satisfactio "attonement" is the satisfaction made to the suffering party of some wrong, or the injured party, in case of innocence.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b425a52b-7c3a-4b26-a4a5-8c5a55eaf19b">GRACE ZHANG 2010</ref>
<title>Using Chinese Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">83</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">









    </div>
</div>