<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-82e84859-f76f-44cd-be74-020f2a4fb6a1">
<head>ARMY</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>ARMED FORCE</item>
<item>MILITARY FORCE</item>
<item>LAND FORCE</item>
<item>MILITARY</item>
<item>SOLDIERY</item>
<item>INFANTRY</item>
<item>MILITIA</item>
<item>TROOPS</item>
<item>SOLDIERS</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">軍隊</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">軍</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>BIG GROUP of SOLDIERS TYPICALLY CONTROLLED by a RULER OR GOVERNMENT.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>[ARCHAIC/CURRENT]</p>
<p>[GENERAL/SPECIFIC]</p>
<p>[IMPERSONAL/PERSONIFIED]</p>
<p>[MOBILE/STATIONARY]</p>
<p>[LARGE/SMALL]</p>
<p>1. Bīng 兵 "armed force" focusses on the weapons ready for use and may refer to any military grouping.</p>
<p>[GENERAL]</p>
<p>2. Jūn 軍 is a complete army as a unit, from Spring and Autumn times onwards, normally attached to an army camp. Complete parts of an army are always jūn 軍, rarely shī 師. Hence the expressions sān jūn 三軍, zhōng jūn 中軍, shàng jūn 上軍, xià jūn 下軍. An army is counted by the number of jūn 軍 in it, where each jūn 軍 is said to be 10 000 men, at least in the Qi system. Systems have varied in different states. For detals of the early history see the monograph by KOLB.</p>
<p>[IMPERSONAL], [LARGE], [OFFICIAL]</p>
<p>3. Shī 師 refers generally to troops a military force on a campaign, not necessarily a complete army. ZUO Ding 4.1.6 commentators quantify an armed force as consisting of 2500 men, in one exceptional context. One often speaks of 三軍之師, never of 三師之軍. One asks for troops 請／乞師, and not for jūn 軍 which would be asking for the whole army of a friendly state. The troops of another state one uses are always shī 師 (e.g. 衛人以燕師伐鄭 ), one's own troops can be described as jūn 軍 or shī 師 almost indifferently. One offers food to the enemy shī 師, not to their jūn 軍. (HF 23.27:01) There are ruì shī 銳師 "crack troops" but no ruì jūn 銳軍 "crack army". Similarly, 楚師之良. The shī 師 may be said to hear about something 師聞之, not the jūn 軍.</p>
<p>[GENERAL], [MOBILE], [PERSONIFIED!]</p>
<p>4. Lu# 旅 is an archaic word for armed forces in any combatant or non-combatant function, and in ZUO Ding 4.1.6 it is quantified to consist of 500 men, and.</p>
<p>[ARCHAIC], [SMALL]</p>
<p>5. Duì 隊 is common in Han texts for a division in the army, the size of this division could vary, but did not exceed the hundreds. SEE ALSO BATALLION</p>
<p>[SMALL]</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006 WARFARE 2.</p>
<p>師，商周軍隊的高級編制單位，以後不採用。</p>
<p>軍，從春秋起成為軍隊的高級編制單位。</p>
<p>旅，師以下編制單位，只用於商周時代。三者均可作軍隊的泛稱。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>軍隊 is the current modern word for an army.</p>
<p>武裝部隊 is a formal bureaucratic way of referring to an army.</p>
<p>武裝力量 is an abstract analytic way of referring to military forces of any kind.</p>
<p>武裝 is a formal way of referring to military forces.</p>
<p>槍桿 (obs) is an old-fashioned way of referring to armed units.</p>
<p>武力 is a westernised way of referrring to armed forces.</p>
<p>行伍 (lit) is a traditionalist way of referring to army units.</p>
<p>部隊 "the military" is a general way of referring to the army of a country.</p>
<p>隊伍 refers to the troops making up an army.</p>
<p>人馬 is an old-fashioned way of referring to military forces.</p>
<p>大軍 is an honorific way of referring to the army.</p>
<p>三軍 is a traditional way of referring to all of the military forces of a state.</p>
<p>師旅 (lit) is a classical way of referring to armed forces.</p>
<p>軍 identifies army units.</p>
<p>師</p>
<p>旅</p>
<p>戎</p>
<p>first rough draft to identify synonym group members for future analysis, based on Cilin. 18.11.2003. CH/</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="mereonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-80a2464f-3efe-4f42-9b15-bcf88291d9e4">BATTALION</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-88575b9f-235d-4059-9203-479486ffb224">FLEET</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-f0e7b237-8209-4441-a19a-5a6046703e53">GROUP</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">20.15</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>ARMY</p>
<p>caterva refers to a limited host of troops in military formation.</p>
<p>cohors refers to a military formation insofar as it is under the command of a military commander.</p>
<p>agmen refers to an army as a solemn procession.</p>
<p/>
<p>ARMY</p>
<p>exercitus refers to an army which consists of legions.</p>
<p>copiae refers to an armed force which consists of cohorts.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">67</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>MILITIA</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">155</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.491</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ddc8dc41-e703-448c-9f61-6db9445685a7">UNGER SACH</ref>
<title>"Sachwoerterbuch zum Alten China"</title>
                <note>
<p>MITTLERE ARMEE</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1388</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>軍，師</p>
<p>1. WL maintains that in terms of size ju1n 軍 is larger than shi1 師.  This is misleading because shi1 師 "armed forces" is quite general and quite standardly is specified in terms to the three armies that make up a formal array of such armed forces:</p>
<p>ZUO Xuan 12.2.1 (597 B.C.); Ya2ng Bo2ju4n 721; Wa2ng Sho3uqia1n 521; tr. Watson 1989:86;  revised tr. CH </p>
<p>夏六月， In summer, in the sixth month,</p>
<p>晉師救鄭。 the Ji4n army came to the rescue of Zhe4ng.</p>
<p>荀林父將中軍， Xu2n Li2nfu3 led the central army,</p>
<p>先縠佐之； Xia1n Gu3 assisted him.</p>
<p>士會將上軍， Shi4 Hui4 led the upper army,</p>
<p>郤克佐之； an Xi4 Ke4 assisted him.</p>
<p>趙朔將下軍， Zha4o Shuo4 led the lower army,</p>
<p>欒書佐之。 Lua2n Shu1 assisted him..</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.374</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">


































    </div>
</div>