<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-70f6343c-f8b1-4c1d-a8b2-274a8edcc8d2">
<head>ARROGATE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>TAKE</item>
<item>CLAIM</item>
<item>APPROPRIATE</item>
<item>SEIZE</item>
<item>EXPROPRIATE</item>
<item>WREST</item>
<item>USURP</item>
<item>COMMANDEER</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">侵權</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">僭</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>TAKE so as to MONOPOLISE AND in so doing OFFEND against the LAW.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>[[CURRENT/RARE]]</p>
<p>[GENERAL/SPECIFIC]</p>
<p>[HABITUAL/OCCASIONAL]</p>
<p>[HIGH-DEGREE/LOW-DEGREE]</p>
<p>1. The current general word for arrogation of power is jiàn 僭.</p>
<p>[OCCASIONAL], [HIGH-DEGREE]</p>
<p>2. Nǐ 擬 refers to fraudulent and presumptuous assumption of the powers of a ruler.</p>
<p>[OCCASIONAL]; [RARE]</p>
<p>3. Shàn 擅 refers to unlicenced wilful assumption of powers of decision which do not belong to one.</p>
<p>[HABITUAL], [LOW-DEGREE]</p>
<p>4. Qīn 侵 refers to an often violent infringement of other's rights (and territories, see ATTACK).</p>
<p>[OCCASIONAL], [HIGH-DEGREE]</p>
<p>5. Líng 陵 refers to serious encroachment of others' rights or authority.</p>
<p>[HABITUAL], [SERIOUS]</p>
<p>6. Yú 踰, and yuè 越 refer to presumptuous or arrogant infringement of others' rights or authority.</p>
<p>[OCCASIONAL], [LOW-DEGREE]; [RARE]</p>
<p>7. Zhuān 專 (ant. fēn 分 "distribute properly") refers to the typically illegal monopolisation of power. For examples see MONOLOPOLISE</p>
<p>[LOW-DEGREE], [HABITUAL], [SPECIALISED]</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>侵權</p>
<p>THIS NEEDS DISCUSSION.</p>
<p>first rough draft to identify synonym group members for future analysis, based on CL. 18.11.2003. CH</p>
        </div>
<div type="old-chinese-contrasts">
<p>1. The claim may be typically temporary (nǐ 擬, jiàn 僭 ), or it may be typically permanent or lasting (zhuān 專 ).</p>
<p>2. The claim may lead to a de facto new legitimate state of affairs (zhuān 專, shàn 擅 ), or it may be a transgression which does not establish any new legal situation (nǐ 擬, jiàn 僭 ).</p>
<p>3. The kind of authority assumed may be always human (shàn 擅, nǐ 擬, zhuān 專 ), or there may be the possibility that this authority is superhuman or divine (jiàn 僭 ).</p>
<p>4. Qīn 侵 refers to the encroachment of another's territorial or other rights.</p>
<p>5. Yú 踰 and yuè 越 refer to deliberate disregard for another's rights. jiang</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-60797be8-f22b-4d40-b23f-99aa77e5aab2">ATTACK</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-91d9a879-afbf-470b-9a01-b61b695defc7">TAKE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="words">












    </div>
</div>