<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-6c1afc3e-006e-4519-b6b6-4db9fc468c26">
<head>BATTLE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>FIGHT</item>
<item>ARMED CONFLICT</item>
<item>CLASH</item>
<item>STRUGGLE</item>
<item>SKIRMISH</item>
<item>ENGAGEMENT</item>
<item>FRAY</item>
<item>DUEL</item>
<item>WAR</item>
<item>CAMPAIGN</item>
<item>CRUSADE</item>
<item>FIGHTING</item>
<item>WARFARE</item>
<item>COMBAT</item>
<item>ACTION</item>
<item>HOSTILITIES</item>
<item>SCRAP</item>
<item>DOGFIGHT</item>
<item>SHOOT-OUT</item>
<item>BRAWL</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">戰鬥</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">戰</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>WARFARE in the form of FIGHTING AND USE of WEAPONS DURING A DEFINED SHORT PERIOD, AND where TYPICALLY ONE ARMY WINS.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>[ACTION/PROCESS]</p>
<p>[BASIC/MARGINAL]</p>
<p>[[COMMON/RARE]]</p>
<p>[GENERAL/SPECIFIC]</p>
<p>[INOFFICIAL/OFFICIAL]</p>
<p>[LASTING/TEMPORARY]</p>
<p>1. The general term is zhàn 戰 (ant. hé 和 "ceasing of hostilities, ceasefire") and refers to any military engagement at a given time.</p>
<p>[GENERAL], [TEMPORARY]</p>
<p>2. An extended official and centrally organised campaign lasting some time and viewed as a task for the military is yì 役.</p>
<p>[PROCESS], [LASTING]</p>
<p>3. Zhēng 征 refers to an official military campaign as conducted by a state. See ATTACK</p>
<p>[ACTION], [LASTING], [OFFICIAL]</p>
<p>4. Chén 陳 refers to the the forming of a battle array. See BATTLE ARRAY</p>
<p>[SPECIFIC]</p>
<p>5. Jūn 軍 can come to refer generally to military action or military campaigns of any kind.</p>
<p>[ACTION], [MARGINAL]; [[RARE]]</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>作戰</p>
<p>打仗</p>
<p>戰鬥</p>
<p>交戰</p>
<p>交火</p>
<p>交鋒</p>
<p>交兵</p>
<p>構兵</p>
<p>爭戰</p>
<p>上陣</p>
<p>殺</p>
<p>戰</p>
<p>征</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-cb0e1ecf-18e6-47a5-a6e4-c01dcbe9061c">WARFARE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">20.12</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4af55868-d85f-4a0a-b22a-adbf6ab4a3a8">DIFFERENTIAE I</ref>
<title>De differentiis</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">422</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>78. Vide Serv., ad illud VIII Aen.: Qui sese in bella sequantur.</p>
<p>-- In bello. C. Fronto.</p>
<p>-- Tuba praelii. Ex Serv., XI Aen., ad illud: Bello dat signum, et ipse Etymolog. lib. XVIII, cap. 1 et 4.</p>
<p>-- Praelium pars. Sic Non. dict. Bellum.</p>
<p>[col. 19C] Ibid. Vat. omittit, id est, totus conflictus. Barthius memoria haec digna esse ait, sive ea ex sua observatione Isidorus promat, sive more suo aliunde describat. Quod autem Barthius saepe lectionem sui Codicis conjectura emendare conatur, actum plerumque agit; nam jam ea fere omnia in Editione Grialiana correcta erant, saltem cum Adversaria Barthii in lucem venerunt, quem aliquando Editionem Grialii vidisse constat. [AREV.]</p>
<p>]</p>
<p>78. Inter Bellum et praelium. Bellum indicitur, praelium geritur. In bello enim non statim praelium; in praelio autem statim et bellum. Unde et apud antiquos tuba praelii signum erat, belli buccina. Item bellum totum est, id est, totus conflictus, ut Jugurthinum [ Al., jurgium), civile, Punicum. Pugna unius diei, praelium pars pugnae, licet et pugna duorum sit [col. 19A] aliquando, et sine ferro, unde et a pugno dicta est.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>BATTLE Schulz 379b</p>
<p>pugna refers to any battle of any kind, from a minor fight or skirmish to a major battle.</p>
<p>acies can refer to a major battle of two contending armies drawn up in battle array, the pitched battle, typically on land.</p>
<p>proelium refers to the occasional encounter of separate divisions of the armies, as an engagement, action, skirmish.</p>
<p>certamen refers to a conflict of any kind, of words of of arms, with emphasis on the competitive element.</p>
<p>dimicatio refers to armed conflict insofar as it threatens one's life and the emphasis is on the defensive aspect of the struggle.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2c59ecb-bbff-4004-8e45-5fc7f92ed0da">Mel'cuk 1984</ref>
<title>Tolkovo-kombinatornyj slovar' sovremmenogo russkogo jazyka. Explanatory Combinatorial Dictionary of Modern Russian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">148ff</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">153 AND 67</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ddc8dc41-e703-448c-9f61-6db9445685a7">UNGER SACH</ref>
<title>"Sachwoerterbuch zum Alten China"</title>
                <note>
<p>SCHLACHTEN</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.99.75</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>BATAILLE.COMBAT</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.323</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">















    </div>
</div>