<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-16328064-e594-499b-b1bf-0e23ffa9f926">
<head>BELL</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">鐘</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">鐘</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>METAL MUSICAL-INSTRUMENT RESEMBLE:like a BIG CUP which one CAUSES-TO PRODUCE SOUND by BEATING it USING a STICK.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>SEE ILLUSTRATIONS</p>
<p>1. The current general word for a bell of any kind is zhōng 鐘 / 鍾. When hung up singly, it is called tè zhōng 特鐘, with round opening as in illustration SUN JI. Rhythmic instrument. Also, hung up in a series of tuned bells, in two rows of eight bells each. Note that these bells were already rare by Han times. [In use mainly from the Western Zhou till the Warring States.]</p>
<p>[GENERAL]</p>
<p>2. Qìng 磬／罄 refers to music stones rather than bells, however, these "stones" could also be made of bronze.</p>
<p>3. Náo 鐃 small handbell with handle which is held in one hand and beaten with the other hand.</p>
<p>4. Zhēng 鉦 is a small bell with a handle like a náo 鐃, but somewhat larger, and not held in the hand but set up on a stand. It is used to order an army into retreat. (The gǔ 鼓 is used to order an army to attack.)</p>
<p>5. Líng 鈴 refers to a small bell with a handle at the top.</p>
<p>6. Duó 鐸 refers to a bell with a tongue which is similar to líng 鈴 but larger.</p>
<p>7. Chuí 棰 refers to a metal or wooden stick with which to strike bells of any kind from the outside in order sound the bell. See STICK</p>
<p>8. Yǔ 敔 is a rare word referring to a bell in the shape of a crouching tiger which is beaten using a bamboo stick. Apparently, this bell was only struck towards the end of a musical piece. [Mentioned in the YIJI chapter of the SHANGSHU. Description of the shape dates from the SONG. For a Chinese antiquity, I have not found any archaeological or pictorial evidence.]</p>
<p>9. Bó 鎛 refers to a kind of suspended bell which is similar to zhōng 鐘 / 鍾 but even larger. Bó 鎛 were suspended not in sets, but alone or in pairs.</p>
<p>10. Chún yú 錞于 refers to a special kind of bell.</p>
<p>11. Luán 鸞 is a bell fixed on vehicles and knives which was supposed to make a sound like a luán-bird or phoenix.</p>
<p>12. Luán 鑾 refers to a harness bell; probably identical with luán 鸞 : see LIJI.</p>
<p>13. Zhù 柷 refers in SHI to some kind of resonance box used in music, an instrument which was struck in the beginning of a musical piece.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>鈴</p>
<p>鈴鐺</p>
<p>令丁</p>
<p>鈴鐸</p>
<p>鑾</p>
<p>鐸</p>
<p>鐘</p>
<p>門鈴</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-73c57fd4-d30b-4911-8e5a-ca7201b1e7b9">MUSICAL INSTRUMENT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d9f914e1-ebc9-4ba0-85f5-f2bdd943ed24">FINSTERBUSCH 1966</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">215</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Glocke:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dcdec461-c248-4809-a141-385e6610d74c">FINSTERBUSCH 2000</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">753</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Glocke:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dcdec461-c248-4809-a141-385e6610d74c">FINSTERBUSCH 2000</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">814</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>to, Kloeppelglocke:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-9eb4d944-6640-47a4-8398-cfe72a1c902f">SUN JI</ref>
<title>漢代無知文化資料圖說</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">376</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">311/2</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1519</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>鈴，鐸</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1556</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>鏞，鑮</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">
























    </div>
</div>