<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-6309fae2-a71b-4620-84ca-f80bbd8eae6d">
<head>BRIBE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>BUY OFF</item>
<item>PAY OFF</item>
<item>SUBORN</item>
<item>GREASE SOMEONE'S PALM</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">賄賂</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>NOT LEGITIMATE GIFT so as to INFLUENCE the DECISIONS of an OFFICIAL OR POWERFUL HUMAN.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. Lù 賂 standardly refers to substantial active bribery of any kind, including the offer of singing girls, music masters, and quite frequently territory as well as imortant ritual objects like tripods and bells, but also in this case the word is used for presents one cannot plausibly construe as straightforward bribes. See GIFT and GIVE.</p>
<p>2. Huì 賄 refers to customary gifts on formal occasions which are often hard to distinguish from bribes, and characteristically the word regularly refers to passive bribery. See also PROPERTY and GIFT. Commentators wish us to believe that the word refers specifically to "bribe with gifts of silk", but there is no clear early evidence of this.</p>
<p>3. Huò 貨 refers to any illegal act of making gifts to encourage unlawful actions, and also to the bribes themselves.</p>
<p>4. Nà 納／內 is the technical term for the receiving of bribes, i.e. passive corruption.</p>
<p>5. The word qiú 賕, which became current in Han times, refers to active as well as passive corruption.</p>
<p>6. Zāng 藏 / 臧 and huò lù 貨賂 occasionally refer to bribes received.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>賄賂</p>
<p>行賄</p>
<p>賄買</p>
<p>打點</p>
<p>收買</p>
<p>買通</p>
<p>買關節</p>
<p>通關節</p>
<p>受賄 refers to being prepared to receive bribes.</p>
<p>納賄</p>
<p>貪賄</p>
<p>貪贓</p>
<p>貪贓枉法</p>
<p>招權納賄</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
<div type="old-chinese-contrasts">
<p>The words for bribery are not easy to distinguish clearly with respect to their semantic nuances, the only clear lines of distinction being between disposition to use bribes, the practice of taking bribes, and the bribes themselves.</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c2f20d19-79ad-4d96-b7c0-0421d08cfc56">SALARY</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ed1aeb49-abff-4167-a18e-60c0f2202d63">GIVE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-d6c0c43b-5272-4d9e-88f9-f6bbac97e134">BUY</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-748fc726-746d-44e1-9a60-bc5853203054">GIFT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>USURA</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1329</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>賄，賂</p>
<p>1. WL maintains that hui3 賄 tends to consist of cloth whereas lu4 賂 tends to consist of other goods.  This traditional view is not borne out by the primary source evidence.  It sounds like a late rationalisation.  Bribes lu4 賂 are frequently specified to consist of specialists like singing girls and music masters and lands, also by offers to senior positions.</p>
<p>2. WL claims that lu4 賂 can refer to property as such.  I have not found such examples in pre-Buddhist literature, and indeed WL provide no example at all..  But I have not checked the examples in HYDCD.</p>
<p>3. WL maintains that the meaning "bribe" for lu4 賂 is a 後起義. This meaning is, of course, exceedingly common in early literature from ZUO onwards. Quoting a JINSHU example for this is most misleading.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">











    </div>
</div>