<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-a820bc31-0905-40df-aac0-4882cd13073c">
<head>BROTHER</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">兄弟</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>MALE SIBLING.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The standard collective term for brothers is xiōng dì 兄弟.</p>
<p>2. Xiōng 兄 can refer to the eldest brother as the head of his own generation (explicitly bó xiōng 伯兄 ), but it word often refers more generally to elder brothers, including those who are not the heir in the clan.</p>
<p>3. Dì 弟 refers to the younger brothers, and never specifically to the youngest.</p>
<p>4. Zōng zǐ 宗子 is a specific, formal, and ritual term for the eldest brother and heir in a family, typically after the death of whom he succeeds. See HEIR.</p>
<p>5. Zhòng 仲 refers to the next-eldest or second-eldest brother.</p>
<p>6. Bó 伯／霸 is the technical term for the eldest brother, and this word is sometimes expanded to bó xiōng 伯兄.</p>
<p>7. Jì 季 refers to the last-born brother or sister.</p>
<p>8. Kūn dì 昆弟 refers to brothers in general, but there is a pervasive doubt whether it does not also include the notion of cousins. See COUSIN.</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>HUMAN AFFAIRS 14. 哥哥。</p>
<p>兄，通稱。</p>
<p>長，代指長兄，可用作狀語，表示對同輩男子敬重的態度。</p>
<p>伯，由排行老大而代指大哥，常用作表字。</p>
<p>昆，方言詞。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>兄</p>
<p>兄長</p>
<p>哥</p>
<p>哥哥</p>
<p>阿哥</p>
<p>昆</p>
<p>長兄</p>
<p>大兄</p>
<p>大哥</p>
<p>伯兄</p>
<p>伯氏</p>
<p>令兄</p>
<p>尊兄</p>
<p>家兄</p>
<p>胞兄</p>
<p>弟</p>
<p>弟弟</p>
<p>兄弟</p>
<p>阿弟</p>
<p>仲氏</p>
<p>棣</p>
<p>令弟</p>
<p>介弟</p>
<p>賢棣</p>
<p>仁棣</p>
<p>舍弟</p>
<p>兄弟</p>
<p>兄台</p>
<p>弟兄</p>
<p>手足</p>
<p>胞弟</p>
<p>哥兒</p>
<p>昆季</p>
<p>昆仲</p>
<p>昆弟</p>
<p>雁行 yànháng refers to brothers in the plural, as a series.</p>
<p>棠棣</p>
<p>棣華</p>
<p>棣鄂</p>
<p>哥兒倆 (coll) refers to brothers</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9e1b6f7f-1dac-4e87-b6f0-6b8a472fa023">SISTER</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9e1b6f7f-1dac-4e87-b6f0-6b8a472fa023">SISTER</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-933d0ea7-b57b-4b69-bde6-94f600928dd8">SIBLING</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.44</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4af55868-d85f-4a0a-b22a-adbf6ab4a3a8">DIFFERENTIAE I</ref>
<title>De differentiis</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">347</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>237. Sic lib. Etymolog. IX, cap. 6.</p>
<p/>
<p>-- Ex eodem... Ex eod. lib. citato videtur legendum [col. 35C] ex eadem matre, non patre, et infra: est enim germanus ex eadem genitrice, non ex eodem germine manans. Alioqui sibi contrarius Isidorus his duobus locis, et Serv., unde sumpsit, ad illud V Aen.: Haec germanus Erix.</p>
<p/>
<p>Ibid. Vat., ex eodem mare et matre. [BREV.]</p>
<p>]</p>
<p>237. Inter Fratrem et germanum. Fratres dicuntur, qui ex eodem patre nascuntur, et non ex eadem matre. Qui vero 32 ex eodem patre et matre [ Al., [col. 35A] eadem matre et patre], germani appellantur. Et est germanus ex eadem genitrice, vel ex eodem germine manans.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>FRATER</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ddc8dc41-e703-448c-9f61-6db9445685a7">UNGER SACH</ref>
<title>"Sachwoerterbuch zum Alten China"</title>
                <note>
<p>GEBURTSRANG</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no. 29</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">60</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-e8e00c8c-6f7d-429d-82a5-84721abe7cc7">T.W.HARBSMEIER 2004</ref>
<title>A New Dictionary of Classical Greek Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no. 29</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">72A</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">
















    </div>
</div>