<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-c34b4d25-90f6-4193-93ab-b64cd297753f">
<head>CARRY</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>CONVEY</item>
<item>TRANSFER</item>
<item>MOVE</item>
<item>TAKE</item>
<item>BRING</item>
<item>BEAR</item>
<item>LUG</item>
<item>TOTE</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">攜帶</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>DISPLACE something by WALKING WHILE HOLDING it.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The commonest words refer to carrying things on one's back is fù 負, and the word is also common in figurative senses.</p>
<p>2. Dān 擔 refer to carrying things on a shoulder pole, but the word is still fairly rare in pre-Buddhist texts.</p>
<p>3. Hè 荷 is to carry over one's shoulder, sometimes on a pole.</p>
<p>4. Rén 任 refers to bearing something in one's arms.</p>
<p>5. Huái 懷 and bào 抱 can refer to carrying things in one's arms so as to protect them. See also EMBRACE</p>
<p>6. Dài 帶 is specifically to carry things along on one's belt, but the word is used more generally for "take along" also in ancient texts.</p>
<p>7. Pèi 佩 is to wear or carry very small objects on the waist. See WEAR</p>
<p>8. Qiè 挈 is to carry fairly small objects with one arm.</p>
<p>9. Gāng 扛 refers to lifting and possibly also carrying along heavy objects, typically as a feat. See primarily LIFT</p>
<p>NP: Káng 扛 "carry on one's shoulders" is a late colloquialism.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>帶</p>
<p>抬</p>
<p>扛抬</p>
<p>抬扛</p>
<p>扛</p>
<p>搭</p>
<p>舁</p>
<p>輿</p>
<p>背</p>
<p>馱</p>
<p>負</p>
<p>負重</p>
<p>負荷</p>
<p>負載</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-e91e37d5-4aa9-4b3a-8bca-e5c2167d9625">SMUGGLE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-6dd6b9ea-8a88-4085-ac31-45a5c87af898">LIFT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-fb4b8b85-67a4-4cbf-9af2-bed7617e2abf">PICK UP</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2ac46b3-e062-42cd-9ab9-9c57452c6eb3">DISPLACE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">10.61</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>CARRY</p>
<p>ferre is the general word referring to the transporting of something, by hand, from one place to another.</p>
<p>portare refers to the carrying of something either for oneself or for others.</p>
<p>bajulare refers to the carrying of something for others, as a porter.</p>
<p/>
<p>BEAR</p>
<p>ferre refers to the supporting of a heavy burden.</p>
<p>tolerare refers to the bearing of some burden without sinking with it, and with a considerable use of strength.</p>
<p>sustinere refers to keeping something up without allowing it to sink down.</p>
<p>pati refers to bearing a burden or suffering something without trying to get rid of it. (Marginal to this group)</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">251</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">59</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1321</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>負，任，荷，擔</p>
<p>1. One might add to WL's description the main difference which is that fu4 負 often takes abstract objects, and re2n 任 became predominantly figurative, whereas he4 荷 and da4n 擔 are nearly always concrete.  In fact, the inclusion of the marginal re2n 任 in this series is misleading, because the relevant meaning became obsolete at an early stage of the language.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.417.376</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>PORTER.APPORTER.TRANSPORTER.EMPORTER</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.389</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">392/4/6</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">
































    </div>
</div>