<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-27a34cec-04db-4cf1-9d79-fad0e99e5b09">
<head>CHANT</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>RECITE</item>
<item>REPEAT FROM MEMORY</item>
<item>SAY ALOUD</item>
<item>DECLAIM</item>
<item>QUOTE</item>
<item>DELIVER</item>
<item>RENDER</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">唱</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">詠</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>SING POETRY OR PROSE CONFORMING to a SIMPLE MELODY, NOT CONFORMING TO SONG MELODY.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current word for chanting poetry in a deeply emotional manner for the benefit of others is yǒng 詠;</p>
<p>2. The current word for chanting prose aloud for the benefit of others is sòng 誦, and the prose chanted normally has to be of high cultural status.</p>
<p>3. F1ē3ng 諷 refers specifically to (possibly reading out and) reciting what one is familiar with and may even know by heart. (Old reading fèng!)</p>
<p>4. Fù 賦 refers to the recital of poetry of any kind, commonly even one's own works.</p>
<p>5. Yín 吟 is to hum and quietly intone something for one's own enjoyment, perhaps as one walks along, typically as an expression of one's emotions, and not primarily for others to listen to, and the word is never used as a transitive verb with an object indicating what exactly is being hummed or intoned.</p>
<p>6. Shēn 呻 is to mournfully hum poetry to oneself.</p>
<p>7. Zàn 贊 refers to the ritual reading out of a prescribed liturgical text on formal occasions.</p>
<p>8. Chàng 唱 refers to dramatic loud and drawn-out recital of prose texts. See SING</p>
<p>See also READ</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>吟詠 is a common word for chanting poetry.</p>
<p>吟哦 refers to a humming chant of poetry.</p>
<p>詠嘆 refers to a pensive mode of chanting.</p>
<p>吟嘯 (lit) refers to free lamenting intonation of poetry.</p>
<p>嘯詠 (lit) refers to the chanting of poetry in an elevated manner.</p>
<p>吟唱 is a familiar word for the quiet recitation of poetry.</p>
<p>吟誦 refers to the quiet recitation of poetry or prose.</p>
<p>哼唧 refers very informally??? to the humming of poetry.</p>
<p>口占 refers specifically to the recital of a spontaneous poem.</p>
<p>吟 (cl)</p>
<p>詠 (cl)</p>
<p>嘆 (cl)</p>
<p>哼 (cl)</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-7fc51e90-6254-422d-9821-33b4e85f9f11">READ</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-f30a70cf-cbce-46e7-a48e-814ec680b91c">SING</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>PRONUNCIATIO</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">759</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1290</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>誦，諷</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-65cb3fa8-ba3e-4eef-b23e-5b43a8bb8651">JONES 2005</ref>
<title>Encyclopedia of Religion</title>
                <note>
<p>MEMORISATION, CHANT</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">344</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">


















    </div>
</div>