<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-6c360266-1a79-4f76-9a18-003b8220bb6a">
<head>CITIZEN</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">公民</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>ADULT who HAS DEFINED RIGHTS AND DUTIES BECAUSE s/he BELONGS TO a STATE.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>The insistution of legal citizenship was linked to tax-paying duty and military duty, not in terms of any specific civic rights. The concrete definition of citizenship will have differed from state to state in Warring States times, and the importance of the definition will have depended on the degree of detailedness of public registers. In China, there was no central and important institution like the bundle of rights and duties of the civis Romanus. The civis Romanus defined himself in terms of rights. It would appear that the Chinese citizen defined himself as a citizen (less enthusiastically) through his duties.</p>
<p>An expression like 齊人 had three meanings in ancient China:</p>
<p>1. commonly: a man from Qí, people from Qí;</p>
<p>2. (in the ANNALS (CQ) and other annalistic contexts: the senior citizens of Qí, the aristocracy of Qí;</p>
<p>3. from Warring States onwards: citizens of Qí.</p>
<p>It is the third notion that badly needs close investigation.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>公民</p>
<p>平民</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-65cb71ac-f777-4e3e-8d7a-372925a65ebb">BOURGEOIS</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-17c5977a-0682-43c0-97c9-80813ff8ad67">ADULT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">19.37</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>INHABITANT versus CITIZEN</p>
<p>incola is the mere inhabitant versus the citizen.</p>
<p>inquilinus refers to the owner of a house, also known as dominus.</p>
<p>colonus refers to the owner of a piece of land.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">134b</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-91ef2ef1-7486-4414-aec0-a25971572d19">KOSELLECK 1972-97</ref>
<title>Geschichtliche Grundbegriffe</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.672-725</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-a012a2b3-03fc-4748-88bb-0d077d69923b">LAUFFER 1981</ref>
<title>Polites Soziale Typenbegriffe</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.120.86</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>HABITANT.BEOURGEOIS.CITOYEN</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.353</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-13b8c22a-fe16-4ea1-aa90-86814381e229">HOROWITZ 2005</ref>
<title>New Dictiornary of the History of Ideas, 6 vols.</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">




    </div>
</div>