<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-62e49b6c-d875-4431-bcae-3d46cf50229c">
<head>COMPLAIN</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>PROTEST</item>
<item>GRUMBLE</item>
<item>WHINE</item>
<item>BLEAT</item>
<item>CARP</item>
<item>CAVIL</item>
<item>GROUSE</item>
<item>MAKE A FUSS</item>
<item>OBJECT</item>
<item>SPEAK OUT</item>
<item>CRITICIZE</item>
<item>FIND FAULT</item>
<item>KICK UP A FUSS</item>
<item>RAISE A STINK</item>
<item>BELLYACHE</item>
<item>MOAN</item>
<item>SNIVEL</item>
<item>BEEF</item>
<item>BITCH</item>
<item>SOUND OFF</item>
<item>GRIPE</item>
<item>KVETCH</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">上訴</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">訴</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>SAY that something is NOT JUST AND BAD IN-RELATION-TO SELF:oneself OR someone CLOSE to SELF:oneself.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current general word for complaint is sù 訴.</p>
<p>2. Gào 告 refers to an inferior complaining to a superior.</p>
<p>NB: Yuān 冤 refers to an injustice suffered, but not to a complaint about it.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>上告 is the current word for lodging a complaint.</p>
<p>上控 focusses on the public accusation which forms part of the complaint.</p>
<p>上訴 refers to stating one's case in court.</p>
<p>越衙上告 refers in a proverbial way to higher authorities.</p>
<p>喊冤 (lit) refers to crying out about an injustice one has suffered.</p>
<p>叫冤 (lit) refers to crying out about an injustice one has suffered.</p>
<p>叫屈 (lit) refers to crying out about an injustice one has suffered.</p>
<p>申冤 (lit, arch) refers to crying out about an injustice one has suffered.</p>
<p>申雪 (lit) refers to an appeal for legal redress for an injustice suffered.</p>
<p>喊冤叫屈 (prov) refers to all manner of loud complaints being made.</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b6823b3f-026c-4d47-91dd-6d53cae03cb1">GRUMBLE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-905c9129-3533-429c-98da-91d01635f2c9">BLAME</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-07855030-3463-472d-bd01-1c7ceebbfb3d">SPEAK</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>COMPLAIN</p>
<p>questus refers to the concise expression of pain through lamentation.</p>
<p>quiritatio refers to a continued expression of main over a period of time.</p>
<p>querimonia is the just feeling of the injured person who will not brook an act of injustice, and this word implies understanding of the situation and aims at redress or satisfaction.</p>
<p>querela tends to refer to the blamable feeling of the discontented person who will brook no hardship, and this word does not normally refer to an action aiming at redressing an unjust situation.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">180</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.235:161</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>LAMENTATION.PLAINTE</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">52A</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">




    </div>
</div>