<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-c5ff4bc7-d691-4101-a732-86b0ebb9ac9a">
<head>CRIME</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>OFFENSE</item>
<item>UNLAWFUL ACT</item>
<item>ILLEGAL ACT</item>
<item>FELONY</item>
<item>MISDEMEANOR</item>
<item>MISDEED</item>
<item>WRONG</item>
<item>NO-NO</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">罪過</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">罪／過</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>WICKED ACT OFFENDING INTENSELY against an IMPORTANT LAW.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current general word for a serious legal transgression is zuì 罪 (ant. gōng 功 "merit"), and the current general word for a minor legal transgression is guò 過 (ant. xiào 效 "positive contribution").</p>
<p>2. Yóu 尤 refers generally to morally disreputable behaviour.</p>
<p>3. Jiù 咎 (ant. láo 勞 "obtain merits") refers to an action for which one deserves blame.</p>
<p>4. Dào 盜 (ant.* dé 德 "virtue") refers to morally and legally outrageous behaviour.</p>
<p>5. Yuè 越 can come to refer to a failure to keep within the boundaries set by one's social status or office.</p>
<p>6. Gū 辜 (ant. xún 勛 "significant contribution") is an archaising word referring to serious crimes at an early stage, but later commonly used (mostly in negated form) to refer to any crime.</p>
<p>7. Tè 忒, qiān 愆, and shěng 眚 refer to a minor but culpable error.</p>
<p>8. Qiān 愆 refers to a minor mistake in procedure.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>罪行</p>
<p>罪名</p>
<p>罪過</p>
<p>過犯</p>
<p>罪</p>
<p>辜</p>
<p>孽</p>
<p>罪孽</p>
<p>罪惡</p>
<p>罪戾</p>
<p>滔天大罪</p>
<p>彌天大罪</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ff36de29-e1d3-4536-b491-1e98b592c635">CHEAT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-d5605d15-1ee3-4b7a-b5fc-b7d04f235139">SIN</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9ab78015-0fad-44a9-a51a-a870f5602d88">CORRECT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-21896666-fc4e-4b61-90e9-5f55c8dcf3aa">GUILT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9dac739b-a566-4517-81f2-92ec535f7571">WICKED</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9dac739b-a566-4517-81f2-92ec535f7571">WICKED</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-0afde884-7a1d-43f1-9b2c-69fedf653c8c">MISTAKE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-699a94f6-628b-44ba-be7a-3454a439b2a0">LAW</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ff36de29-e1d3-4536-b491-1e98b592c635">CHEAT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-abfdc4bb-445b-44d8-a4e9-f9f114a2beba">ACT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4af55868-d85f-4a0a-b22a-adbf6ab4a3a8">DIFFERENTIAE I</ref>
<title>De differentiis</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>299. In textu Pantinus fortasse legebat totque, aut totidem et, pro quo varia lectio assignatur totidemque. [AREV.]</p>
<p>]</p>
<p>299. Inter Iniquitatem et peccatum sic distare dicit Ambrosius, quod iniquitas ad mentis acerbitatem refertur, peccatum vero ad prolapsionem corporis. Praecedit igitur iniquitas, peccatum sequitur. Sed gravior est iniquitas, tanquam materia peccatorum, in cujus comparatione levius est peccatum. Item peccatum est quod admittitur; piaculum autem id quod admissum est, et id quod expiatur admissum. Iniquitatis [col. 41B] autem tres sunt differentiae: 40 suggestionis, delectationis, et consensus. Inter iniquitates et peccata sanctus Hieronymus hanc differentiam facit: iniquitates dicimus quae ante susceptam fidem, sive per ignorantiam, sive per scientiam committuntur. Peccata vero, quae post cognitionem fidei, vel gratiam baptismatis contrahuntur; totidemque et peccata, verbi, operis et consensionis.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>TRANSGRESSION</p>
<p>delictum refers to a relatively light offense against punitive laws.</p>
<p>peccatum refers to a transgression of natural rules of reason or morality.</p>
<p>malefactum refers to any deed that one should not have done.</p>
<p>maleficium refers to any misdeed that springs from an evil intention.</p>
<p>facinus is a major daring misdeed which springs from wickedness of nature.</p>
<p>flagitium is a flagrant breach of the norms of honourable behaviour that one has set for oneself, e.g. through gluttony, cowardice, licentiousness.</p>
<p>scelus is a fragrant offence against society through malice.</p>
<p>nefas refers to sacrilege against what is holy to the gods or ordained by the gods.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">87</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>CRIMEN</p>
<p>SCELUS</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-abc2f8ad-0bc4-4663-a70c-806e480d7081">LUNHENG TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>論衡同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">88</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4acb4e0c-daab-4369-9991-912c64da1ee6">RITTER 1971-2007</ref>
<title>Historisches Woerterbuch der Philosophie</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">11.58</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>VERBRECHEN</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.283.241</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>FAUTE.CRIME.PECHE.DELIT.FORFAIT</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no. 31</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">145A</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">

































    </div>
</div>