<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-c5280909-0367-44d7-b6e2-5a9280a661f6">
<head>DISCUSS</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>TALK OVER</item>
<item>TALK ABOUT</item>
<item>TALK THROUGH</item>
<item>CONVERSE ABOUT</item>
<item>DEBATE</item>
<item>CONFER ABOUT</item>
<item>DELIBERATE ABOUT</item>
<item>CHEW OVER</item>
<item>CONSIDER</item>
<item>CONSIDER THE PROS AND CONS OF</item>
<item>THRASH OUT</item>
<item>INFORMAL KICK AROUND</item>
<item>HASH OUT</item>
<item>BAT AROUND</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">討論</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>SPEAK SYSTEMATICALLY on something, BASING oneself on INVESTIGATION AND REFLECTION.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The most current words for discussion are yì 議 "public (often formal) discussion", and lùn 論 "discursive discourse; written summary discussion with a conclusion".</p>
<p>2. Biàn 辯 refers to a rational subtle discussion and investigation.</p>
<p>3. Zhēng 爭 refers to an eristic discussion or an altercation, and the word emphasises the intellectual conflict involved. See STRUGGLE.</p>
<p>4. Jiǎng 講 refers to discussing something as an important subject and in a systematic manner.</p>
<p>5. Tǎo 討 is to engage in a deep and thorough discussion and investigation of something.</p>
<p>6. Píng 評 is a rare word that refers to discussion. (NB: this word enjoyed a renaissance and become more common in post-Buddhist times.)</p>
<p>7.Tán 談 refers (often pejoratively) to an informal, perhaps even inconsequential, dialogue or or discourse on something. See DIALOGUE.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>商量 is the most current general word for the discussion of differing views on a matter.</p>
<p>討論 is the current modern word for discussion.</p>
<p>議論 refers to public debate, typically of matters of political relevance.</p>
<p>座談 refers to formal public debate on a certain subject, on a certain public occasion.</p>
<p>審議 refers to detailed often public discussion leading to a definite conclusion.</p>
<p>商討 focusses on the different opinions involved in discussion, typically on major matters of policy.</p>
<p>探討 focusses on investigation as background to discussion.</p>
<p>研討 refers to discussion based on study.</p>
<p>議事 (lit, obs) focusses on the matters discussed as serious.</p>
<p>會商 (lit) refers to a formal discussion with a view to reaching a decision.</p>
<p>協商</p>
<p>談判</p>
<p>洽談</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-65c1c732-370e-4a5c-ab62-3ebbc2b8cf71">EXPLAIN</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-3f5f8978-4fb5-4fca-9b4a-7c71aa001033">POLITICS</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-24caf902-af72-4494-a2c3-c08f3dbaec4d">DIALOGUE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-1bc82b48-48b1-4d9c-879f-714019e8cbd1">FIGHT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-07855030-3463-472d-bd01-1c7ceebbfb3d">SPEAK</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b8242ce-9fc6-4b7b-bd52-14c744308409">COMENIUS 1665</ref>
<title>De Rerum Humanarum Emendatione</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">511</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>DISPUTARE est de qvaestione ambigua in utramqve partem decertare, donec utro veritas praeponderet, pateat. Constat 1. ex qvaestione dubia.2. Argumentis in utramqve partem facientibus. 3. erumqve accurata collatione, a duobus earundem rerum peritis instituta. Ergo videndum 1. an sit vere dubium, et 2. quid proprie, et 3. inter qvos....</p>
<p>Disputationis leges. 1. Quastio formetur. 2.Termini omnes definiantur. 3. Demum status controversiae recte formetur. 4 Demum affirmatnti incumbat probatio. 5 Neganti responsatio. 7.Affirmanti liqvidatio. 7. usquve dum non restet de quo ambigatur....</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">211</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>DISPUTATIO</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-abc2f8ad-0bc4-4663-a70c-806e480d7081">LUNHENG TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>論衡同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4acb4e0c-daab-4369-9991-912c64da1ee6">RITTER 1971-2007</ref>
<title>Historisches Woerterbuch der Philosophie</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.262</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1281</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>談，論</p>
<p>1. WL takes the difference between ta2n 談 and lu4n 論 to be one of formality versus informality of discussion.  In fact, lu4n 論 is not primarily dialogical in nature at all, and the word only refers to dialogue by a relatively rare extension.  Ta2n 談, on the other hand, is by no means limited to dialogue, and the distinctive feature of the word is its predominant pejorative nuance "chatter".</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1284</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>議，論</p>
<p>1. WL rightly points out that yi4 議 aims at some decision, whereas lu4n 論aims at a judgment.  One may add that the main difference here is that yi4 議 refers to a formal discussion in council, whereas lu4n 論 refers to a disquisition quite generally.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b425a52b-7c3a-4b26-a4a5-8c5a55eaf19b">GRACE ZHANG 2010</ref>
<title>Using Chinese Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">318</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-93502795-e958-4bb9-ae45-2b1258a7d635">TENG SHOU-HSIN 1996</ref>
<title>Chinese Synonyms Usage Dictionary</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">384</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-7fede423-9ddf-4c45-9d79-c88d5a457eb7">CAI SHAOWEI 2010</ref>
<title>跟我學同義詞</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">80</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">




















    </div>
</div>