<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-5a6418f0-0044-439d-a1eb-858537fd25e2">
<head>EGO</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>I </item>
<item>ME</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">我</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">我</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>[GRAMMAR] PRONOUN (or pseudo-pronoun) USING WHICH A SPEAKER REFERS to HIMSELF.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The umarked current first person pronoun most current by Warring States times is wú 吾, and the word is never emphatic in constructions like 吾實 "It was I who...". (Not in OBI. Note the Jinwen variant graphs for the same word 𫊣 and 䱷.) This word does not normally occur in object position and is highly idiomatic in a possessive pre-nominal position. Significantly, this pronoun can never be used emphatically or contrastively. (NB: The word also serves as an impersonal pronoun meaning "we" in the sense close to "one", German man, French on.) 我亦 "I too", versus 予亦 "I shall moreover V".</p>
<p>2. Wǒ 我 (which can be used in the emphatic construction 我實 "It was I who...") is contrastive and emphatic by Warring States times, as in wǒ zé 我則 "I on the other hand...". (In OBI 我 was not yet in opposition to wú 吾 and was the standard unmarked pronoun during earlier stages of the language). The word freely occurs in subject, modifying, and object position and often has an idiomatic meaning like "I for my part" and the formal slightly depersonalised "our party". NB: The word also serves as a derived impersonal pronoun meaning "one", German "man", French "on". 我亦 "I too", versus 予亦 "I shall moreover V".</p>
<p>3. Yú 予／余 is personal and often autobiographical, speaking of the author in the past. It it a preferred pronoun used by poets.</p>
<p>4. Zhèn 朕 is an ordinary southern dialect first person pronoun in CC, but by decree the word came to be limited to use by the emperor alone after the unification of the Chinese Empire in 221 BC.</p>
<p>NB 1: Many official titles - but by no means all - function as quasi pronouns. For example, no king could call himself wáng 王 "king", but all ministers will normally refer to themselves as chén 臣 in the presence of their king, and not by the more assertive pronoun wǒ 我. Thus most quasi-pronouns serve a self-deprecatory function and are not usable in contexts where no self-deprecation is called for. A fascinating exception is fūzǐ 夫子 "the master" which is apparently used in self-reference meaning "I, your master" by Confucius.</p>
<p>For the internal complexity of the notion of the EGO in German see C. Harbsmeier, "Ueber den inneren Schweinehund, das bessere Ich und die rausgelassene Sau" [On lack of will-power and one's better Self???]</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>我</p>
<p>咱</p>
<p>俺</p>
<p>余</p>
<p>吾</p>
<p>予</p>
<p>儂</p>
<p>咱家</p>
<p>洒家</p>
<p>本</p>
<p>身</p>
<p>個人</p>
<p>老朽</p>
<p>老拙</p>
<p>老夫</p>
<p>小老兒</p>
<p>老漢</p>
<p>老可</p>
<p>老軀</p>
<p>老身</p>
<p>朽人</p>
<p>老妾</p>
<p>老身</p>
<p>老娘</p>
<p>愚兄</p>
<p>為兄</p>
<p>小弟</p>
<p>兄弟</p>
<p>愚弟</p>
<p>奴</p>
<p>奴家</p>
<p>奴奴</p>
<p>妾</p>
<p>妾身</p>
<p>賤妾</p>
<p>小女</p>
<p>朕</p>
<p>孤</p>
<p>孤王</p>
<p>孤家</p>
<p>寡人</p>
<p>職</p>
<p>卑職</p>
<p>下官</p>
<p>奴婢</p>
<p>奴才</p>
<p>貧道</p>
<p>小道</p>
<p>貧僧</p>
<p>貧衲</p>
<p>老子</p>
<p>在下</p>
<p>人家　coquettish: "I"</p>
<p/>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
<div type="old-chinese-contrasts">
<p>BHT 2.13.5: 朕、我也。或稱予者，予亦我也。</p>
<p>QIAN ZONGWU 2004: 王力先生认为 " 上古人称代词具有相当整齐的系统，各词都有对应关系 : ‘ 吾 ' 、 ‘ 余 ' 、 ‘ 予 ' 和 ‘ 汝 ' 相配， ‘ 我 '</p>
<p>和 ‘ 尔 ' 相配. " 我 " 多用于表自谦， " 予 " 大致表自尊.</p>
<p>HONG B O: 洪　波</p>
<p>南开大学</p>
<p>内　容　提　要</p>
<p>上古汉语第一人称代词 “ 余 ( 予 ) ”“ 我 ”“ 朕 ” 之间的分别近人多从形态着眼去考证, 但未</p>
<p>能得到令人满意的结论。本文根据这三个代词在上古文献中的使用情况, 结合古代语文学</p>
<p>家的研究成果, 指出这三个代词的本质区别在于意义上有谦敬功能的不同 “, 余 ( 予 ) ” 是谦称</p>
<p>形式, 表示谦卑的意义;“ 朕 ” 是尊称形式, 表示尊崇的意义;“ 我 ” 是通称形式, 不具有谦卑尊</p>
<p>崇的意义。这三个代词的其他差异都是从它们的本质差异中衍生出来的。</p>
<p>3HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>HUMAN AFFAIRS 7. GENERAL SELF-DEPRECATORY 自謙詞。</p>
<p>鄙，修飾社會稱謂 “ 人 ”“ 夫 ”“ 字 ”“??” 等，以表自身。</p>
<p>賤，修飾親屬稱謂 “ 息 ”“ 子 ” ，以表與己有關的人；修飾社會稱謂 “ 臣 ” ，以表自身。</p>
<p>愚，用於臣子對君王自謙的場合。</p>
<p>臣，表謙的通稱，特指臣子對諸侯或天子的自謙。</p>
<p>仆，大夫家臣的自謙之詞，漢後用於同輩或同事之間。妾，女子自謙之詞。</p>
<p>38. ROYAL SELF-DEPRECATORY 王侯自謙。</p>
<p>孤，有喪事的大國諸侯或庶方小國諸侯的謙稱，後漢時，地方割據者僭用。</p>
<p>寡，作定語，表示諸侯或諸侯夫人的自謙、臣子對他國謙稱自己的君主。</p>
<p>不穀，諸侯的謙稱。</p>
<p>一人，商王和周王的謙稱。</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-1cd544ac-9d88-4038-abd5-45912cc6e154">YOU</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-87ba5d81-cf48-47b1-84dd-7a48657f1454">WE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-eb838b61-6aa5-4255-8c00-4196789a449a">SELF</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c1654743-3e55-4188-816b-511da251682f">PRONOUN</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-c6a5120d-a888-44ce-b517-b0cbba82518a">CASSIN 2004</ref>
<title>Vocabulaire européen des philosophies. Dictionnaire des intraduisibles</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">383</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ES</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-c6a5120d-a888-44ce-b517-b0cbba82518a">CASSIN 2004</ref>
<title>Vocabulaire européen des philosophies. Dictionnaire des intraduisibles</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">646</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>JE</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f7087d0d-0ada-46a4-970e-975f938474e9">MAUTHNER WP 1924</ref>
<title>Woerterbuch der Philosophie. Neue Beitraege zu einer Kritik der Sprache</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">I.468</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4acb4e0c-daab-4369-9991-912c64da1ee6">RITTER 1971-2007</ref>
<title>Historisches Woerterbuch der Philosophie</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">4.1</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ICH</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-74ef242e-0300-4994-8992-f23c46362473">SANBAITI 1987</ref>
<title>中國文化史三百題</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">336</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">371</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>1. WL 9f claims that wo3 我，吾 and 余，予 are synonymous apart from the fact that wu2 吾 cannot occur in object position.  In fact, the two groups are totally different from each other semantically in three striking ways: </p>
<p>A. Wo3 我 and wu2 吾 can be used for the plural, the others cannot.</p>
<p>B. Wo3 我 and wu2 吾 have very common and philosophically important impersonal uses like German man, English you, French on, whereas the others can never be used in this way.</p>
<p>C. Wo3 我 is assertive ("I for my part"; "our party in the conflict") whereas all the other words never are.</p>
<p>2. WL claims that zhe4n 朕 and wo3 我 are synonymous in pre-Qin Chinese.  But zhe4n 朕 is a dialect word very unlike the colourless wo3 我, and especially, zhe4n 朕 is never used impersonally or contrastively in the way indicated above.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-2607d22a-6e25-4703-9704-64e7c0254044">YUAN TINGDONG 1994</ref>
<title>古人稱謂 Guren chengwei</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2a</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">

























































































































































































    </div>
</div>