<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-0bfa613e-e3a5-4489-b947-fd71fc381db4">
<head>ENCOURAGE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>HEARTEN</item>
<item>CHEER</item>
<item>BUOY UP</item>
<item>UPLIFT</item>
<item>INSPIRE</item>
<item>MOTIVATE</item>
<item>SPUR ON</item>
<item>STIR</item>
<item>STIR UP</item>
<item>FIRE UP</item>
<item>STIMULATE</item>
<item>INVIGORATE</item>
<item>VITALIZE</item>
<item>REVITALIZE</item>
<item>EMBOLDEN</item>
<item>FORTIFY</item>
<item>RALLY</item>
<item>INFORMAL BUCK UP</item>
<item>PEP UP</item>
<item>GIVE A SHOT IN THE ARM TO</item>
<item>PERSUADE</item>
<item>COAX</item>
<item>URGE</item>
<item>PRESS</item>
<item>PUSH</item>
<item>PRESSURE</item>
<item>PRESSURIZE</item>
<item>PROD</item>
<item>GOAD</item>
<item>EGG ON</item>
<item>PROMPT</item>
<item>INFLUENCE</item>
<item>SWAY</item>
<item>INFORMAL PUT IDEAS INTO ONE'S HEAD</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">勸</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">勸</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">

    <p resp="#CH" modified="2021-03-18T18:22:14.908+09:00">ADVISE someone IN ORDER TO TRY to PERSUADE that HUMAN to ACT in a way one BELIEVES to be PROFITABLE FOR THAT HUMAN. </p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The dominant current word is quàn 勸 (ant. jǔ 沮 "try to stop") which refers to all kinds of encouragement, both from inferiors and from superiors.</p>
<p>2. Miǎn 勉 focusses on the effort needed in doing what one is encouraged to do.</p>
<p>3. Qū 驅 "drive on hard" refers to "encouragement" by threat of force from the part of superiors.</p>
<p>4. Lì 勵 refers to a superior encouraging others to strive hard for the ideals they already have.</p>
<p>5. Cù 趣 refers to encouraging others to make greater speed in doing what they are already doing or aiming to do.</p>
<p>6. Jí 急 refers to an urgent request to speed up what one is doing in a concrete way.</p>
<p>7. Xù 勗 is an elavated archaic word which was quite current in SHANGSHU and reappeared as an archaism in Han times.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>勸告 refers to spoken formal advice and encouragement.</p>
<p>相勸 refers to an informal offer of encouragement and advice.</p>
<p>規勸 refers formally to encouragement along regular or conventional lines of morality.</p>
<p>奉勸 refers formally to insistent encouragement.</p>
<p>勸導 refers rather formally to encouragement as guidance.</p>
<p>勸化 refers to typically religious exhortation and moral encouragement, typically with a view to conversion.</p>
<p>勸戒 refers to religious encouragement and exhortation against transgressions of any kind.</p>
<p>勸助 refers to the offer of hopefully helpful encouragement.</p>
<p>勸誘 refers to a typically reprehensible form of encouragement in the form of inducement.</p>
<p>勸說 refers to encouragment by way of friendly persuasion.</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-14a83efe-3bd6-458e-b596-c2e57150739f">INCITE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ae0f45f9-f415-4072-8647-dc01d9190674">FORBID</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-fc9fd26b-ca6f-4080-a717-5eddf7688e5e">SEDUCE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c2bc9fbb-4965-4acc-9807-9ab30e495efe">ADVISE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>ENCOURAGE/URGE</p>
<p>incitare refers to the urging an inactive person by merely bidding, speaking to, and calling upon him, to an action, often of a laudable kind.</p>
<p>hortari refers to urging an inactive person by merely bidding, speaking to, and calling upon him, to an action, the action always being presumed to be of the laudable kind.</p>
<p>instigare refers to the spurring on of a reluctant person by vehement exhortations, promises, threats, to engage in an adventurous undertaking.</p>
<p>irritare refers to inciting a generally quiet person, by rousing passions, ambitions, to engage in a violent and adventurous course of action.</p>
<p/>
<p>ADMONISH Dum 1665</p>
<p>hortatio refers to an admonition that is addressed directly to the will and resolution of the person admonished, and the aim of hortatio is always an action.</p>
<p>monere refers to an admonition and warning regarding the future which is directed almost entirely to the consciousness of the person adminished, and to his judgment, and the aim of monitio is always a way of thinking about things, where this way of thinking may or may not result in action. Monitio may be among equals.</p>
<p>admonere refers to admonitions and warnings regarding the past.</p>
<p>obiurgare refers to a reproach or reprimand from a superior.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>ADMONITIO</p>
<p>EXHORTATIO</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">cf 76</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-93502795-e958-4bb9-ae45-2b1258a7d635">TENG SHOU-HSIN 1996</ref>
<title>Chinese Synonyms Usage Dictionary</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.161.120</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>EXCITER.ANIMER.ENCOURAGER</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">56A</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">


























    </div>
</div>