<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-9803f093-d964-43b1-8883-722218e08099">
<head>FATE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>FORTUNE</item>
<item>DESTINY</item>
<item>DESTINY</item>
<item>PROVIDENCE</item>
<item>THE STARS</item>
<item>CHANCE</item>
<item>LUCK</item>
<item>SERENDIPITY</item>
<item>FORTUNE</item>
<item>KISMET</item>
<item>KARMA</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">命運</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">命</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>SUPERNATURAL FORCE which FIXES CONTINGENT EVENTS.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current word referring to what is fated, determined or decreed by Heaven, and thus invested with unquestionable moral or metaphysical authority is mìng 命, sometimes expanded to tiān mìng 天命.</p>
<p>2. Shù 數 construes fate as something which can be ascertained by the relevant specialists of prognostication.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>命運 is the current general word for fate.</p>
<p>天命 is a popular but literary word for fate as ordained by Heaven.</p>
<p>命 is a current literary word for fate in general.</p>
<p>天意 refers to fate as intended by Heaven.</p>
<p>氣運 refers to fate as the fortuious result of natural processes.</p>
<p>氣數 refers to destiny as determined naturally in all detail.</p>
<p>運氣 refers to fate as fortuitous (good or bad) luck.</p>
<p>運道 focusses on fate as fortuitous good or bad fortune guided by the Way.</p>
<p>天時 refers to fate as determined in its details of timing by Heaven.</p>
<p>天機 focusses on the mysterious heavenly mechanisms which produce fate.</p>
<p>造化 refers to fate as the result of complex and inscrutable natural developments.</p>
<p>大命 refers to fate as an overwhelming force.</p>
<p>定命 focusses on the deterministic feature of fate.</p>
<p>天數 refers to one's destiny as determined in its details by Heaven.</p>
<p>定數 focusses on the predictably deterministic feature of one's destiny.???</p>
<p>命數 refers to one's destiny as ordained.</p>
<p>大數 refers to one's destiny as overwhelming metaphysical force.</p>
<p>世運 refers to fate as fortuitously changeable.</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-0f3ce66a-25d2-4900-8cdd-a81d6032e7b6">PROVIDENCE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-21deb72a-27fb-460b-aa38-11493c980b09">FORCE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">16.17</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-c6a5120d-a888-44ce-b517-b0cbba82518a">CASSIN 2004</ref>
<title>Vocabulaire européen des philosophies. Dictionnaire des intraduisibles</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1117</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>SCHICKSAL</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b8242ce-9fc6-4b7b-bd52-14c744308409">COMENIUS 1665</ref>
<title>De Rerum Humanarum Emendatione</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">530</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>FATUM providentiae divinae immutabilis Ordo, res occultis viis ad suas metas ducens.</p>
<p>Conc. 1. Res. 2. Metae rerum. 3. Occulta divina vis, res ad metam dirigens.</p>
<p>Detailed discussion.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4af55868-d85f-4a0a-b22a-adbf6ab4a3a8">DIFFERENTIAE I</ref>
<title>De differentiis</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">136</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>FATUM, FORTUNA</p>
<p>Fatum autem et fortunam pagani ita separabant:  quod enim fortuitu venig nulla palam causa, fortunam vocabant;  fatum vero quod adpositum singulis et statutum erat...</p>
<p>219. Inter Fatum et fortunam pagani ita separabant: quod enim fortuitu venit, nulla palam causa, fortunam vocabant, fatum vero quidquid appositum singulis, et statutum erat, ut puta, fati esse dicebant quod nascimur, quod occidimus; fortunae quidquid in vita varietatis accidit [ Al., occiderit].</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>FORTUNE</p>
<p>fors refers to blind and meaningless arbitrary fortune.</p>
<p>fortuna refers to arbitrary purposeful fortune as interfering in human affairs.</p>
<p>fatum refers to meaningful, purposeful, structured and in principle often even predictable fate, typically as enacted by the gods.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>FATUM</p>
<p>NECESSITAS</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2c59ecb-bbff-4004-8e45-5fc7f92ed0da">Mel'cuk 1984</ref>
<title>Tolkovo-kombinatornyj slovar' sovremmenogo russkogo jazyka. Explanatory Combinatorial Dictionary of Modern Russian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">857</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.2343</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4acb4e0c-daab-4369-9991-912c64da1ee6">RITTER 1971-2007</ref>
<title>Historisches Woerterbuch der Philosophie</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">8.1275</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>SCHICKSAL</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ddc8dc41-e703-448c-9f61-6db9445685a7">UNGER SACH</ref>
<title>"Sachwoerterbuch zum Alten China"</title>
                <note>
<p>MANDAT</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-88e7f5cb-b9f3-4519-8630-808dc92ba3d2">WIERZBICKA 1992</ref>
<title>Semantics, Culture, and Cognition.  Universal Human |Concepts in Culture-Specific Configurations</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">65-118</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-5b9ff356-3696-4cac-8669-ad8277c13004">ZHANG DAINIAN 2002</ref>
<title>Key Concepts in Chinese Philosophy</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">125</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.80.57</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>HASARD.FORTUNE.SORT.DESTIN</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.251</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">










    </div>
</div>