<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-8ab808df-97f3-40fd-9b35-a9fc0a7aee53">
<head>FEAR</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>BE AFRAID OF</item>
<item>BE FEARFUL OF</item>
<item>BE SCARED OF</item>
<item>BE APPREHENSIVE OF</item>
<item>DREAD</item>
<item>LIVE IN FEAR OF</item>
<item>BE TERRIFIED OF</item>
<item>BE ANXIOUS ABOUT</item>
<item>WORRY ABOUT</item>
<item>FEEL APPREHENSIVE ABOUT</item>
<item>HAVE A PHOBIA ABOUT</item>
<item>HAVE A HORROR OF</item>
<item>TAKE FRIGHT AT</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">害怕</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">懼</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>BAD FEELING IN-RELATION-TO what one BELIEVES to be a DANGER which one is TRYING to AVOID.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The most general word for any kind of passing fear is probably jù 懼 and this word naturally links with yōu 憂 "worry", and this word refers to a momentary historical moment where that fear manifested itself ( 文王乃懼 "then King Wén got scared"). Jù sǐ 懼死 is momentary fear for one's life, whereas wèi sǐ 畏死 refers to a general state where one is too frightened to sacrifice one's life.</p>
<p>2. Kǒng 恐 refers primarily to intense or overwhelming possibly passing state of fear, and the word differs from jù 懼 mainly in degree of intensity and in the managability of the danger faced.</p>
<p>3. Wèi 畏 is typically a stable state of reasoned fear, typically relating those who are in authority (the etymologically related wēi 威 on which relation there is much word-play in texts like ZUO), or ghosts etc, but the word also has extended generalised uses, as in wèi sǐ 畏死 "be afraid to die".</p>
<p>4. Jīng 驚 refers to the sudden onset of fear when someone is faced with an unexpected danger.</p>
<p>5. Lì 栗 / 慄 and zhàn 戰 is to shiver with intense fear, and the physical expression of fear can be more prominent the inner feeling expressed through shivering.</p>
<p>6. Qiè 怯 "chicken-livered and unlikely to undertake risky tasks" and nuò 懦 (ant. yǒng 勇 "courage, boldness") as well as dàn 憚 "unduly prone to feelings of fear" refer to being pusilanimousness or the lack or courage where courage is required.</p>
<p>7. Bù 怖 "be in a current acute state of fear" has no weakened generalised uses.</p>
<p>8. Sǒng 悚 / 聳 "be fretful, given to fear; get slightly frightened" refers to mild forms of (possibly superfluous or reprehensible) fear.</p>
<p>9. Jì 悸 refers to symptoms of violent heart-beat caused by intense fear.</p>
<p>NB: Pà 怕 is post-Buddhist (TANG).</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>害怕</p>
<p>懼怕</p>
<p>生怕</p>
<p>怕</p>
<p>生恐</p>
<p>畏怯</p>
<p>畏懼</p>
<p>恐懼</p>
<p>疑懼</p>
<p>恐怖</p>
<p>膽寒</p>
<p>破膽</p>
<p>心寒</p>
<p>心悸</p>
<p>忌憚</p>
<p>畏葸</p>
<p>狼顧</p>
<p>懍懍</p>
<p>惶惑</p>
<p>失色</p>
<p>失容</p>
<p>惕息</p>
<p>戒懼</p>
<p>怵惕</p>
<p>悚然</p>
<p>震悚</p>
<p>喪膽</p>
<p>破膽 refers to being thoroughly frightened out of one's wits.</p>
<p>懾</p>
<p>恐</p>
<p>憚</p>
<p>懼</p>
<p>畏</p>
<p>怖</p>
<p>亡魂喪膽</p>
<p>聞風喪膽</p>
<p>喪魂落魄</p>
<p>魂不附體</p>
<p>魂飛魄散</p>
<p>魄散魂飛</p>
<p>戰戰兢兢</p>
<p>驚心掉膽</p>
<p>毛骨悚然</p>
<p>提心吊膽</p>
<p>膽顫心驚</p>
<p>心驚膽顫</p>
<p>心驚肉跳</p>
<p>心膽俱裂</p>
<p>不寒而栗</p>
<p>噤若寒蟬</p>
<p>驚恐萬狀</p>
<p>大驚失色</p>
<p>面如土色</p>
<p>面無人色</p>
<p>脅肩累足</p>
<p>視為畏途</p>
<p>望而生畏</p>
<p>望而卻步</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-15831024-bfe8-489b-b701-e1a0143abdd6">COWARDLY</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-1f8d86d4-83bd-4713-8936-fdd2916f040b">SHY</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-6332ab66-0ce7-4235-aaac-40d470a9be8d">ANGST</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-f170669d-cdeb-4b7d-811a-e32d9fa5a33e">FEELING</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b1c8c39d-b2b9-4994-80ba-33686a5c1fe8">APRESJAN 2004</ref>
<title>Novyj objasnitel'nyj Slovar' Sinonimov Russkogo Jazyka</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1109</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6676c2c0-86d9-4be8-9efc-d0429d4e1282">BERGENHOLTZ 1980</ref>
<title>Das Wortfeld Angst.  Eine lexikographische Untersuchung</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">16.53</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b8242ce-9fc6-4b7b-bd52-14c744308409">COMENIUS 1665</ref>
<title>De Rerum Humanarum Emendatione</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">449</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ABHORRERE</p>
<p>aliquid, est contactum illius metuere. 2. ideoque aversari aut si id nequit, fugere.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0090b598-0ae2-4d03-867a-7d1003984683">DELUMEAU 1978</ref>
<title>La peur en Occident</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4af55868-d85f-4a0a-b22a-adbf6ab4a3a8">DIFFERENTIAE I</ref>
<title>De differentiis</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">63</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>TIMIDUS, TIMENS</p>
<p>554. Ex Serv. ad ill. Eclog. 7, Timidisque supervenit [col. 66D] Aegle.</p>
<p>]</p>
<p>554. Inter Timentem et timidum. Timidus est qui semper timet, timens vero qui ad tempus formidat ex [col. 65C] causa. Tali intellectu distinguuntur pavidus et pavens, providus et providens, superbus et superbiens, languidus et languens, furibundus et furens, et caetera similia.</p>
<p>99</p>
<p>FORMIDO, PAVOR, METUS, TIMOR</p>
<p>214. Inter Formidinem, pavorem. et metum, sive [col. 32A] timorem. Formido objicitur, vel oculis, vel animo, sine adhibita ratione, et maxime parvulis, pavor autem cum timiditate animi subita est conturbans occasio, quae tamen solvitur ratione, vel tempore, nec stat, item metus est motus interior animi subitus, sive cordis, factus ex aliqua tristi recordatione. Timor vero est accedens dolor mentis extrinsecus, ex aliqua accidenti occasione. Porro timiditas animi vitium sempiternum est. Nam timor, pro tempore est. Itaque in viro forti est aliquando timor, timiditas nunquam. Est autem et bonus timor et malus. Malus est, cum temporalia bona quisque sibi subtrahi perhorrescit [ Al., abstrahi pertimescit]; bonus, cum quanto quis Deum ardentius diligit, tanto eum diligentius offendere pertimescit. Nam timere interdum [col. 32B] prodest, et decet, pro qualitate temporum atque causarum.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>FEAR</p>
<p>vereri is fear that has its foundation in what is strikingly venerable or perceived as such.</p>
<p>metuere is fear that has its source in a threatening danger inherent in an object or a situation, and it is based on anticipation of an impending evil, as well as reflection upon it, and it is based on prudence and foresight.</p>
<p>timere refers to fear of an impending danger that proceeds from cowardice and weakness rather than weakness.</p>
<p>ignavia is inaptitude for noble action and particularly for deeds of valour, for reasons of exaggerated fearfulness.</p>
<p>horror is an immediate feeling of fear which overpowers the understanding by some dreadful image, as a bodily expression of such a feeling.</p>
<p>formido is the immediate feeling of overpowering fear as a purely mental state.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc235203-2ca8-4006-a7f5-c3246090e146">DUFOUR 1910</ref>
<title>Traite elementaire des synonymes grecques</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">40</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">203</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8ee30d31-dbb4-4849-8d49-2aa25c81118f">LAFAYE 1884</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire des synonymes de la langue francaise. Avec une introduction sur la theorie des synonymes.</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">479</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>A. CRAINTE, APPREHENSION;   </p>
<p>B. INQUIETUDE, ALARME, PEUR;   </p>
<p>C. EPOUVANTE, EFFROI, FRAYEUR, TERREUR</p>
<p/>
<p>A. </p>
<p>Lafaye distinguishes "crainte" of a probable danger and "apprehension" of a possible danger: a brilliant definition.  "Crainte" is a involves an envisioning of what is dangerous, "apprehension" involves a suspicion concerning what may be dangerous.  These two words have the common feature that they focus on the intellectual rather than the emotive part of fear. Malebranche: "La crainte, qui produit la tristesse,, n'est point une emotion de l'ame, mais un simple jugement."  The same may be said about "apprehension".  Both these words are quite different from "inquietude, alarme, peur", even more from "epouvante, effroi, frayeur, terreur".</p>
<p/>
<p>B. </p>
<p>"Inquietude, alarme, peur" are weak forms of fear, "inqietude" being the weakest.</p>
<p>"Alarme" is an intense form of "inqietude".</p>
<p>"Peur" is subjective and less based on externals than on inner temperament, and the word is pejorative in the sense that it often denotes a lack of courage.</p>
<p/>
<p>C. </p>
<p>"Epouvante" is stronger than "peur", but like "peur" it connotes a tendency to flee from what is dangerous, a lack of proper courage.</p>
<p>"Effroi" connotes horror as well as strong, stifling fear.</p>
<p>"Frayeur" is transitory "effroi".</p>
<p>"Terreur" focusses on the state of the mind as caused by the envisaging of its cause.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>FORMIDO</p>
<p>METUS</p>
<p>PUSILLANIMITAS</p>
<p>TIMOR</p>
<p>VERECUNDIA</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2c59ecb-bbff-4004-8e45-5fc7f92ed0da">Mel'cuk 1984</ref>
<title>Tolkovo-kombinatornyj slovar' sovremmenogo russkogo jazyka. Explanatory Combinatorial Dictionary of Modern Russian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">163ff</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2c59ecb-bbff-4004-8e45-5fc7f92ed0da">Mel'cuk 1984</ref>
<title>Tolkovo-kombinatornyj slovar' sovremmenogo russkogo jazyka. Explanatory Combinatorial Dictionary of Modern Russian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">806</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">11</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-05ed74f0-1015-4215-90be-a8a88a450962">MENGZI TONGYI 2002</ref>
<title>“孟子”同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">239</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">3.1622</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4acb4e0c-daab-4369-9991-912c64da1ee6">RITTER 1971-2007</ref>
<title>Historisches Woerterbuch der Philosophie</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.1147</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>FURCHT UND MITLEID</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-3cf76dec-e8bc-4732-bde9-e5ca60e7fb1a">SCHMIDT 1889</ref>
<title>Handbuch der lateinischen und griechischen Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">116</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-e3cd2631-2db9-43d5-bf95-08ef4a75ad08">WIERZBICKA 1999</ref>
<title>Emotions across Languages and Cultures</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">123-167</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">742</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>畏，恐，懼</p>
<p>1. WL claims that these words are basically synonymous.  In fact, they differ clearly in basic semantic content.  We4i 畏 is basically a state of fear of what inspires awe and respect, perhaps shuddering awe, and indeed there are many cases where the meanings of the words hovers between fear and respect, encompassing elements of both;  ko3ng 恐 is momentary and powerful basically terrified fear of what is simply overpowering, although these words have occasional "blunted" or neutralised usages where they refer to generalised fear; and ju4 懼 is momentary fearful concern about an impending danger, thus a much weaker form of ko3ng 恐.  The cases where these words are interchangeable semantically are few.</p>
<p>2. WL claims that it is characteristic of ko3ng 恐 and ju4 懼 that these have causative uses, but we4i 畏 is also used in such causative senses "inspire fearfuyl awe in people".  Moreover, all these words are current as transitive non-causative words, contrary to what WL suggests.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b425a52b-7c3a-4b26-a4a5-8c5a55eaf19b">GRACE ZHANG 2010</ref>
<title>Using Chinese Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">296</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-93502795-e958-4bb9-ae45-2b1258a7d635">TENG SHOU-HSIN 1996</ref>
<title>Chinese Synonyms Usage Dictionary</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">167</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.25:22</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ALLARME.TERREUR.EFFROI.FRAYHEUR.EPOUVANTE.CRAINTE.PEUR.APPREHENSION</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.218.179</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>CRAINDRE.APPREHENDER.REDOUTER.AVOIR PEUR</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.390</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">362</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">48A</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">















































































    </div>
</div>