<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-069ae7d2-0c4f-45a4-99e0-012ab9c92fcf">
<head>FINAL PARTICLES</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">句後虛詞</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>PARTICLE USED at the END of a SENTENCE. [NOTE THAT THE GRAMMATICAL PARTICLES HAVE NOT BEEN FOCUSSED SO FAR IN THE SYSTEM AND NO SYSTEMATIC ANALYSIS HAS BEEN APPLIED SO FAR.]</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>LU JIANMING</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-976a96df-788e-40c3-9630-a579a83b7689">PARTICLE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="words">

<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-c50f0683-6469-4877-8095-0d926befdf1d">
            <form corresp="#uuid-32021026-3e9b-46d7-967b-a3563b36310b">
<orth>云</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yún</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢun</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦi̯un</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">476</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">476</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e2fa4e61-dc50-44f2-8216-c78fdf58bc75">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>marker of end of quotation</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-785f3b18-8bd2-4924-ab22-3eef816b7487">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-28210b5a-450e-4014-b362-39e05decea1c">euphonic</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>euphonic colloquial particle at the end of phrases 禮云禮云 "It is all a matter of ritual..."</def>
            </sense>
</entry>

<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-49e6aba2-826b-4233-bcee-5106589eef91">
            <form corresp="#uuid-9ef8de95-a9bb-45e9-a9eb-4ba693fb26c6">
<orth>來</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">lái</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">m-rɯɯ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ləi</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-91cce1db-78cb-4b26-80cc-55ad3d26b0cf">ANDERL 2004B</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zǔtáng jí 祖堂集</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">517-518</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>In this function la2i indicates that any action should be carried out for the sake of the speaker and it expresses the direct request to the addressee to carry out this action. It is actually often an action which could be carried out by the speaker himself but which is delegated to the addressee. Consequently la2i is usually used in dialogues by the person of higher rank. The person the action is carried out for, is sometimes marked by a coverb (usually by coverb yu3 與 which regularly appears in sentences expressing a request).1395 This usage is closely connected to the one discussed above: 'to come &gt; to come for the purpose of VERBING &gt; request to VERB for the speaker'. In this function I regard la2i as grammaticalized into a sentence final since the original meaning has faded away and it affects the whole proposition (changing it from a statement to a request).</p>
<p/>
<p>In the following two examples the benefactor of the action is marked by yu3 與 (COV):</p>
<p>1251) ZTJ 1.116; WU: 72</p>
<p>“與老僧過淨瓶水來。”</p>
<p>yu3 la3o-se1ng guo4 ji4ng pi2ng shui3 la2i</p>
<p>COV.INDIR/NPRO1SG.SEMIold-monk/pass(hand over)/pure/CLASSbottle/water/SF.IMP(REQUEST)</p>
<p>"Hand me over a jar with fresh water."</p>
<p/>
<p>1252) ZTJ 1.173; WU: 105</p>
<p>“汝與我擎缽盂來。”</p>
<p>ru3 yu3 wo3 qi2ng bo1-yu2 la2i</p>
<p>NPRO2SG/COV.BENEFACT/NPRO1SG/lift/alms bowl-jar/SF.IMP(REQUEST)</p>
<p>"Get the alms bowl for me."1396</p>
<p/>
<p>Note that la2i is restricted in its function to indicate a direct request (imperative). The contents of the request must indicate something which is performed for the sake of the speaker. As such the original meaning of la2i is still present to a certain extent.</p>
<p/>
<p>Note that la2i also has this function when it appears as part of the complex verbal complement jia1ng-la2i 將來 (V.COMP). In this construction jia1ng indicates the immanent future and la2i indicates that the action is directed towares the speaker and by extension a request:</p>
<p>1253) ZTJ 4.060; WU: 319</p>
<p>“併卻咽喉唇吻，"Closing your throught and your lips, </p>
<p>速道將來。”quickly speak up!"</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-5ab4b9b6-44e4-4d6b-865f-40d6b29547f3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c2c4bfc7-4e20-47c6-b583-2a4c5638d23b">vpostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2712e600-399e-41e1-8a65-af983a80bcff">past</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>deverbal sentence final particle indicating a past event (indicating temporal distance to the speech act, and typically action with a subjective purpose)</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-175456bc-2c95-41b2-bb94-cdf577ea6e9e">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c2c4bfc7-4e20-47c6-b583-2a4c5638d23b">vpostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-e92d19a7-9dd9-40f7-9e71-5075ae5c0b4d">request</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>come &gt; come for the purpose of &gt; do for the speaker &gt; sentence final expressing a request (to do something for the sake of the speaker); sometimes more neutrally expressing mild obligation or a suggestion</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-769361e0-cfc7-4804-a0a0-85948bfe1693">
            <form corresp="#uuid-827fc8a5-b76b-4a8f-b089-157ba660ab3f">
<orth>去</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">qù</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">khas</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">khi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a29b7ca5-5a6f-4955-b358-0520972b6159">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c2c4bfc7-4e20-47c6-b583-2a4c5638d23b">vpostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-96e19999-b4f5-4323-96c1-8371e72b18fd">future</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>leave from the speaker &gt; temporally distant from the speaker &gt; sentence final marking an event in the future (marking that the act/state indicated by S has not taken occurred yet; sometimes qù also seems to mark an intention)</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-208658e4-d69a-4bb4-87b5-34297006b322">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c2c4bfc7-4e20-47c6-b583-2a4c5638d23b">vpostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-b8276c57-c108-44c8-8c01-ad92679a9163">imperative</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>go and V &gt; go ahead and V (grammaticalized deverbal sentence final particle expressing a very mild imperative, an invitation to do something)</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1553c978-7dcf-4850-9016-09884e8a0fa9">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8ea309af-0157-4198-9940-927815f1972d">vpostadS1.post-S2</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-07753e6c-9183-4ff1-9668-399a8bc40c14">apodosis</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>go and V &gt; sentence final marking the apodosis in hypothetical conditions (if S2 then S1)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-aa510721-1a63-4ad2-aee5-29f8a6567ccb">
            <form corresp="#uuid-68383a76-4bb0-42bd-abf4-1567b3ccf244">
<orth>在</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zài</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sɡɯɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dzəi</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-91cce1db-78cb-4b26-80cc-55ad3d26b0cf">ANDERL 2004B</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zǔtáng jí 祖堂集</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">512-515, 537-539</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>According to Sun Xixin 1999: 87-92 sentence final za4i 在 (SF)  is commonly used in the vernacular texts of the late Tang and Song periods. He thinks that it often expresses the speaker's conviction that an event will take place in the future. Simultanously it seems to give emphasis to the speaker's statement. Za4i appeared in this function during the Tang and early examples can also be found in Tang poetry. During The Five Dynasties and Song periods the sentence final became more common in vernacular texts like the Recorded Sayings of the Cha2n school and Neo-Confucianists. During the Yuan period it gradually decreased in frequency and had completely become obsolete by Ming times.</p>
<p/>
<p>The original meaning of za4i 在 (VT) is 'to exist' and in this meaning it also regularly appeared at the end of a sentence. This probably was one of the preconditions for the development into a sentence final particle. During the Tang za4i at the end of the sentence began to be emptied of its original meaning and began to function as sentence final. It was suggested that in some examples it seems to function comparable to Modern Mandarin ne 呢 and li 哩.</p>
<p/>
<p/>
<p>2.3.2.3.5.2 PATTERNS WITH SENTENCE FINAL za4i 在</p>
<p/>
<p>Typical pattern of sentences with za4i in ZTJ and the Recorded Sayings and are:</p>
<p/>
<p>Pattern (a) yo3u 有 + NP(X) + za4i 在 'a certain NP(X) exists'</p>
<p/>
<p>1233) ZTJ 1.102; WU: 62</p>
<p>“更有庵在。”"There is another cottage (small hermitage) there."</p>
<p/>
<p>In this pattern zai4 still has its original meaning 'to exist'.</p>
<p/>
<p>Pattern (b) we4i 未 + VP + za4i 在 (SF)</p>
<p/>
<p>Za4i often appears in the pattern we4i 未 + VP + za4i 在. We4i 未 (NEG) originally means 'not yet' but in most examples it seems more appropriate to translate it with 'not', syn. to bu4 不. In sentences with adverbs of negation za4i seems to emphasize the fact that an action which should have been performed or was expected to be performed has actually not been performed after all.</p>
<p>1234) ZTJ 5.044; WU: 395</p>
<p>“去ㄐ未見老僧在ㄐ”</p>
<p>qu4 we4i jia4n la3o-se1ng za4i</p>
<p>leave/NEGnot yet/see&gt;understand/NPRO1SG.SEMIold-monk/SF.EMPHASIS</p>
<p>"Leave! You have not understood me (yet)!"</p>
<p/>
<p>1235) ZTJ 2.048; WU: 137</p>
<p>“這個人未出家在。”</p>
<p>zhe4-ge4 re2n we4i chu1-jia1 za4i</p>
<p>NPRO.DEMthis-CLASS/person/NEGnot yet/leave-family/SF.EMPHASIS</p>
<p>"This person has not yet left home (yet) (i.e. is not a real monk)!"</p>
<p/>
<p>1236) ZTJ 4.114; WU: 354</p>
<p>師云：The master said:</p>
<p>“某甲未喫茶在。”"I have not drunk tea yet."</p>
<p/>
<p>1237) ZTJ 2.120; WU: 174</p>
<p>“雖則如此，有人未許專甲在。”</p>
<p>sui1-ze2 ru2 ci3 yo3u re2n we4i xu3 zhua1n-jia3 za4i </p>
<p>SI.CONSalthough/be like/NPRO/exist/person/NEG/allow/NPRO1SF/SF.EMPHASIS</p>
<p>"Although it is like this, there is a person who does not allow [it] to me."</p>
<p/>
<p>Pattern (c) VP + za4i 在 (SF)</p>
<p/>
<p>In the following examples za4i gives emphasis to the statement, za4i 在 (SF.EMPHASIS):</p>
<p>1238) ZTJ 1.111,09; WU: 70</p>
<p>“猶持瓦礫在。” </p>
<p>yo2u chi2 wa3-li4 za4i</p>
<p>be like/hold/tile-gravel/SF.EMPHASIS</p>
<p>"This is like holding rubble."</p>
<p/>
<p>1239) ZTJ 5.138,05; WU: 450</p>
<p>“向後有多口阿師與你點破在。” </p>
<p>xia4ng-ho4u yo3u duo1-ko3u a1-shi1 yu3 ni3 dia3n-po4 za4i</p>
<p>afterwards/exist/many-word&gt;garrulous/PREF-master/COV.OBJ.INDIR/expose-break/SF.EMPHASIS?</p>
<p>"Afterwards there will be a garrulous monk who will expose you."</p>
<p/>
<p>Pattern (d) Constructions with multiple sentence finals: za4i often co-appears with sentence final qu4 去 and za4i is always postposed to qu4.</p>
<p/>
<p>1240) ZTJ 5.138,05; WU: 450</p>
<p>“長老與摩識弁人，"You elder are such an eloquent person, </p>
<p>瞎卻鎮州城裡人眼去在。”you are going to blind the eyes of the people of Zhe1nzho1u city."</p>
<p/>
<p>1241) ZTJ 2.092; WU: 160 </p>
<p>“每日在長連床上，"Everyday [sitting] on the long meditation platform</p>
<p>恰似漆村里土地相似！it just resembles adding earth in the village!</p>
<p>他時後日，on day in the future</p>
<p>魔魅人家男女去在！”you will deceive (bewitch) the men and women of the families!"</p>
<p/>
<p>1242) ZTJ 5.052; WU: 400</p>
<p>“但得其本，"Just [try to] attain the origin [of the mind]</p>
<p>不愁其末。not worrying about its perphery (lit. branches).</p>
<p>他時後日，[Then] one day in the future</p>
<p>自具足去在。”by itself it will suffice."</p>
<p/>
<p>In this pattern sentence final qu4 去 marks that the event is going to take place in the future and za4i 在 gives emphasis to the statement. Combined the two sentence finals mark the speaker's conviction that an event/action certainly will take place in the future.</p>
<p/>
<p>As mentioned above the original meaning of za4i is to 'to exist' and it was often used in patterns with localizers (N.GR.LOC):</p>
<p>za4i 在 + NP + zho1ng 中 (N.GR.LOC)</p>
<p>za4i 在 + NP + sha4ng 上 (N.GR.LOC)</p>
<p>za4i 在 + NP + li3 P (N.GR.LOC)</p>
<p/>
<p>1243) ZTJ 3.095; WU: 250</p>
<p>“老僧在你肚P。” </p>
<p>la3o-se1ng za4i ni3 du4 li3</p>
<p>NPRO1SG.SEMIold-monk/be in(exist in)/NPRO2SG/stomack/N.GR.LOCinside</p>
<p>"I am in your stomach (belly)."</p>
<p/>
<p>In phrases with za4i...li3 the NP was frequently deleted and the phrase was contracted to za4i li3 在裡, used at the end of the sentence.</p>
<p>1244) ZTJ 2.040; WU: 133</p>
<p>“若与摩和尚來時，"If that's the case then, when the Preceptor comes,</p>
<p>莫向他說納僧在裡。”don't tell him that there is a monk here."</p>
<p/>
<p>li3 裡 also appears in the form li3-xu3 裡許:1386</p>
<p>1245) ZTJ 3.111; WU: 262</p>
<p>師云：“曹山在裡許。”</p>
<p>shi1 yu2n Ca2osha1n za4i li3-xu3</p>
<p>master/say/NPR/be at/N.GR.LOC-SUFF</p>
<p>The master said: "Ca2osha1n is inside."</p>
<p/>
<p>In ZTJ 在裡 is still used in its original meaning, expressing the location of a  certain object but during Song times this construction was emptied of its original meaning. Originally a NP had to be placed inbetween za4i and li3 but from Song times onwards also a VP could be inserted between the two elements. Thus the construction did not express any longer a location but began to function as sentence final construction giving emphasis to an utterance (SUN XIXIN 1999: 91).</p>
<p>Also the construction with deleted object, za4i li3 在裡 underwent a similar change and it was emptied of its original meaning. There seems to have occurred a shift from marking a concrete location to an abstract location (such as a proposition/speech act).</p>
<p>One reason for this development possibly is the following: During the Tang and Five Dynasties periods both za4i and li3 were already used as sentence finals independently and in the course of time za4i li3 began to be interpreted as sentence finals in a sequence.</p>
<p>Interestingly, also the construction za4i zhe4-li3 在這裡 underwent a similar development. In Song texts it usually still has its literaty meaning 'be here' (WUDENG) but in some sentences it already seems to have the function of giving emphasis to a statement (e.g. in ZHUZI). During the Yuan and Ming periods it clearly could function as sentence final affirming a statement (SUN XIXIN 1999: 92 and YU GUANGZHONG 1986 who analyzes the construction in SHUIHUZHUAN).</p>
<p/>
<p>The frequency of sentence final za4i it ZTJ is quite high (F: &gt; 50) and as such it is one of the most frequently used vernacular sentence finals in ZTJ. Many of the examples of za4i appear in a derogatory context, and the phrases it appears in often express a notion of despise. As a consequence, in dialogues it is usually used by the person relatively higher in rank (i.e. the master).</p>
<p/>
<p>An analysis of za4i in ZTJ shows that it does not function to indicate an event in the future or the speaker's conviction that an event/action will take place in the future. This function seems rather to be indicated by qu4 去 which often appears together with za4i. The primary function of za4i is the adding of emphasis of a statetment, and the function probably derived from its original meaning 'exist &gt; that's how it is'; in its original meaning it indicates a concrete location whereas as sentence final it marks and gives emphasis to an abstract location, such as the proposition of the speech act.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-9e3fec7b-f4bc-4645-bd35-e87b8a7f5d92">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c2c4bfc7-4e20-47c6-b583-2a4c5638d23b">vpostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-5ae85a4e-5823-417b-b04f-58d7d9f263f5">emphatic</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>exist &gt; that's how it is &gt; sentence final particle giving emphasis to a statement (frequently used in vernacular texts of the late Tang and Song periods)</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d0d7df23-3b3e-47c4-847c-e40e4391f177">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c2c4bfc7-4e20-47c6-b583-2a4c5638d23b">vpostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-5ae85a4e-5823-417b-b04f-58d7d9f263f5">emphatic</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>exist &gt; that's how it is &gt; sentence final particle giving emphasis to a statement (frequently used in vernacular texts of the late Tang and Song periods); in the pattern with negated VP (the negator is usually 未) the emphasis is on the fact that an action should have been performed or was expected to be performed, but was in fact not</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-56d0b8e8-fad8-4439-a019-680ccb39c0a8">
            <form corresp="#uuid-f3fd05c7-81ff-4e2d-b8b2-b7eee24b8fe0">
<orth>婆</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">pó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">baal</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">bʷɑ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-554d8ecc-c1de-47b6-88a7-ef297bd1d5e7">FENG CHUNTIAN 2000</ref>
<title>近代漢語語法研究 Jìndài hànyǔ yǔfǎ yánjiū</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">524-526</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-5aa05892-3502-427d-8eaa-2e012120ea53">KARASHIMA 1997</ref>
<title>漢譯佛典的語言研究 Hànyì Fódiǎn de yǔyán yánjiū [Studies in the Language of Buddhist Texts from the Han Period] 俗語言研究 Suyuyan yanjiu</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">45-47</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-76e161d4-5165-4fbc-874a-92a5f88867fe">LONG GUOFU 2004</ref>
<title>姚秦譯經助詞研究 Yáo Qín yìjīng zhùcí yánjiū Studies in Function Words in the Translated Buddhist Scriptures of the Yáo Qín Period Wei Jin NanBeichao Hanyi fojing yuyan yanjiu congshu</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">259-263</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>Long counts 12 examples of sentence final 婆 in the BINAIYE, clearly indicating a question. In affirmative sentences &gt; demanding the answer yes or no (similar to the later 摩); it also appears in sentences with negated main verbs and in these cases it seems to corrspond to 耶 or 乎. in the BINAIYE 不 and 婆 are used parallel and in a similar way., therefore it is by some regarded as 音變形式 (form representing a sound change) of 不. However, Long doubts this interpretation and also points out the two examples in ZTJ where po2 is rather used similiar to Modern Chinese 吧 (Iriya interpretes it like this). Long interpretes it as representation of a final particle in a local dialect.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f544b6d7-27fb-418d-afac-62149ea6218f">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-d82256cd-a1c1-4a58-b15f-615a92237386">question</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>This is a rare EMC interrogative sentence final particle (discovered by Seishi  Karshima) used in the 鼻奈耶 tr. by Zhú Fóniàn 竺佛念 (used similarly to the later 摩) (examples see in SOURCES)</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-16a5515a-2a56-449f-9d23-2bf74adc5cdf">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-ff53e5da-89f7-4601-ae05-d2119e933dfa">rhetorical question</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>this is an extremely rare sentence final particle (discovered by Seishi Karashima in the BINAIYE), in ZTJ it appears two times and is used quite differently from the examples in BINAIYE, in ZTJ it rather seems to function like Modern Mandarin final 吧</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-c5a6ade3-ad44-4d13-b569-b222c345e30e">
            <form corresp="#uuid-e799b325-78d4-4326-a46d-ca3498ecce7a">
<orth>已</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yǐ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">k-lɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">jɨ</pron>
            </form>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-dcf84913-0918-42b6-b7b7-12564f5148b8">
            <form corresp="#uuid-62efd968-fcbb-4774-9c42-a22187c35c91">
<orth>摩</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">mó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">maal</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">mʷɑ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b5fd3fd3-001b-4ebe-82e9-0d3b034abd04">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2d131ece-0e8e-4fd3-8839-9395b7aa4b14">colloquial</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>vernacular interrogative sentence final particle, indicating a yes/no question (precursor of Modern Chinese 嗎)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-6db77d38-5b17-4006-a94f-d7687e80719d">
            <form corresp="#uuid-5e796aa6-3208-44c6-bb32-f95a2c00c89a">
<orth>焉</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yān</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qran</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔiɛn</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-cab82859-7455-4e19-b105-ad38459b1a4c">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-ef863d81-5e5e-4d13-9533-e7b878cc3edc">result</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>from it&gt; as a result</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1ef8d9bc-c7a7-4c3a-893c-0d072d3766ff">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-3427424e-b45e-41c1-a64d-21b6508958ae">vi{vt+npro}.postadV</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>contraction for 於之: in it; from it; to it; than it; by it</def>
            </sense>

</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2658efd6-16e8-4cd6-a652-54f1ef611450">
            <form corresp="#uuid-9bbb9d85-e760-4462-bd4e-779a8bb1b5da">
<orth>爾</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">ěr</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">mljelʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ȵiɛ</pron>
            </form>

</entry>

<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-ee0cf7bf-38cf-41e1-b4af-307bae7e7834">
            <form corresp="#uuid-638f5102-6260-4085-891d-9864102bc27c">
<orth>者</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhě</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kljaʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕɣɛ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-55305d78-9a29-45ba-a8a3-9d260ba3b2df">HU ZHU'AN 1958</ref>
<title>宋元白話作品中語氣助詞 Sòng Yuán báihuà zhōng yǔqì zhùcí [Modal Auxiliaries in the Vernacular Literature of the Sòng and Yuán Periods] 中國語文 Zhongguo yuwen</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-8f4dbb99-a843-4bae-9bfb-5057b568a6e6">LV SHUXIANG 1984</ref>
<title>漢語語法論文集 Hànyǔ yǔfǎ lùnwénjí A Collection of Articles on Chinese Grammar</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">70</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-846f849d-88b3-4e56-bebc-c13365bedd85">SUN XIXIN 1997</ref>
<title>漢語歷史語法叢稿 Hànyǔ lìshǐ yǔfǎ cónggǎo An Outline of an Historical Grammar of Chinese</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">72</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c5071353-00d4-49f2-ba16-266fa8183ab5">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-b8276c57-c108-44c8-8c01-ad92679a9163">imperative</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2020-03-05T01:49:36.861+09:00">vernacular (Tang dynasty) sentence final particle expressing an imperative/prohibition</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-6431f5cc-f3e5-4037-b701-e10ed8fe1dcd">
            <form corresp="#uuid-7c88fece-5607-45d0-8d33-133b97cc251d">
<orth>耳</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">ěr</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">mljɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ȵɨ</pron>
            </form>

<sense xml:id="uuid-49f3ec5c-b76d-4f5b-a6ba-ed9a7488a72e">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-5ae85a4e-5823-417b-b04f-58d7d9f263f5">emphatic</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2024-02-26T01:44:55.365+09:00">=而已 emphatic sentence final particle: and that's how it is, and there is nothing to add to this matter, and that's all to it (the scope typically is the whole sentence and not some constituent inside it.</def>
            </sense>
        </entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-be3ddd71-d955-4d5c-ab00-0742a167cbea">
            <form corresp="#uuid-724ba4a2-8b6e-4d50-97be-800a29d2944d">
<orth>邪</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yé</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">la</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">jɣɛ</pron>
            </form>
            <form corresp="#uuid-cf26f85b-5790-48dc-93fd-fdd13dc565f8">
<orth>邪</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yé</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">k-la</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">jɣɛ</pron>
            </form>



</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-80814ba7-0fc7-4c5a-b36c-6e1e3be92044">
            <form corresp="#uuid-257cc1ea-48fa-40f5-bcac-2e75328d6894">
<orth>著</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhuó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">k-laɡ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈi̯ɐk</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-498d85c4-d730-4ae0-bcd2-e2f3a58da628">ANDERL 2004C</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zu-tang Ji 祖堂集</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-cb17830b-5acc-4f5a-9be0-ba9470f72ff6">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>colloquial sentence final particle giving emphasis to a judgemental conclusion/apodosis (it seems to used in the way of sentence final 去 or 在 here)</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e7427ad5-db71-433c-8f74-5e21bcb922fa">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2d131ece-0e8e-4fd3-8839-9395b7aa4b14">colloquial</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>colloquial sentence final particle: usually expressing a straightforward imperative; however, occasionally expressing a somewhat 'indirect' imperative and conveying the notion of strong obligation</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f18e6d83-7d8c-49ca-b635-8cf9118bfc95">
            <form>
<orth>那</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin"/>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc"/>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc"/>
            </form>

</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-d27f137f-c5d6-4fff-b310-0bcda1d794fc">
            <form corresp="#uuid-c27dc167-4b8e-4dd1-9a2d-95754ccec107">
<orth>麼</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">mǒ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">maalʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">mʷɑ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-2f0132dc-3a05-4201-8150-6fefbdd270cb">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2d131ece-0e8e-4fd3-8839-9395b7aa4b14">colloquial</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>vernacular interrogative sentence final particle, indicating a yes/no question (precursor of Modern Chinese 嗎)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-cbd373c3-bcff-4951-912e-f312425e59c9">
            <form corresp="#uuid-208b48d4-5b38-4edb-8418-80f4dcff11e3 #uuid-5de002ac-c1a1-4519-a177-4a3afcc155bb">
<orth>也無</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yě wú</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lalʔ ma</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">jɣɛ mi̯o</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-10796444-8b6a-4471-bbd7-12c74bf7eaba">OTA 1958</ref>
<title>中國語歷史文法 Chūgokugo rekishi bunpō A Historical Grammar of the Chinese Language</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-c678cffb-3790-4b8c-a57d-27cc0c95d12c">PAN CHONGZHONG 1982</ref>
<title>漢語語法史概要 Hànyǔ yǔfǎ shǐ gàiyào An Outline of the History of Chinese Grammar</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-80ae2ee5-ca69-4ba8-90dc-e207aa53d945">SUN XIXIN 1999</ref>
<title>近代漢語語氣詞 Jìndài hànyǔ yǔqǐcí Sentence Final Modal Particles in Early Mandarin</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">50-60</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-c111c87d-9108-40ab-a231-c80b81a13ca4">WANG LI 1989</ref>
<title>漢語語法史 Hànyǔ yǔfǎ shǐ A History of Chinese Grammar</title>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>

</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-604fde62-a5f1-492e-bec4-41104680808e">
            <form corresp="#uuid-9ee768eb-a750-42e6-ba2b-6dc77cbb010e #uuid-208b48d4-5b38-4edb-8418-80f4dcff11e3">
<orth>了也</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">liǎo yě</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">reewʔ lalʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">leu jɣɛ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-91cce1db-78cb-4b26-80cc-55ad3d26b0cf">ANDERL 2004B</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zǔtáng jí 祖堂集</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">490-491</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>Sentence final ye3 frequently occurs in combination with semi-grammticalized lia3o 了. There have been numerous suggestions how lia3o ye3 了也 should be interpreted in this construction. I think that the sequence of those two markers should be interpreted along the line with their individual functions. </p>
<p/>
<p>The typical function of lia3o 了  in ZTJ is to mark relative anteriority of a VP(X) to a VP(Y) in the pattern VP(X) + lia3o 了  + VP(Y). Lia3o indicates that an action is completed and ye3 expresses perfective, and indicating that the consequences of the action are still relevant at the moment of the speech act:</p>
<p/>
<p>In the following example co-occurring with yi3 已:</p>
<p>1163) ZTJ 1.150; WU: 90</p>
<p>“你已是受戒了也， </p>
<p>ni3 yi3 shi4 sho4u jie4 lia3o ye3</p>
<p>NPRO2SG/ADV.TEMPalready/COP.EMPHASIS/receive/precept/V.GR.TEMPcomplete/SF.PERF</p>
<p>"You have already received the precepts</p>
<p>還聽律也無？”do you still obey to the disciplinary rules?"</p>
<p/>
<p>In the sentence above the person has already received the set of precepts, i.e. the event of being ordained is completed and has occurred in the past. However, this event has consequences which are still relevant at the moment of the speech act, indicated by the question whether the person still obeys to the precepts.</p>
<p/>
<p>1164) ZTJ 1.156,02; WU: 94</p>
<p>“何不問老僧？”"Why do you not ask me?"</p>
<p>僧曰： The monk said:</p>
<p>“問則問了也。”"I have already asked [you]."</p>
<p/>
<p>1165) ZTJ 1.166; WU: 101</p>
<p>師曰： The master said:</p>
<p>“吃飯也未?”"Have you eaten?"</p>
<p>對曰：[The monk] answered:</p>
<p>“喫飯了也。”"I have [already] eaten."</p>
<p/>
<p>In the next example co-occurring together with za3o 早 'already' which can function synonymous to yi3 已 in vernacular texts:</p>
<p>1166) ZTJ 1.173; WU: 105</p>
<p>雲嵒問：Yu2nya2n asked:</p>
<p>“一句子如何言說?”"How about expounding one sentence with words?" </p>
<p>師曰：The master said:</p>
<p>“非言說。”"There are no words to expound (express) [it]."</p>
<p>道吾曰：Da4owu2 said:</p>
<p>“早說了也。”"I have already expounded (expressed) [it]."</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>

</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-09e864f6-e8f4-4418-bffe-47b32ac044c2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-32021026-3e9b-46d7-967b-a3563b36310b #uuid-9bbb9d85-e760-4462-bd4e-779a8bb1b5da">
<orth>云爾</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yún ěr</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢun mljelʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦi̯un ȵiɛ</pron>
                <ptr type="compound-id-ref" target="#uuid-a0da14bb-d0f5-4204-86ed-9093d6f0a17a"/>
            </form>

</entry>

<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-8a147961-7d7f-4b33-a8a0-9926aa1d9c68">
            <form corresp="#uuid-e799b325-78d4-4326-a46d-ca3498ecce7a #uuid-644760a0-b567-4543-90dd-32afbfa9849c">
<orth>已矣</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yǐ yǐ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">k-lɯʔ ɢɯʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">jɨ ɦɨ</pron>
            </form>

</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-d1b96739-c1fa-4af5-9485-2799ed3cc0c1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-644760a0-b567-4543-90dd-32afbfa9849c #uuid-37d48986-0938-4d3c-84fb-6e713e43a651">
<orth>矣哉</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yǐ zāi</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢɯʔ skɯɯ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɨ tsəi</pron>
                <ptr type="compound-id-ref" target="#uuid-dd191d8b-31fa-4f37-9baf-8702c3cbf719"/>
            </form>


</entry>

<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-65e069bd-d162-4c39-9754-18d5262c5f96">
            <form corresp="#uuid-c21f7a99-de70-44d2-a0e2-4266db4736bd">
                <orth>夫</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">fú</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc" resp="rec:baxter">bju</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc" resp="rec:pan-wuyun">ba</pron>
            </form>

</entry>
    <entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-1ec71807-27c5-4141-b31f-2f33d1ae84fe" resp="#CH" tls:created="2019-12-17T23:02:41.957+09:00">
            <form corresp="#uuid-724ba4a2-8b6e-4d50-97be-800a29d2944d">
                <orth>耶</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yé</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc" resp="rec:baxter">yae</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc" resp="rec:pan-wuyun">la</pron>
            </form>
            <sense xml:id="uuid-d723c8b7-f607-4f04-909f-6d8421cf8999" resp="#CH" tls:created="2019-12-17T23:02:41.957+09:00">
                <gramGrp>
                    <pos>P</pos>
                    <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c086c9bd-8ec5-463f-9803-c938c8b0d4d9">ppostadS</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
                <def>question marker</def>
            </sense>
        </entry>
    </div>
</div>