<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-a7781b07-2b28-4722-910c-4465de00a1ef">
<head>FORGIVE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>FORGIVING</item>
<item>MILD</item>
<item>MERCY</item>
<item>PARDON</item>
<item>PARDON</item>
<item>EXCUSE</item>
<item>EXONERATE</item>
<item>ABSOLVE</item>
<item>MAKE ALLOWANCES FOR</item>
<item>FEEL NO RESENTMENT TOWARD</item>
<item>FEEL NO MALICE TOWARD</item>
<item>HARBOR NO GRUDGE AGAINST</item>
<item>BURY THE HATCHET WITH</item>
<item>LET BYGONES BE BYGONES</item>
<item>INFORMAL LET OFF (THE HOOK)</item>
<item>FORMAL EXCULPATE</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">原諒</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">宥</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>PROMISE someone one ASSUMES to be GUILTY of a CRIME OR MISTAKE which OFFENDS ONE so as to SAY that one WILL NOT HATE THAT PERSON BECAUSE of that CRIME OR MISTAKE.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The most general current word for leniency and forgiveness is yòu 宥 (ant. kè 刻 "strict and ruthless").</p>
<p>2. Kuān 寬 (ant. kè 刻 "ruthless strictness") refers to a general attitude of mind which inclines one to pardon others and to show forgiveness.</p>
<p>3. Róng 容 is an individual act of forgiveness or pardoning vis-a-vis a person who is guilty of something or might be blamed for something.</p>
<p>4. Shì 釋 refers to a personal act of forgiveness directed at a certain person, and in regard of a certain action.</p>
<p>5. Shù 恕 (ant.* chóu 仇 "take a strict hostile attitude to") refers to acts of forgiveness as well as an understanding attitude which involves forgiveness as a virtue.</p>
<p>6. Shè 赦 refers more properly to the formal act of pardoning or acquiting in court, but the word is also commonly used for mental acts of non-legal social forgiveness.</p>
<p>7. Shì 貰 is too rare to be very sure of it, but the word is used to refer to forgiveness as something psychological rather than as a social act merely promising non-punishment.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>原諒 is the current colloquial word for forgiving somehing.</p>
<p>原宥 focusses on the tolerance of the forgiver.</p>
<p>寬宥 (lit) focusses on the tolerance of the person who forgives.</p>
<p>寬貸 (lit) is to pardon in a formal way.</p>
<p>見諒 is particularly current in performative contexts like 請見諒</p>
<p>見宥 (lit) focusses on tolerance in view of a transgression.</p>
<p>寬容 (lit) focusses on tolerance in view of a transgression.</p>
<p>見原 (lit, arch) refers to forgiveness in an old-fashioned way.</p>
<p>擔待 focusses on the bearing with something which forgiving practically implies.</p>
<p>包涵 refers to forgiveness in terms of leaving room for transgressors.</p>
<p>海涵 (lit, arch) refers very formally and periphrastically to polite and symbolic forgiveness.</p>
<p>包荒 (dial) refers to forgiveness as an act of generosity.</p>
<p>涵容 (lit) focusses on the willingness to live with an offence or an offender which is involved in forgiving.</p>
<p>包容 refers to tolerant forgiveness.</p>
<p>優容 focusses on the special treatment involved in an act of forgiveness.</p>
<p>諒察 refers to a (requested) investigation of something in a forgiving spirit, and the word is marginal in the group.</p>
<p>諒解 focusses on understanding.</p>
<p>白饒 focusses on the letting someone off without taking any action one obviously could have taken.</p>
<p>容 (cl) focusses on the non-narrowness of the moral perspective involved.</p>
<p>原 (cl) focusses on the empathy and understanding involved in forgiving.</p>
<p>諒 (cl) focusses on the moral confidence and understanding shown towards to forgivee.</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-876bb1f3-4a64-44d4-a352-38216cb8f038">ACCUSE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-905c9129-3533-429c-98da-91d01635f2c9">BLAME</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-58343a1a-8cf0-4be2-a65d-c8e4f9392722">ANGER</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b4700a09-fdca-4ff2-93cc-1c0726d4897d">GENEROUS</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-247311de-b762-4cdf-92db-b006cb9fdf7d">PARDON</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-7bdf4fa2-873a-4896-898a-416d49d002a3">ACQUIT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-247311de-b762-4cdf-92db-b006cb9fdf7d">PARDON</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-cb9fb7d3-752e-4db2-82df-7d0eacac269d">PROMISE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-726fde12-1c46-4bf4-bbb8-cadeb7abdd34">AUROUX 1990</ref>
<title>Les notions philosophiques Encyclopedie philosophique universelle</title>
                <note>
<p>Insubstantial small article, which does, however manage to supplement the magisterial survey in Historisches Wörterbuch der Philosophie on "Verzeihen".</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">16.69</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-c6a5120d-a888-44ce-b517-b0cbba82518a">CASSIN 2004</ref>
<title>Vocabulaire européen des philosophies. Dictionnaire des intraduisibles</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1093</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Brilliant brief survey by Barbare Cassin herself, contrasting the Greek notion of common knowledge establishing a common "us" through the declaration of sympathetic understanding, versus the hierarchical disregarding/ignoring (ignosco), remission of what is owed (pardonare). It was the latter paradigm which came to dominate in Western Europe.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>FORGIVE</p>
<p>ignoscere refers to the moral act of forgiving someone from one's heart for an immoral act, and to be prepared to forget all about this act.</p>
<p>veniam dare refers to a political act by which one allows clemency to take the place of formal justice.</p>
<p/>
<p>MILD</p>
<p>mitis refers to mildness versus harshness.</p>
<p>lenis refers to gentleness versus vehemence.</p>
<p>placidus refers to mild composure versus restless or nervous hustle.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4beb5f76-f7ca-4c25-b417-0e270bb1cde9">GRISWOLD 2007</ref>
<title>Forgiveness</title>
                <note>
<p>Rich discussion of many of the issues raised in modern philosophical literature on forgiveness. With an interesting detailed discussion of J. Butler's seminal analysis.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-68b55112-fdef-41ee-be4b-d2f5a434f2f4">HARBSMEIER 2009</ref>
<title>Forgiveness and Forbearance in Ancient China </title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-327e6378-eea5-49ad-af87-ab293e9dfd22">KRASOVEC 1999</ref>
<title>Reward, Punishment, and Forgiveness: The Thinking and Beliefs of Ancient Israel in the Light of Greek and modern Views</title>
                <note>
<p>One of the few detailed comparatist analyses. Indispensable.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8ee30d31-dbb4-4849-8d49-2aa25c81118f">LAFAYE 1884</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire des synonymes de la langue francaise. Avec une introduction sur la theorie des synonymes.</title>
                <note>
<p>PARDONNER</p>
<p>Excellent survey of the French synonymy.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>EXCUSARE</p>
<p>Unfortunately, this does not concentrate on the aspects of forgiveness that interest me here. The recommendations quoted in this instance are for unforgiving moral strictness.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ignoscere is to ignore the offence and to cease to resent.</p>
<p>veniam dare refers to remission of punishment.</p>
<p>condonare refers to an act of grace letting someone go free.</p>
<p>indulgere refers to an emotional act of leniency.</p>
<p>conivere in re is to refuse to do one's official duty and let someone go free.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-69668762-87a6-463f-b58f-ec6090f8c928">METZLER 1991</ref>
<title>Der griechische Begriff des Verzeihens</title>
                <note>
<p>Indispensable handbook. Something of a philological masterpiece.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4acb4e0c-daab-4369-9991-912c64da1ee6">RITTER 1971-2007</ref>
<title>Historisches Woerterbuch der Philosophie</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">11.1020</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>VERZEIHEN VERGEBEN</p>
<p>Magisterial concise survey of the literature and the main results. Indispensable.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b425a52b-7c3a-4b26-a4a5-8c5a55eaf19b">GRACE ZHANG 2010</ref>
<title>Using Chinese Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">346</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-55346dd4-de2a-46ce-a93f-ce0f27d001a5">BORCHERT 2005</ref>
<title>The Encyclopedia of Philosophy</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.282.240</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>PARDON.REMISSION.ABSOLUTION</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">63B</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>GNADE</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">
















































    </div>
</div>