<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-2b02173a-4036-4917-911f-fc00505a6adf">
<head>GRINDSTONE</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">磨刀石</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">磑</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>FLAT STONE USED FOR GRINDING.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. Ài 磑 refers to the round grindstone revolving on an axle. It is not completely clear whether the implement to which the word refers was used to grind the grain or to remove the husk. It is also not known when round revolving grindstones actually began to be used. The oldest finds dates from the Warrring States period, and in Han times they were already common.</p>
<p>2. Mó 磨 originally referred to the polishing; in Han times the word began to be used for grinding grain and like another term for a grindstone.</p>
<p>3. Lóng 礱 refers to the grindstone for removing husk of the grain.</p>
<p>NB: It is difficult to distinguish the terms which follows below and attribute them to concrete archaeological finds; but it is at least obvious that part of them, particularly lì 礪 and lì 厲 does not fit the definition given above. Round grindstones seems to be no older than the Warring States period (CHEN 1991: 199) and it is highly probable that particularly archaic whetstones described below were quite simple implements like these illustrated in XIANG 1997: pp. 58, fig. 1, 2]</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>磨刀石</p>
<p>礪石</p>
<p>油石</p>
<p>硎</p>
<p>砥</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b082ea1d-6e1a-49de-a989-bcad816f37a2">WHETSTONE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-4a3ff01e-b3ed-4980-b8c8-ff65f3a076ed">STONE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">809</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>砥，厲，礪</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">







    </div>
</div>