<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-0ec5e516-7549-4985-bfe3-c44f344e574b">
<head>HAND UP</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>OFFER</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">獻上</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">獻</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>TRANSMIT to a SUPERIOR.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current general word for handing something up to superiors is xiàn 獻 (ant. cì 賜 "present to inferior").</p>
<p>2. Jìn 進 is a very common bureaucratic word for submitting something to a superior.</p>
<p>3. Fèng 奉 is a rather dramatic word depicting a person handing something up with both hands (possibly with the intention of making a formal gift of it, xiàn 獻.</p>
<p>4. Nà 納 is a cold strictly bureaucratic term referring to the handing some upwards in the hierarchy.</p>
<p>5. Gòng 貢 refers to the formal and ritual handing up or pledging of something to high authorities (typically tribute) in the course of one's ritual or political duties (the two being not held apart in ancient Chinese society). This tribute may even consist of lands or populations.</p>
<p>6. Bǐng 稟 refers to handing up something to high authority (typically reports) with a show of extreme but customary deferential politeness.</p>
<p>7. Xiào 效 typically refers to the offering up of abstract things such as effort on behalf of high authority.</p>
<p>8. Zòu 奏 refers to the formal submission of a text to the highest authorities, and typically to the emperor.</p>
<p>9. Shàng 上 is a neutral word referring to the submission of anything to someone higher up in the official hierarchy.</p>
<p>10. Gōng 供／共 refers to the provision of what is necessary to the higher authorities.</p>
<p>11. Nà 納 is to hand in formally to the authorities.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>獻上</p>
<p>交</p>
<p>繳</p>
<p>捐獻</p>
<p>捐輸</p>
<p>捐</p>
<p>輸</p>
<p>獻</p>
<p>奉</p>
<p>呈獻</p>
<p>貢獻</p>
<p>奉獻</p>
<p>進奉</p>
<p>孝敬</p>
<p>進貢</p>
<p>朝貢</p>
<p>芹獻</p>
<p>獻芹</p>
<p>first rough draft to identify synonym group members for future analysis, based on CL. 18.11.2003. CH</p>
        </div>
<div type="old-chinese-contrasts">
<p>1. Some words refer to a highly formal act of submitting something (gòng 貢, fèng 奉, bǐng 稟, and zòu 奏 ).</p>
<p>2. Some words are restricted to the submission of text (zòu 奏 ).</p>
<p>3. Some words are specialised on the submission of action in the service of someone (xiào 效 ).</p>
<p>4. Some words take only concrete objects (gòng 貢, fèng 奉 )</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-6309fae2-a71b-4620-84ca-f80bbd8eae6d">BRIBE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-a823943f-8158-412e-8e21-e4cdda760789">PAY</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ed1aeb49-abff-4167-a18e-60c0f2202d63">GIVE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>HAND UP</p>
<p>conferre denotes the carrying of something to a central authority, typically as an offering.</p>
<p>comportare denotes the carrying of something by one authority to a higher authority.</p>
<p/>
<p>OFFER</p>
<p>praebere denotes a voluntary act of the giver by which a want or wish of the receiver is satisfied, and in particular the thing given was in the possession of the giver.</p>
<p>exhibere can refer to a voluntary act of delivering something to someone who is thought to have the best claim to what he is given.</p>
<p>praestare denotes an involuntary act of the giver who only fulfills a duty, as the English "discharge".</p>
<p>suppeditare is the habitual and abundant giving wherever it is necessary.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">281</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1321</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>1. WL claims that go4ng 貢 is generally to the emperor whereas xia4n 獻 refers to giving a respectful gift to anyone.  In fact, all courts had the go4ng 貢 system, and the crucial point is that go4ng 貢 refers to the formal and ritual presentation of what is owed as tribute, whereas xia4n 獻 can refer to anything one wishes to respectfully give to superiors.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-93502795-e958-4bb9-ae45-2b1258a7d635">TENG SHOU-HSIN 1996</ref>
<title>Chinese Synonyms Usage Dictionary</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">141</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-93502795-e958-4bb9-ae45-2b1258a7d635">TENG SHOU-HSIN 1996</ref>
<title>Chinese Synonyms Usage Dictionary</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">237</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">



























    </div>
</div>