<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-7580f81e-0340-443b-88a3-04c3f129428c">
<head>HOOK</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">鉤子</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">鉤</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>ROUND SHARP TOOL USED to CATCH FISH PULL OR SUSPEND THINGS. []</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current general word for a hook is gōu 鉤, which can refer to:</p>
<p>a. the fishhook, mentioned for the Warring States in ZHUANGZI. Fishhooks can be made of bone or metal; bone ones are known since the Neolithic, bronze ones since the early Shang period.</p>
<p>b. belt-hook, which came to use in the late Western Zhou and Chunqiu period, and became common in Warring States times. It was made of bronze, iron, gold, silver, jade, or ivory; valuable pieces were richly inlaid with precious metals or turquoise.</p>
<p>c. the hook to hang up something; the most remarkable among this group are hooks for suspending bronze bells, which are known already from the early Chunqiu period.</p>
<p>d. the word can also refer to the implements and weapons with a hook or to the crooked artefacts; the term is therefore used for the ladders with a hook to climb city walls (mentioned already in SHIJING), crooked swords mentioned in HANSHU, and sickles.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>鉤子</p>
<p>掛鉤</p>
<p>鉤頭　</p>
<p>鉤</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-403b2f16-b0b3-487b-905b-dd6a0a609f57">TOOL</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">12.75</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.12</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">100B</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">


    </div>
</div>