<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-7e9d0c54-d1a9-4c11-9ba1-3ec882fbd1c1">
<head>INVITE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>ASK</item>
<item>SUMMON</item>
<item>HAVE SOMEONE OVER</item>
<item>REQUEST SOMEONE'S COMPANY</item>
<item>REQUEST THE PLEASURE OF SOMEONE'S COMPANY</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">邀請</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">延</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>RITUALLY REQUEST someone to JOIN one in an ACT:activity one ASSUMES to be MUTALLY PLEASANT.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. An ordinary general word for a ritualised invitation is yán 延.</p>
<p>2. Yāo 要 refers to a rather formal invitation to a meal, a feast, or a stay, and the word never refers to an invitation to join a political movement or the like.</p>
<p>3. Pìn 聘 refers to a strictly formal diplomatic invitation.</p>
<p>4. Qǐng 請 comes to refer to a general social invitation by SHIJI times, but the word can also refer more generally to an invitation to join any activity or movement.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>邀請 is the current modern word referring (verbally or nominally) to an invitation.</p>
<p>請 is a current informal way of referring (always verbally) to an invitation.</p>
<p>約請 focusses on the need for agreement on the part of the invitee.</p>
<p>敦請 refers to a cordial invitation of a rather formal kind.</p>
<p>邀約 refers in a somewhat literary way to an invitation by mutual agreement.</p>
<p>特約 refers to a special invitation.</p>
<p>招要 refers in a very literary almost periphrastic way to a formal invitation.</p>
<p>三顧茅廬 refers proverbially and in a highly literary mode to an invitation to take up an honourable appointment.</p>
<p>Compare also the monosyllabic literary terms:</p>
<p>邀</p>
<p>約</p>
<p>first rough draft to identify synonym group members for future analysis 18.11.2003. CH</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c1d0456b-e8a5-4e51-bb67-dee740ea13ae">FEAST</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-8776e03b-d58b-43cd-b694-22237290bbeb">REQUEST</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2c59ecb-bbff-4004-8e45-5fc7f92ed0da">Mel'cuk 1984</ref>
<title>Tolkovo-kombinatornyj slovar' sovremmenogo russkogo jazyka. Explanatory Combinatorial Dictionary of Modern Russian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">659</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-e65dd863-ccd1-4064-8fac-710a1be058a0">Mel'cuk I</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire explicatif et combinatoire du francais contemporain, vol. I</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">111</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">79B</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">















    </div>
</div>