<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-16de396a-482f-44f4-bc0a-dd073c887f9b">
<head>KILL</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">殺</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">殺</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>VOLUNTARILY CAUSE TO DIE.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The overwhelmingly dominant term referring to any form of taking the life of anything is shā 殺.</p>
<p>2. Some words specify the range of objects murdered: Thus shì 弒 refers to the killing of a reigning ruler, zhū 誅 and yí 夷 refer to the killing of a convicted criminal; zǎi 宰 and tú3 屠 refer primarily to the slaughtering of animals for the purpose of food production.</p>
<p>3. Some words specify the number of objects killed: yí 夷, zú 族, jiān 殲 tú 屠 (when applied to humans) refer to the killing of groups of people. See PUNISHMENT. The other words refer normally to the killing of one person or a specified set of several persons.</p>
<p>4. Some words specify modes of killing: cì 刺 is to murder by stabbing with a pointed object, typically a dagger; liè 裂 and jiě 解 refer to dismembering by a wide variety of methods; zhèn 鴆 refers to poisoning; jǐng 剄 refers to cutting the throat; xī 腊 refers to killing followed by making a person into minced meat; rèn 刃 is to kill with a sword; jiǎo 絞 and yì 縊 refer to strangulation, è4 mèi 扼昧 and refer to strangulation; è 餓 can refer to starving someone to death. For a more detailed account of the varieties of death penalties in ancient China see PUNISHMENT.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>殺</p>
<p>害死</p>
<p>殺死</p>
<p>誤殺</p>
<p>結果</p>
<p>害</p>
<p>殺害</p>
<p>要命</p>
<p>扼殺</p>
<p>幹掉</p>
<p>格斃</p>
<p>格殺 refers to killing someone in open combat.</p>
<p>撂倒</p>
<p>活活打死</p>
<p>first rough draft to identify synonym group members for future analysis 18.11.2003. CH</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-09d4fd56-a4a8-4b40-91a5-5f7ffe59e32e">HUNT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ec275871-9869-48f3-890b-a7dceadab50d">STRANGLE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-1f8c72e2-a5ea-47a4-af5e-7883986f8303">EXECUTE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b9645fd1-f199-4879-9b96-f638a137c54f">MURDER</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-dd9aeb4f-a422-431e-9925-807ba494d82e">SUICIDE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-2d18de2c-a840-4747-84dd-8f8d08b67620">PUNISH</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9f80ea87-ad33-4605-bcc0-faf2b536f92a">CAUSE TO</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">4.76</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>KILL</p>
<p>interficere are the most general expressions for putting some living being to death for any reason and under any circumstances.</p>
<p>perimere is an old-fashioned precious word synonymous otherwise with interficere.</p>
<p>interimere refers to murder in private contexts to remove someone.</p>
<p>necare refers to killing someone cruelly as an unjust act of murder.</p>
<p>occidere refers to killing by cutting someone down, especially by a soldier in open battle.</p>
<p>iugulare refers to killing by cutting the throat or neck, or by a skilfuly-direct4ed thrust to the collar-bone, which is especially the biusiness of the bandit.</p>
<p>obtruncare refers to the reckless butchering and cutting into pieces.</p>
<p>trucidare refers to slaughtering a living being as one might a cow.</p>
<p>percutere refers to taking someone's life as a mere mechanical act in the manner of an executioner of a death sentence.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc235203-2ca8-4006-a7f5-c3246090e146">DUFOUR 1910</ref>
<title>Traite elementaire des synonymes grecques</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">184</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">164</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">19</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-05ed74f0-1015-4215-90be-a8a88a450962">MENGZI TONGYI 2002</ref>
<title>“孟子”同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">255</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-3cf76dec-e8bc-4732-bde9-e5ca60e7fb1a">SCHMIDT 1889</ref>
<title>Handbuch der lateinischen und griechischen Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">76</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.302</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">



































































    </div>
</div>