<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-fdd2e445-4a61-4cf3-bfd1-158726b36de6">
<head>NONSENSE</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">廢話</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>CONFUSED SPEECH which LACKS MEANING.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>The concept of nonsense is not prominent in ancient Chinese discourse.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>胡說 is the current modern Chinese verb for talking nonsense.</p>
<p>放屁 (informal) is a highly colloquial word referring to talking nonsense.</p>
<p>胡扯 is a highly colloquial modern Chinese word for nonsense.</p>
<p>嚼舌 focusses in a colloquial way on inarticulateness as the cause for the production of nonsense.</p>
<p>瞎扯 is colloquial and intensitive.</p>
<p>瞎說 is a more literary common word for talking nonsense or nominally nonsense.</p>
<p>亂說 focusses on the intellectually chaotic nature of nonsense.</p>
<p>亂道 (lit) refers to confused discourse in a rather formal way.</p>
<p>瞎謅 (lit, rare) refers to un-thought-through wild talk in a dignified way.</p>
<p>嚼蛆 jiáoqū refers to talking nonsense.</p>
<p>咧咧 (coll) refers to meaningless blabbering.</p>
<p>亂彈琴 "strum the lute chaotically" is a figurative literary way of referring to talking nonsense.</p>
<p>胡言亂語 (prov) refers in a hyperbolic literary way to the talking of nonsense.</p>
<p>胡說八道 (prov) is a highly colloquial idiomatic way of referring to the talking of nonsense.</p>
<p>妄言妄語 (prov) is a formal and still way of referring to the talking of nonsense.</p>
<p>說夢話 "talk dream talk" is a figurative way of referring to the talking of nonsense.</p>
<p>鬼話連篇 (prov) focusses on the lengthiness of the onsense.</p>
<p>囈語連天 (prov, obs) refers in a recondite way to the talking of nonsense.</p>
<p>言不及義 (prov) focusses on the failure of nonsense to articulate even wrong meaning.</p>
<p>信口開河 (prov) focusses on the irresponsibility of talk and is marginal in the group.</p>
<p>信口雌黃 (prov) focusses on the irresponsibility of talk and is marginal in the group.</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ce3105d5-fa21-46b9-bef5-e77386a58891">FART</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-07855030-3463-472d-bd01-1c7ceebbfb3d">SPEAK</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-c6a5120d-a888-44ce-b517-b0cbba82518a">CASSIN 2004</ref>
<title>Vocabulaire européen des philosophies. Dictionnaire des intraduisibles</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">859</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4acb4e0c-daab-4369-9991-912c64da1ee6">RITTER 1971-2007</ref>
<title>Historisches Woerterbuch der Philosophie</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">11.270</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>UNSINN</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">


    </div>
</div>