<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-06b1cfae-3bed-4939-9de0-0afd5dc5f2a4">
<head>POND</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>POOL</item>
<item>WATERHOLE</item>
<item>LAKE</item>
<item>TARN</item>
<item>RESERVOIR</item>
<item>SLOUGH</item>
<item>BEAVER POND</item>
<item>LAGOON</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">池塘</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>SMALL LAKE PRODUCED by HUMANS.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The most common word for an artificial lake of any kind is chí 池, and this word typically refers to a meandering lake, sometimes close in shape to a moat, particularly round elevated terraces and the like, around gardens and orchards, but also as part of palaces.</p>
<p>2. Zhǎo 沼 is an elevated word referring to elaborate artificial lakes in or near palaces and the like, although the word can also come to refer more generally to natural lakes and marshlands.</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>GEOGRAPHY 17.</p>
<p>池，蓄水池，通稱，有娛樂、水產養殖等多種用途。</p>
<p>瀦，利用低窪地構築堤壩、用來灌溉的蓄水池，南方用語。</p>
<p>陂，利用窪地、坡谷障圍而成的大水池，主要用於灌田。</p>
<p>塘，人工築堤而成的方形水池。</p>
<p>湖，大於陂的人工水庫，用於灌溉，南方用語。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>池塘</p>
<p>池沼</p>
<p>池子</p>
<p>池</p>
<p>塘</p>
<p>玉池</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-eb2179a7-57c0-4003-b071-9155bfd6dc29">PUDDLE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-dd7585ff-f781-43d6-8bd4-d43b15415838">SEA</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-87e6da35-ec45-4ace-b5d3-b7cf67a82118">LAKE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d9f914e1-ebc9-4ba0-85f5-f2bdd943ed24">FINSTERBUSCH 1966</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">241</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Teich:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dcdec461-c248-4809-a141-385e6610d74c">FINSTERBUSCH 2000</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">808</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Teich;  Lotosteich</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b233856d-aa73-4285-ba03-e61399e6537b">LEIBNIZ 1704</ref>
<title>Table de definitions, pp. 437-</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">442</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">577</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>池，沼</p>
<p>1. WL maintain that in the meaning "pond, pool" the words are completely synonymous.  This is certainly not so.  Zha3o 沼 is a dignified word belonging to an elevated style, hence li2ng zha3o 靈沼 and never li2ng chi2 靈池.  Zha3o 沼 is often deep and round, with fish typically diving deep into it, whereas chi2 池 can be elongated and curved, as in qu3 chi2 曲池 "winding lakes". The association of zha3o 沼 is with palaces and the like, that of chi2 池 is with platforms and orchards, gardens, orchards.  There is no 園沼 nor is there a pu3 zha3o 圃沼.  These are chi2 池. Lakes hu2 湖 are associated with chi2 池 "ponds" as sources for food, never zha3o 沼, which are too elevated to be used for such mundane purposes. </p>
<p>YTL 04.17.05; Wang 1992: 153; Wang 1995: 220; Lu: 235; tr. Gale 1931: 107;</p>
<p>食湖池， Indeed with him who feeds on the Nation掇 lakes and pools</p>
<p>Chi2 池 are often (though by no means always) mundane things, zha3o 沼 never are.  Thus we always have the proverbial jiu3 chi2 酒池 and no jiu3 zha3o 酒沼.  A king might go out to shoot birds at a chi2 池 "meandering lake" somewhere, but the zha3o 沼 tend to be near or within the confines of palaces and the like:</p>
<p>HSWZ 09.10.01; tr. Hightower 1951, p.298f</p>
<p>齊景公出弋昭華之池， Duke Ching of Ch剫 went on a shooting expedition to the lake at Chao-hua.</p>
<p>The constant reference to ga1o ta2i she1n chi2 高臺深池 suggests that the chi2 池 were those places where the earth for the platforms was taken, just as in the case of city walls.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">








    </div>
</div>