<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-98abac13-a01c-4d97-a840-00b8498b74ac">
<head>PURSUE</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>FOLLOW</item>
<item>RUN AFTER</item>
<item>CHASE</item>
<item>HUNT</item>
<item>STALK</item>
<item>TRACK</item>
<item>TRAIL</item>
<item>SHADOW</item>
<item>HOUND</item>
<item>COURSE</item>
<item>INFORMAL TAIL</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">追趕</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">逐</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>FOLLOW so as to TRY to REACH OR CATCH.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current general word for pursuing something or going after something in a hostile way, driving what is pursued before one, competing with it for speed, is zhú 逐 and the word can only very occasionally refer to abstract pursuits like that of wisdom, as in the venatio sapientiae of Nicolas Cusanus. It is significant that the word currently means "to expel", where expelling and chasing are not always easy to distinguish.</p>
<p>2. Zhuī 追 refers to the attempt of catching up with anything, characteristically a kòu 寇 "enemy" or thief (who may not know he is being pursued) but without any attending notion that what is being caught up with is NECESSARILY trying to escape or to make great speed, and the word is regularly used in figurative derived meanings "to seek", as in zhuī lì 追利 "chasing after profit".</p>
<p>3. Suǒ 索 emphasises the seeking aspect in the pursuit of something or someone.</p>
<p>4. Jí 及 and the rarer dài 逮 refer to a successful pursuit. See CATCH UP</p>
<p>5. Qū 驅 suggests a hot and fast pursuit typically uncrowned by success.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>追趕</p>
<p>追逐</p>
<p>追逼</p>
<p>尾追</p>
<p>追</p>
<p>趕</p>
<p>攆</p>
<p>你追我趕</p>
<p>迎頭趕上</p>
<p>奮起直追</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9097ca31-10f7-4435-b048-8d1668b1460a">AVOID</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c43f4c45-617b-4e09-8cb1-17917eb759fb">FOLLOW</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">10.53</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">180</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-05ed74f0-1015-4215-90be-a8a88a450962">MENGZI TONGYI 2002</ref>
<title>“孟子”同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">312</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1432</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>追，逐</p>
<p>1. WL claims that at the earliest stage zhu2 逐 refers to the pursuit of wild beasts.  The reference, here, should be specifically to Jiaguwen, becasuse the one occurrence in the old part of SHU refers to human objects, and the word does not come in SHI.  Moreover, in ZUO, what is pursued by way of animals is very little indeed: fish, dogs and the like, and very little of the bovines, boar, tigers and the like the prevail throughout Jiaguwen.  This kind of discontinuity of usage is quite interesting.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">319</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">


















    </div>
</div>