<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-a0565ad5-b3d5-4bcf-97f7-90ae00999356">
<head>REPORT</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>TELL</item>
<item>ANNOUNCE</item>
<item>DESCRIBE</item>
<item>GIVE AN ACCOUNT OF</item>
<item>DETAIL</item>
<item>OUTLINE</item>
<item>COMMUNICATE</item>
<item>DIVULGE</item>
<item>DISCLOSE</item>
<item>REVEAL</item>
<item>MAKE PUBLIC</item>
<item>PUBLISH</item>
<item>BROADCAST</item>
<item>PROCLAIM</item>
<item>PUBLICIZE</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">報告</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">告</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>ADDRESS others so as to CAUSE them to BECOME AWARE of a FACT.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current word for any report or the passing on of any information is gào 告. But see also ADDRESS.</p>
<p>2. Yù 語 is a common word referring to informal oral notification or instruction.</p>
<p>3. Bào 報 and the rarer fù 復 refer to an oral report to the authorities as required by these authorities.</p>
<p>4. Yè 謁 refers to the transmitting of a message, typically by the ancient Chinese equivalent of a butler.</p>
<p>5. Wén 聞 refers to making something known to a superior or to the public at large.</p>
<p>6. Fěng 諷 refers to an informal (often subtly disguised) personal opinion passed on to superiors.</p>
<p>7. Bái 白 refers to a personal report, often urgent, and typically by an inferior to a superior, and when used among equals it is a polite form of self-deprecation.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria" resp="#CH" modified="2022-10-26T02:23:09.533+09:00">
            <p>告訴 is the current colourless general word for passing on information.</p>
            <p>告知 is a more old-fashioned way of letting someone know something.</p>
            <p>報告 is the current modern word for making a report.</p>
            <p>反映 is the current word for reporting something (e.g. public views) by way of publication.</p>
            <p>回報 / 匯報 / 彙報 is a more formal current word for a report.</p>
            <p>上告 focusses on the upward-directedness of a report, typically made on one's own initiative.</p>
            <p>上報 focusses on the upward-directedness of a report, typically made by orders of higher authorities.</p>
            <p>呈報 refers to a formal, required report to the authorities.</p>
            <p>層報 is a technical term referring to a formal required report submitted to one level above one's own.</p>
            <p>申報 refers to a report one makes on one's own initiative to higher authorities of some sort.</p>
            <p>稟報 (lit) refers in an elevated manner to a report made to high authorities.</p>
            <p>密報 refers to a secret report.</p>
            <p>呈文 (lit, obs) refers to a formal report to the authorities.</p>
            <p>呈兒 (coll, obs) refers to a formal report to the authorities.</p>
            <p>呈子 (lit, obs) refers to a formal report to the authorities.</p>
            <p>簽呈 (lit, obs) refers to a formal report to the authorities.</p>
            <p>講述</p>
            <p>談論</p>
            <p>講解</p>
            <p>通風報信 refers pejoratively to the informing authorities etc. on someone.</p>
            <p>&lt;div&gt;rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;GREEK KEYWORDS&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;αγγελία ας, Ion. άγγελίη ης/ [άγγελος] | Some instances&lt;br&gt;of Ion. άγγελίης and άγγελίην in IL may also be taken as&lt;br&gt;nom. and acc. masc.sb. messenger. |&lt;br&gt;1 message, announcement, news Hom. Hes. Thgn. Pi. B.&lt;br&gt;Hdt. +; (phr.) άγγελίην έλθόντα having come with a message&lt;br&gt;(or as a messenger) IL&lt;br&gt;2 (personif., as daughter of Hermes) Angelia Pi.&lt;br&gt;3 command, order Pi. Hdt.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;αγγέλλω vb. [άγγελος] | fut. άγγελώ, Ion. άγγελέω | aor.&lt;br&gt;ήγγειλα | pf. ήγγελκα || pass.: aor. ήγγέλθην, aor.2 ήγγέλην&lt;br&gt;(Plu.) | pf. ήγγελμαι |&lt;br&gt;1 act as a messenger, carry a message (sts. w.dat. to&lt;br&gt;someone) Hom. + —w.inf. or acc. + inf. to do sthg. or that&lt;br&gt;someone shd. do sthg. Hom. E. Th.; (fig., of a beacon) A.&lt;br&gt;2 make a report or an announcement Pi. S. Th. +&lt;br&gt;3 report, announce (sts. w.dat. or prep.phr. to someone)&lt;br&gt;—sthg. Hom. + —w.compl.cl. that sthg. is the case IL Hdt. S.&lt;br&gt;E. Th. + —W.ACC. + INF. Th. Ar. Plu. —W.INDIR.Q. what is the&lt;br&gt;case Ar. PL&lt;br&gt;4 || pass, (of an event or circumstance) be reported E. Th. Ar.&lt;br&gt;X. Plu. —w.inf. as taking place or as having been such and&lt;br&gt;such E. PL; (of a city) —as being betrayed Th.; (of ships)&lt;br&gt;—w.ptcpl. as doing sthg. Th. || impers.pass. it is reported&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Th. —w.compl.cl. that sthg. is the case Hdt. S. E. Th. +&lt;br&gt;—W.ACC. + INF. E. Th. Plu. II neut.pl.pass.ptcpl.SB. (pres.,&lt;br&gt;aor., pf.) news or reports A. Hdt. Th. +&lt;br&gt;5 give news of —an absent person Od.; report —a person (i.e.&lt;br&gt;their name, w.dat. to someone) Antipho Pl. —(w.predic.adj.&lt;br&gt;as being such and such) E. — (w.ptcpl. or ως + ptcpl. as&lt;br&gt;doing or having done sthg.) S. E. Plu. || mid. declare oneself&lt;br&gt;—w.inf. to be such and such S. || pass, (of a person) be&lt;br&gt;reported -w.PREDic.ADJ. as being such and such E.&lt;br&gt;—w.ptcpl. as doing or having done sthg. E. Th. Plu. —as&lt;br&gt;being alive or dead S. X. Is. D. Plu. —w.inf. to be doing sthg.&lt;br&gt;Pl. X. Plu.&lt;br&gt;6 (of the morning star) announce the arrival of, herald&lt;br&gt;—the light of dawn Od.&lt;br&gt;7 (fig., of clothes) announce —their wearer (w.predic.adj.&lt;br&gt;as being of a certain nationality) E.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-e0e5decd-d012-4a63-bcc6-6d669fa2c85e">PUBLICISE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-1bebc2e6-a495-453e-aa66-4919c1ddaf15">PREDICT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-4cf207dc-f42a-417e-b1d5-5823f4c3f5b2">STORY</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d2d8dc-853b-49a0-9709-80c80c7845e1">ANNUNCIATION</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ffe85849-0547-451b-8952-d32067596c12">ADDRESS</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b1c8c39d-b2b9-4994-80ba-33686a5c1fe8">APRESJAN 2004</ref>
<title>Novyj objasnitel'nyj Slovar' Sinonimov Russkogo Jazyka</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1089</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc235203-2ca8-4006-a7f5-c3246090e146">DUFOUR 1910</ref>
<title>Traite elementaire des synonymes grecques</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">134</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">222</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">45</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">755</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1279</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>告，誥，詔</p>
<p>1. Ga4o 告 is not just to inform and to warn, it also has important generalised uses "to address", occasionally even with what is a question.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b425a52b-7c3a-4b26-a4a5-8c5a55eaf19b">GRACE ZHANG 2010</ref>
<title>Using Chinese Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">146</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-e8e00c8c-6f7d-429d-82a5-84721abe7cc7">T.W.HARBSMEIER 2004</ref>
<title>A New Dictionary of Classical Greek Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no. 4</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">76B</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">




































    </div>
</div>