<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-2c1b9e8c-9b60-47a2-bd66-ab3e56cf5c0f">
<head>RIBBON</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>STRIP</item>
<item>TAPE</item>
<item>BAND</item>
<item>CORD</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">絲帶</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>INTENSELY SMALL LONG AND NARROW CLOTH.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. Probably most general word for a ribbon is zǔ 組 and it usually refers to the wide and thin ribbon made of silk. Its shape, size and functions are very variable. The word can thus refer to a belt ribbon, strings for use with hats, string used to tie an armour etc.</p>
<p>2. Xún 紃 refers to the round plaited ribbon which can be used in various ways (on shoes for instance):</p>
<p>3. Tāo 絛 is a small plaited ribbon which can be used in various ways (to make a shoes lace for instance) similar to xún 紃. The two perhaps differs by value???.</p>
<p>4. Shòu 綬 refers to the ribbon which was originally used to tie jade pendants to the waistband; in the Han dynasty it was used for tying the seal. In Han times, shòu 綬 was an important marker of the status of its holder, and length and colour of the ribbon varied according to it.</p>
<p>5. Lún 綸 in Han times refers to the green/blue silk ribbon used by minor officials to tie the seal to the waistband.</p>
<p>6. Yīng 纓 refers specifically to one of two ribbons used to keep hat straight. The word also refers to the colour ribbon worn by a woman when having reached an age for marriage; it was also used for tying fragrant things.</p>
<p>7. Hóng 紘 refers to the ribbon used to keep hat; in this case only one ribbon is used.</p>
<p>8. Yīng ruí 纓 (written like 10.) refers to the ribbon used to keep a hat.</p>
<p>9. Màn hú 縵胡 refers to the ribbon used to keep a hat which was worn by warriors, and was made of plaint undecorated silk.</p>
<p>10. Ruí (written like 竹 above and down 豕 with 生 ) refers to the part of the hat ribbon which is hanging down.</p>
<p>11. Qí 綦 refers to the small ribbon which can be used on shoes.</p>
<p>12. Zuǎn (written like 算 above and 系 below) refers in SHUOWEN to the red ribbon.</p>
<p>13. Xǐ 縰 refers to a ribbon used to tie up hair.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>緞帶</p>
<p>絲帶</p>
<p>綬帶</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-2d174c46-a88e-4999-b48b-73e2bc3fa0fe">BELT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-8af64033-a8a3-4405-b563-c0054ea51288">CLOTH</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="words">

















    </div>
</div>