<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-56391328-912b-4408-91c8-ed8d3f602e6c">
<head>ROOF</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">屋頂</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>MOST UPWARD PART of a BUILDING which PROTECTS that BUILDING AGAINST RAIN.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The earliest general word for the roof is wū 屋, which occurs in this meaning in SHIJING, ZUO, and CHUCI. The term can refer both to the roof of aristocratic buildings which was since the early Western Zhou period covered with tiles, or to the thatched roof of ordinary dwellings. Evidence for the shape of the roof in the Zhou period is of course scarce, we can recognize it only from several bronze vessels in the shape of the building and from pictorial presentations on late Chunqiu and early Warring States bronzes. Much better evidence is from the Han. It can be seen that by Han times basic types of Chinese roof had already developed; the most common among them was a saddle-like roof.</p>
<p>2. Dòng 棟 refers to the ridge-pole of the roof, oriented usually in the east-western direction. It is also general term for the east-western beams in a roof construction.</p>
<p>3. Jí 极 is another term for the ridge-pole used in pre-Qin times; it does not generally refer to the east-southern beams:</p>
<p>4. Fú 桴 refers to the east-western beam which is second when counted from the ridge-pole: [HUANG 1995: 1044 - 1045]</p>
<p>5. Méi 楣 is another term for fú 桴. Later, the word began to be used for the horizontal beam above the door. [HUANG 1995: 1044 - 1045]</p>
<p>6. Guǐ 庪 refers to the third east-western beam. [HUANG 1995: 1045]</p>
<p>7. Yǐn (written like 隱 but with 木 radical) and fén 棼 both refer to the highest east-western ridge-pole of the double-roof. [HUANG 1995: 1045]</p>
<p>8. (I did not find the character) can generally refer to the east-western beams. [HUANG 1995: 1045 - 1046]</p>
<p>9. Méng 甍 refers to the east-western ridge-pole, but also to the eaves of the roof. [HANYU DACIDIAN: vol. 5, pp. 294]</p>
<p>10. Lǔ (written 木 Lu Buwei de lu) refers to the beam supporting the rafters of the roof. [HANYU DACIDIAN: vol. 4, pp. 973]</p>
<p>11. Liù 霤 refers in LIJI and ZUOZHUAN to the eaves of the houses. [HANYU DACIDIAN: vol. 11, pp. 724 - 725]</p>
<p>12. Chuán 椽 refers to the rafters supporting the tiles; these were usually made of wood, but sometimes also of bamboo, and were usually laid on the beams in one layer. [HUANG 1995: 1054 - 1055]</p>
<p>13. Jué 桷 is another word for the rafters. It can refer to the rafters generally, but also specifically to the rafters with the square or edged section. [HUANG 1995: 1055]</p>
<p>14. Cuī 榱 refers to the large rafters which can be decorated with jade pieces hanged down. [HUANG 1995: 1055]</p>
<p>[15. Lǎo 橑 refers to the rafters of the double roof: HUANG 1995: 1056] [JM]</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>屋頂</p>
<p>頂</p>
<p>There must be more words, but I have not been able to find them easily.</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-5ee75842-ac52-4055-9d15-ecec19fa2ac1">BALDACHIN</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="mereonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c15965ad-e3f2-4fc7-a812-2269b338df9b">EAVES</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-dd0c968f-64b3-44cb-aeb8-ffd6309b4699">GARGOYLE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-655477fe-20d2-4632-84ba-b7407a50786b">RAFTER</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-fb6d18a8-a42b-4cc9-bfbf-7b0597a2b084">N/A</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">7.28</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d9f914e1-ebc9-4ba0-85f5-f2bdd943ed24">FINSTERBUSCH 1966</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">207</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Dach:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dcdec461-c248-4809-a141-385e6610d74c">FINSTERBUSCH 2000</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">783</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Dach:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">














    </div>
</div>