<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-51f3e644-6a3d-484b-b92e-db27d286e973">
<head>SCALES</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">秤</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>TOOL USED FOR WEIGHING THINGS.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. General word for scales is chèng 秤 / 稱, which occurs already in LSCQ. It refers to the whole implement, i.e. both to the weighing rod and the weight. Today, typical Chinese lever scales consists of the weighing rod and the weight suspended from it. The thing to be weighed is put on the bowl hanged down from the one end of the weighing beam, and its weight is determined by moving the weight till balance between the weight and weighed thing is reached. It seems that this type of scales came to be used only in Tang times. Scales known from the Warring States period consists of the wooden stick with two small bronze bowls suspended from its both sides; the things to be weighed were put on one bowl and weights on the other.</p>
<p>2. Héng 衡 refers to the whole of the weighing contraption, the scales, but the term does not include a weight.</p>
<p>3. Quán 權 refers to the weight. Weights known from the Warring States period are usually made of bronze. According to the late Warring States and Han texts, they were divided into five categories - zhū 銖, liǎng 兩, jīn 斤, jūn 鈞, and shí 石 - but it should be noted that situation was more complicated, and in Warring States times weights differred from state to state.</p>
<p>4. Chuí 錘 refers to the weight. According to FANG YAN, in Han times the word was used in the area of ancient states of Lu and Song; later it came to be used as general word for the weight.</p>
<p>5. Quán 銓, when used in the meaning "scales" is synonymous with chèng 秤, but the word is rare.</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>TRADE 21.</p>
<p>衡，天平，特指天平的衡杆；後泛指桿秤的秤桿。</p>
<p>稱，桿秤，東漢末出現。</p>
<p>權，上古秦漢指天平稱的砝碼；桿秤出現後，也指秤砣。</p>
<p>錘，桿秤的秤砣。</p>
<p>銓，上古時衡器總稱，泛指用來稱物重量的器具，多用於書面語。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>秤</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b3320f73-ed89-40c6-b631-8e13ff8f33eb">WEIGHT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-403b2f16-b0b3-487b-905b-dd6a0a609f57">TOOL</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">284</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1523</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>銓，稱</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">533</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>權，衡</p>
<p>1. The difference between qua2n 權 "weights" and he2ng 衡 "scales as such (without weights)". WL defines qua2n 權 as "秤（秤錘）", and this is confusing on the very core of the distinction, because che4ng 秤 does refer to the whole of the weighing contraption including the weights, not only the weights themselves, the 秤錘.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ceec1ff7-e9e2-4e81-8c76-a29b231e6074">WU SANXING 2008</ref>
<title>中國文化背景八千詞 Zhongguo wenhua beijing ba qian ci</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">361</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">






    </div>
</div>