<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-59d560a0-7465-4598-8d03-b00e37f229c2">
<head>SEAL</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>EMBLEM</item>
<item>SYMBOL</item>
<item>INSIGNIA</item>
<item>DEVICE</item>
<item>BADGE</item>
<item>CREST</item>
<item>COAT OF ARMS</item>
<item>MARK</item>
<item>MONOGRAM</item>
<item>STAMP</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">圖章</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>SYMBOL USED TO PROVE OFFICIAL AUTHORITY of a DOCUMENT by PRODUCING a MARK on that DOCUMENT.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. General word for the seal was originally xǐ 璽, and this could refer to the seals used both by officials and commoners, particularly traders. Originally, seals perhaps served mainly to the exchange of goods in Warring States times, but in the same period they came to be used by officials as a symbol of administrative authority. Official documents had to be all sealed with a piece of mud adhered on the cord tying up the document and impressed with an official seal. In the Han period, the word xǐ 璽 came to refer to the seals used by an Emperor and members of his family; these were usually made of jade.</p>
<p>2. Yìn 印 refers to the seals used by officials as a symbol of authority and also status in the bureaucratic hierarchy. The word began to be used in the Warring States period. Seals were worn tied to the waist (perhaps in a small sack; but there are also sealing fingerrings known from the Han period), were mostly of square shape, and material of which they were made expressed status of their holders. According to Han texts, the highest officials and aristocracy had golden seals, the lower silver, and minor officials had seals made of bronze.</p>
<p>3. Zhāng 章 is the word for the official seal which was used since Han times onwards.</p>
<p>4. Fēng ní 封泥 refers to the the piece of mud adhered on a document and impressed with a seal. The mud used for this purpose was worn in special tubes.</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>GOVERNMENT/LAW 8.</p>
<p>璽，先秦尊卑通用。秦始皇之後，專指皇帝之印，玉製。至漢代，皇后、諸侯王之印也可稱璽。唐代武後改 “ 璽 ” 為 “ 寶 ” ，唐玄宗以後，皇帝用印名 “ 寶 ” 漸成定製。</p>
<p>章，吏秩二千石以上的五字官印，始於漢武帝時，隋唐以後漸廢。</p>
<p>印，漢武帝太初元年至隋唐，專指吏秩千石以下至四百石者所用官印；也泛稱私人印章。</p>
<p>記，唐代起可作官印，五代時多指高官之印，宋以後指下級官吏印。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>圖章</p>
<p>印章</p>
<p>戳兒</p>
<p>戳記</p>
<p>手戳</p>
<p>圖書</p>
<p>圖記</p>
<p>鈐記 (obs) refers to a traditional official seal.</p>
<p>印信</p>
<p>章</p>
<p>印</p>
<p>篆</p>
<p>璽</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-43ed7810-ef10-416c-8044-df9eade18fa0">SYMBOL</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dcdec461-c248-4809-a141-385e6610d74c">FINSTERBUSCH 2000</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">803</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Siegel:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">78</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">4.603</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">140/2</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">







    </div>
</div>