<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-f28f17dd-220d-4410-813a-811361c4a269">
<head>SLANDER</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>DEFAMATION (OF CHARACTER)</item>
<item>CHARACTER ASSASSINATION</item>
<item>CALUMNY</item>
<item>LIBEL</item>
<item>SCANDALMONGERING</item>
<item>MALICIOUS GOSSIP</item>
<item>DISPARAGEMENT</item>
<item>DENIGRATION</item>
<item>ASPERSIONS</item>
<item>VILIFICATION</item>
<item>TRADUCEMENT</item>
<item>OBLOQUY</item>
<item>LIE</item>
<item>SLUR</item>
<item>SMEAR</item>
<item>FALSE ACCUSATION</item>
<item>INFORMAL MUDSLINGING</item>
<item>BAD-MOUTHING</item>
<item>ARCHAIC CONTUMELY</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">毀謗</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">毀</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>CRITICISE INTENSELY, LACKING APPROPRIATE REASONS, NOT ADDRESSING the HUMAN BLAMED.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The standard current word for speaking ill of a person is huǐ 毀 (ant. yù 譽 "praise"), and the slander involved can be of all kinds.</p>
<p>2. Chán 讒 (ant. zàn 贊 "praise justly") refers to popular slander, sometimes by persons without significant political influence.</p>
<p>3. Bàng 謗 "vilify a person" (ant. chēng 稱 "praise") refers to public serious criticism, sometimes coming close to public abuse; increasingly, the word tended to refer to unjustified such accusations, i.e. slander, but the word is also used for justified serious criticism in public.</p>
<p>4. Fěi 誹 (ant. yáng 揚 "spread good reports about") refers to critical comments on a person, and these may come from persons of influence or from the common people. See CRITICISE</p>
<p>5. Zèn 譖 (ant. zhāng 彰 "be full of public praise for") refers specifically to a secret malicious whispering campaign.</p>
<p>6. Jī 譏 refers to subtle satirical slander.</p>
<p>7. Wū 誣 (ant. zàn 贊 "praise justly") refers specifically to unjustified slander.</p>
<p>8. Shàn 訕 (ant. sòng 頌 "sing the praises of") adds an element of ridicule to that of speaking ill of a person.</p>
<p>9. Wù 惡 (ant. měi 美 "speak well of") can be used to focus on maligning someone to his superiors.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>說壞話 "speak bad speech" is a very informal colloquial way of referring to slander.</p>
<p>誣蔑 focusses on the unwarranted nature of the slander.</p>
<p>污蔑 focusses on the dirtiness of the slanderous remarks.</p>
<p>誣賴 focusses on the untruthfulness of the incriminations.</p>
<p>誣陷 focusses on the aspect of fraudulent entrapping of the object of slander.</p>
<p>詆毀 focusses on the malicious destructiveness in slander.</p>
<p>醜詆 focusses on the malicious uglification in slander.</p>
<p>誹謗 focusses on the unwarranted behind-the-back criticism in slander.</p>
<p>毀謗 (lit) focusses on the destructive behind-the-back criticism in libelous slander.</p>
<p>中傷 (lit) focusses on the hurtfulness of sllander.</p>
<p>非議 (lit) refers to derogatory remarks in the context of political or public debate.</p>
<p>訾議 (lit) refers to malicious unwarranted attack in public debate.</p>
<p>造謠 focusses on the function of slander as creating malicious rumours.</p>
<p>謠諑 (lit) refers to slanderous rumours.</p>
<p>讒害 refers to slander as a way of harming a person.</p>
<p>讒謗 (lit) is a literary word referring to behind-the-back slander.</p>
<p>醜化 "uglify" refers to extreme defamation and vilification.</p>
<p>抹黑 "blacken" refers figuratively to defamation.</p>
<p>搞臭 "make stink" refers figuratively to maligning someone.</p>
<p>含血噴人 (prov) refers in a hyperbolic way to malicious slanderous accusations.</p>
<p>血口噴人 (prov) refers in a hyperbolic way to malicious slanderous accusations.</p>
<p>造謠中傷 (prov) refers to the creation of hurtful slanderous rumours.</p>
<p>惡語中傷 (prov) focusses on the the use of vicious language in the creation of hurtful slander.</p>
<p>讒 (cl)</p>
<p>詆 (cl)</p>
<p>謗 (cl)</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-876bb1f3-4a64-44d4-a352-38216cb8f038">ACCUSE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-55128168-da10-4764-be8d-400c8756d7a1">CRITICISE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b8242ce-9fc6-4b7b-bd52-14c744308409">COMENIUS 1665</ref>
<title>De Rerum Humanarum Emendatione</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">477</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>CALUMNIA malitiose de aliquo sparsus sermo, seu, intentamentum alicui falsum crimen, ad involvendum eum apud alios odio comparatum.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc235203-2ca8-4006-a7f5-c3246090e146">DUFOUR 1910</ref>
<title>Traite elementaire des synonymes grecques</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc235203-2ca8-4006-a7f5-c3246090e146">DUFOUR 1910</ref>
<title>Traite elementaire des synonymes grecques</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">113</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">191</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>CALUMNIA</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>DETRACTIO</p>
<p>OBTRECTATIO</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-233f2660-a4e2-4ab6-8d05-41cd958ac07a">THEOPHRASTUS 1960</ref>
<title>Theophrast, Charaktere</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no. 28</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1290</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>誹，謗，譏</p>
<p>1. WL claims that ba4ng 謗 and fe3i 誹are both used for justified criticism in early texts, and that from Han times onwards the words tend to be used less and less for criticism and more and more for unwarranted criticism or slander.  In fact, fe3i ba4ng 誹謗 is a current word for slander, but the two words differ considerably. Fe3i 誹 refers to censure or criticism and has yu4 譽 "give praise to" as a very high frequency  regular antonym.  Ba4ng 謗 never has an antonym yu4 譽, and the word does very often refer to unwarranted slander and vilification rather than criticism. Thus fe3i 誹 "popular censure, criticism" is significantly absent in CC, where ba4ng 謗 "malicious slander" is ubiquitous.  I have not found a single instance where fe3i 誹 refers unambiguously to malicious slander.</p>
<p>2. Moreover, WL claims that ba4ng 謗 is public whereas fe3i 誹 is popular but private and mumbling. The evidence for this is unclear.  The contrast between ba4ng 謗 involving malice and fe3i 誹 focussing primarily on disapproval fe1i 非 as such is much clearer.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.230.189</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>DIFFAMATOIRE.DIFFAMANT.INFAMANT</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dd880ef8-7a84-4159-b910-4eac902c9273">ROBERTS 1998</ref>
<title>Encyclopedia of Comparative Iconography</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">149</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">65A</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">




























    </div>
</div>