<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-07855030-3463-472d-bd01-1c7ceebbfb3d">
<head>SPEAK</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>TALK</item>
<item>SAY ANYTHING/SOMETHING</item>
<item>UTTER</item>
<item>STATE</item>
<item>DECLARE</item>
<item>TELL</item>
<item>VOICE</item>
<item>EXPRESS</item>
<item>PRONOUNCE</item>
<item>ARTICULATE</item>
<item>ENUNCIATE</item>
<item>VOCALIZE</item>
<item>VERBALIZE.</item>
<item>GIVE A SPEECH</item>
<item>TALK</item>
<item>LECTURE</item>
<item>HOLD FORTH</item>
<item>DISCOURSE</item>
<item>EXPOUND</item>
<item>EXPATIATE</item>
<item>ORATE</item>
<item>SERMONIZE</item>
<item>PONTIFICATE</item>
<item>DECLAIM</item>
<item>INFORMAL SPOUT</item>
<item>SPIEL</item>
<item>SPEECHIFY</item>
<item>JAW</item>
<item>SOUND OFF.</item>
<item>SPEAK PUBLICLY</item>
<item>SPEAK OPENLY</item>
<item>SPEAK FRANKLY</item>
<item>SPEAK ONE'S MIND</item>
<item>SOUND OFF</item>
<item>STAND UP AND BE COUNTED</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">說</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">曰</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>ACT so as to USE WORDS FOR SHOWING MEANING.</p>
<p>*Speech by speaker X, directed towards audience Y, in order to communicate message Z.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-13T19:00:23.219+09:00">
            <p>1. The most colourless and general way of referring to any act of saying attributed to any subject, no matter whether animate or inanimate, something is yuē 曰, and the verb introduces what poses as direct but can often be the summarising of such speech and even the summarising of the subject's opinion.</p>
            <p>2. Yán 言 is to speak up, propose, typically in public, and on one's own initiative, to maintain something, and the word can indroduce direct speech as well as occasionally very limited indirect speech.</p>
            <p>3. Yǔ 語 is to say something as part of typically informal conversation. Contrast yù 語 "tell, inform" in REPORT.</p>
            <p>4. Tán 談 refers to informal communicative talk, sometimes but not always with some pejorative connotation.</p>
            <p>5. Yún 云 is used of books as well as persons and tends to refer to what are typically construed as authoritative acts of saying, and the word often has to be taken figuratively as "run as follows". (Note the perfectly regular contrast 曰 / 云 in MOUZI.)</p>
            <p>6. Wèi 謂 is to say or predicate something of someone. See also MEAN.</p>
            <p>7. Cí 辭 is primarily an act of careful articulation and rhetorical formulation.</p>
            <p>8. Dào 道 "speak of with authority, speak of adequately; quote" often involves quotation or especially serious discussion of important points, or the relating of important evidence.</p>
            <p>9. Jǔ 舉 is a technical term referring to the bringing up of a subject, and the subject of this verb is always a person, not a text.</p>
            <p>10. Chēng 稱 refers in a rather formal historian's style to the making of statements and the applying of terminology. See also NAME.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria" resp="#CH" modified="2022-10-26T02:55:49.216+09:00">
            <p>講</p>
            <p>講話</p>
            <p>說</p>
            <p>談話</p>
            <p>聊</p>
            <p>聊天</p>
            <p>談天兒</p>
            <p>聲明</p>
            <p>申明</p>
            <p>話 is the general noun for speech.</p>
            <p>言 is a literary word for words used.</p>
            <p>語 by itself is a literary word referring to talk.</p>
            <p>談 refers informally to dialogue.</p>
            <p>言語 is a rather formal way of speaking of discourse.</p>
            <p>言辭 refers to speech as a result of a deliberate act of formulation.</p>
            <p>說話 is the most common verb for talking.</p>
            <p>講話 refers to speech as an expression of opinion.</p>
            <p>話語 is a rather scientific abstract term for spoken forms of language.</p>
            <p>吐露 refers to speaking up on what ought to be kept secret.</p>
            <p>口稱 (lit) refers to the making of a (typically opening) remark.</p>
            <p>脫口而出 refers to blurting out a remark without proper reflection.</p>
            <p>&lt;div&gt;rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;GREEK KEYWORDS&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;αγορεύω vb. [reltd. άγορα] | impf. ήγόρευον, ep. άγόρευον&lt;br&gt;| aor. ήγόρευσα, ep. άγόρευσα | 1 speak before an assembly&lt;br&gt;or in public, make a speech, speak Hom. Hes. Hdt. E. Isoc.&lt;br&gt;X.+&lt;br&gt;2 hold — w.cogn.acc. an assembly IL&lt;br&gt;3 (as a formula used by the herald in the Assembly) τίς&lt;br&gt;άγορεύειν βούλεται; Who wishes to speak? Ar. Aeschin. D.&lt;br&gt;4 say (sthg.) before an assembly or in public; say, declare&lt;br&gt;—w.acc. or dir.sp. sthg. Hom. Hdt. Ar. X. AR. —W.COMPL.CL.&lt;br&gt;that sthg. is the case IL Hdt.; speak or tell οΐ—sthg. Hom.;&lt;br&gt;propose -w.inf. that sthg. shd. be done E.&lt;br&gt;5 || pass, (of a speech) be delivered Th.&lt;br&gt;6 (gener.) speak Hom. Hes. E. PL AR. Theoc. -words or sim.&lt;br&gt;Hom. AR.&lt;br&gt;7 say -W.ACC. or dir.sp. sthg. Hom. Hes. Thgn. Hdt. S. E. AR.&lt;br&gt;—w.indir.q. or compl.cl. what (or that sthg.) is the case&lt;br&gt;Od. Hdt.&lt;br&gt;8 speak or tell of -someone or sthg. Hom. AR. Theoc.; (fig., of&lt;br&gt;the lionskin worn by Herakles) -the prowess of his hands&lt;br&gt;Theoc.; speak —w. κακώς, κακόν or κακά abusively (usu.&lt;br&gt;W.ACC. of someone) Od. Hdt. Ar. D.(law) Plu.&lt;br&gt;9 give an order —w.inf. to do sthg. AR. —w.dat. and μή +&lt;br&gt;inf. to someone not to do sthg. Hdt. Ar.&lt;br&gt;10 (in an indignant q.) ούκ ήγόρευον; Didn’t I say (so)? Ar.&lt;br&gt;—w.acc. sthg. S. —w.compl.cl. that sthg. would be the case&lt;br&gt;Ar.&lt;br&gt;11 make a formal pronouncement; (of officials) pronounce&lt;br&gt;—sthg. (w. ως + predic.ptcpl.phr. as being such and such)&lt;br&gt;PL; (of a court herald, seer, auctioneer) announce, declare&lt;br&gt;—sthg. Arist. Theoc. Plu. || mid. (of a commander) have an&lt;br&gt;announcement made Hdt. || pass, be pronounced&lt;br&gt;—W.PREDIC.ADJ. evil PL&lt;br&gt;12 (of a law) pronounce, declare, prescribe D. Arist. —sthg.&lt;br&gt;Lys. —w.inf. or ACC. + inf. that one shd. do sthg. or that&lt;br&gt;sthg. shd. be done Antipho Lys.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br&gt;</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ffe85849-0547-451b-8952-d32067596c12">ADDRESS</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-55128168-da10-4764-be8d-400c8756d7a1">CRITICISE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c5280909-0367-44d7-b6e2-5a9280a661f6">DISCUSS</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-1fe8eefc-3167-45e1-ae40-a1e45c48cb6a">DISTINGUISH</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-e6b4e1e1-6e1e-4f01-a01b-4d658b1fb7d4">MOCK</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-69026a4a-550e-4b08-be94-0b5717050be4">PRAISE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-43301ee0-76a6-4734-a758-7be4ded906f5">SHOUT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-f30a70cf-cbce-46e7-a48e-814ec680b91c">SING</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-dd3de4ff-729c-487d-b762-f32b60f7cc45">DENY</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b8bacb6-d2b7-48e0-bf4f-23c19ba0882c">LIE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b4f91d33-15db-4b95-b0d8-5d582cee3f1a">ASSENT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-62e49b6c-d875-4431-bcae-3d46cf50229c">COMPLAIN</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-a9ce2789-dac0-45ea-8428-c483b4ffb65c">DISAGREE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-4977f342-0d3f-4880-a636-0866767917e5">CLASSIFY</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9e013653-f50a-43f1-b769-fee7c363a579">STUTTER</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-28207f02-7a6e-4b32-a4f0-7ab30a2c2ea9">CURSE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-e03e06fd-c039-47fc-a9b4-b439babd78a0">REPEAT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-1a4793cc-5ea5-4976-a6d9-76f951c94a59">SENTENCE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b6b64ef3-c1ee-4880-8c67-74af01e81f9d">EXAGGERATE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-69f9092a-b61c-4ba2-8aea-1e01c90d10e3">QUOTE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b0a506ed-e519-4542-9b61-a72558f74619">REFER TO</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-cb22b5dd-9568-4d1c-aa9e-392e26532c52">INTERRUPT</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-349040da-c1eb-4fa3-b050-afe086d9be7e">IRONY</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-fdd2e445-4a61-4cf3-bfd1-158726b36de6">NONSENSE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9947a411-73ef-4a80-a6e7-da950cf31a4d">QUOTATION MARKER</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-c75c9f91-6ddf-47b6-a920-362d8b9aa00a">EMPHASISE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-db1dabff-fad6-405f-8bbf-7cb4f6ac636d">SPEECH</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-81dd4d51-1010-4a3a-8e99-ec68b20aba81">BRAG</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ac2e06e9-975b-4a13-80ec-9a5ffb727472">AFFIRM</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-94248933-45fb-4136-8f80-4f0a3eb099ca">ORAL</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-05d3d56b-88da-4f57-b25a-35f20ae71cf8">JUBILATION</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-01183e72-9136-4006-8d2d-2bcdf9cff129">PRONOUNCE</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b5c76985-0c6b-497c-a427-d693b6d1108c">SILENCE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-bd2fb0c3-9ea9-4bd7-8841-9da413e46e49">DUMB</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-be238a91-d7bf-4b0c-97c3-543ac5d851e4">MEAN</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b5b456c9-7718-4f55-b20f-df79449d9820">SOUND</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-aa314ef9-9a5b-43c6-ae30-73674727ab51">NAME</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-abfdc4bb-445b-44d8-a4e9-f9f114a2beba">ACT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">18.22</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-c6a5120d-a888-44ce-b517-b0cbba82518a">CASSIN 2004</ref>
<title>Vocabulaire européen des philosophies. Dictionnaire des intraduisibles</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">727</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b8242ce-9fc6-4b7b-bd52-14c744308409">COMENIUS 1665</ref>
<title>De Rerum Humanarum Emendatione</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">573</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>LOQUI est cogitata sua voce lingvae significare alteri.</p>
<p>Req. 1. Aliqvis cogitans aliqvid.2. alqvis cui cogitata sua revelare velit. 3 Sina illa, per qvae cogitationes a mente illius in mentem hujus transeant, hoc est soni articulati.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-4af55868-d85f-4a0a-b22a-adbf6ab4a3a8">DIFFERENTIAE I</ref>
<title>De differentiis</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">226</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>GARRIRE LOQUI</p>
<p>267. Inter Garrire et loqui. Loquitur qui recte et temperanter dicit; garrit qui aut multa verba dicit, aut sordide loquitur.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>SAY</p>
<p>dicere refers to an act of saying as a means of conveying information.</p>
<p>aio refers to a claim that is being made.</p>
<p>asseverare is to affirm emphatically, and with special reference to earnestness.</p>
<p>affirmare refers to the claim that something is solidly certain.</p>
<p>contendere refers to the making of a claim as diverging froma tradition or a common assumption.</p>
<p>loqui refers to the act of talking as an activity by a speaker, often with connotations of idle talk.</p>
<p/>
<p>ENUNCIATE</p>
<p>enuntiare is to pronounce on something that has been on one's mind.</p>
<p>eloqui is to formulate something that has been one one's mind with some attention to form.</p>
<p/>
<p>enuntiatio is a logical term.</p>
<p>elocutio is primarily a rhetorical term.</p>
<p/>
<p>proloqui is to speak forth, as a moral act, as opposed to reticere "keep silent on a matter".</p>
<p>pronuntiare refers to the physical act of elocution of sounds or words.</p>
<p>recitare refers to the artistically modulated recitation of a whole sentence or text in public, with due attention being paid to the meaning of the text. See CHANT.</p>
<p/>
<p>SPEECH</p>
<p>verbum refers to the word as part of a complete utterance.</p>
<p>vocabulum refers to the word as part of a complete vocabulary.</p>
<p>voces refers to words with special refernce to their sounds.</p>
<p>vox is an expression of feeling or passion, like "exclamation".</p>
<p>dictum is an expression of wit or intellect, a point made.</p>
<p>dicterium is a late elevated word for dictum.</p>
<p/>
<p>TALK</p>
<p>garrire refers to the act of talking as performed by someone habitually and excessively fond of talking.</p>
<p>fabulari refers to the act of talking with emphasis on the nullity of what is being said.</p>
<p>blatire refers to the act of talking with special emphasis on the foolishness of what is being said.</p>
<p>blaterari refers to the act of talking with special emphasis on the extreme and remarkable foolishness of what is being said.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc235203-2ca8-4006-a7f5-c3246090e146">DUFOUR 1910</ref>
<title>Traite elementaire des synonymes grecques</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">35</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc235203-2ca8-4006-a7f5-c3246090e146">DUFOUR 1910</ref>
<title>Traite elementaire des synonymes grecques</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">62</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">204</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>VERBUM</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-abc2f8ad-0bc4-4663-a70c-806e480d7081">LUNHENG TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>論衡同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2c59ecb-bbff-4004-8e45-5fc7f92ed0da">Mel'cuk 1984</ref>
<title>Tolkovo-kombinatornyj slovar' sovremmenogo russkogo jazyka. Explanatory Combinatorial Dictionary of Modern Russian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">644</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-e65dd863-ccd1-4064-8fac-710a1be058a0">Mel'cuk I</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire explicatif et combinatoire du francais contemporain, vol. I</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">144</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">3.1381</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-9427a079-8f18-48af-805a-2628e9f9e725">WANG WEIHUI 2000</ref>
<title>東漢﹣隨常用詞演變研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">157</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1278</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>言，語</p>
<p>1. WL claim that the object of ya2n 言 is never a person spoken to.  In fact, ya2n yu2 言於 regularly means "speak to (a person of higher status)", and SSC records 62 instances of this.  </p>
<p>ZUO Xi 30.3.2 (630 B.C.); Ya2ng Bo2ju4n 479;  Wa2ng Sho3uqia1n et al. 356; tr. Watson 1989:65;  revised tr. CH </p>
<p>佚之狐言於鄭伯曰： Yi4 Zhi1hu2 delared in front of the Earl of Zhe4ng:</p>
<p>2. In many contexts ya2n 言 is to speak up and to formally propose or suggest something, typically to a superior. Yu3 語 does not have such usages and is almost always informal.  Formal serious discussion with question and answer tends to be ya2n 言and not yu3 語.</p>
<p>3. WL claims that that for "proverb, saying" one generally uses yu3 語 and not ya2n 言.  SSC has over 50 examples where ya2n 言 means "saying". Zuo Zhao 27.2.3(516 B.C.) Ya2ng Bo2ju4n 1483; Wa2ng Sho3uqia1n et al.1368 tr. Legge:721</p>
<p>「上國有言曰： "The upper States have a saying </p>
<p>『不索， that if you do not seeek for a thing </p>
<p>何獲？』 you will not get it."</p>
<p>The special feature of the sayings ya2n 言, regularly introduced by yo3u ya2n 有言 "there is/was a saying", is that they tend to be located or even attributed as bon-mots or geflgelte Worte to a person or even an author.  Yu3 語 on the other hand is only once in SSC attributed to someone specific (the people of the state of So4ng), and the word generally tends to refer to current popular sayings even when the phrase bi3 yu3 鄙語 is not used.</p>
<p>4. WL compares“言”和“語”. But it remains quite unclear whether the reference is to yu3 語 or yu4 語, two very different words.  When WL talk about the nominal uses of 語 the reference must be to yu3 語, whereas when they speak of the meaning "tell" for 語 the reference is to yu4 語.  As a result the article is a complete mess.</p>
<p>This example shows up clearly that the method of attaching synonym discussions to words rather than to words under a given interpretation is manifestly wrong and thoroughly confusing.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ceec1ff7-e9e2-4e81-8c76-a29b231e6074">WU SANXING 2008</ref>
<title>中國文化背景八千詞 Zhongguo wenhua beijing ba qian ci</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">234ff</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b425a52b-7c3a-4b26-a4a5-8c5a55eaf19b">GRACE ZHANG 2010</ref>
<title>Using Chinese Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">217</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-93502795-e958-4bb9-ae45-2b1258a7d635">TENG SHOU-HSIN 1996</ref>
<title>Chinese Synonyms Usage Dictionary</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">374</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-93502795-e958-4bb9-ae45-2b1258a7d635">TENG SHOU-HSIN 1996</ref>
<title>Chinese Synonyms Usage Dictionary</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">378</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ad3bdc83-0b1c-471f-b1ef-28c098e55626">BARNARD AND SPENCER 2002</ref>
<title>Encyclopedia of Social and Cultural Anthropology</title>
                <note>
<p>DISCOURSE</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.315</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.310</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">338</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">75B</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>AEUSSERUNG(SPRACHLICHE)</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">











































































    </div>
</div>