<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650">
<head>STATES</head><list type="translations"><item xml:lang="zh">國家類</item></list>
<div type="definition">
<p>An individual STATE, names of major states in the Warring States period.</p></div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>[TO BE ENTERED: 1. Location and general characteristics</p>
<p>2. The order of geographical size.</p>
<p>3. The order of political importance, and the change of this hierarchy, ending with the predominance of Qin.</p>
<p>4. Distinctive prominent features economically and culturally.</p>
<p>5. Current opinion on every state, where applicable.]</p></div></div>
<div type="pointers"><list type="mereonymy">
<item><ref target="#uuid-7ece8d12-ab6f-4a9d-85a1-56ae48c83be0">CITIES</ref></item></list></div>
<div type="source-references"><listBibl>
<bibl><ref target="#uuid-80d7dd9f-4545-4784-8419-dfc8d0f1b818">DOSSIERS 2003</ref>
<title>Apercus de civilisation chinoise</title><note>
<p/></note></bibl>
<bibl><ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title><biblScope unit="page">1053</biblScope><note>
<p>楚，荊</p>
<p>1. Ji1ng is certainly the deprecatory term for Chu3.  But it is not true that HF uses mainly Ji1ng: Chu3 is used ca. 64 times, Ji1ng something like 80 times depending on what editions one bases oneself on.</p></note></bibl></listBibl></div>
<div type="words">
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f36b3543-b9bd-42d4-bc91-54ae3a696e67"><form corresp="#uuid-06609cb8-c3e0-46fd-b12b-6e55d00cb797">
<orth>任</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">rén</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">njɯm</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ȵim</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-8c6de167-87b7-4353-ad78-ce26339ae568">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Ren</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-07fa44a6-6896-421e-b73a-b5a520f6cdfb"><form corresp="#uuid-df0ef17d-04e9-4382-87d5-e6a239d1682b">
<orth>共</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">gōng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">koŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ki̯oŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f9ff4601-7d6f-4c00-8248-78c932c19fe8">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Gōng 共 (CHEN PAN 1969, 318-327)Clan: Unknown. Rank: According to the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì, the rulers of Gōng were of the bó rank 伯. Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: In the early Chunqiu period (but after 722 B.C. - Yin 1 - when Gōng is mentioned in the ZUO), Gōng was conquered by Wèi 衛 (in 660 B.C. - Min 2 - the people of Gōng were attached to the people of Wèi). Location: According to the Cheng's Guó cè dì míng kǎo, Gōng was located in the modern Huī 輝 district, Henan province.History: Gōng was a very small state, but it was not completely unimportant in the early Chinese history. According to the Zhúshū jǐnián, Hé 和, the ruler of Gōng, ruled as a regent from 841 to 828 B.C., after Zhōu King Lì 周厲王 was sent to an exile by aristocracy (the period being thus known as Gōng Hé 共和 ). This is attested also by the inscription on the Shī X guǐ 師 X 簋 (see Shaughnessy 1999, 345). The state of Gōng is mentioned also for the later periods; in 722 B.C. (Yin 1), Shū Duàn 叔段, the brother of Lord Zhuāng of Zhèng 鄭莊公 (743-701 B.C.), fled to this state, and was then known as Gōngshū Duàn 共叔段. It should be noted that prior to the beginning of the Western Zhōu period, there was also another state of Gōng, the conquest of which by the King Wén of Zhōu 周文王 is recorded in the poem Huáng yī of the Shī jīng. Apparently, it must have been located close to the former Zhōu realm in the Wèi 渭 river valley; Lù shǐ Guó míng jì suggested the modern Língtái 靈臺 district in Gansu province as the probable location. Which was the relationship (if there was any) between this Gōng and Gōng in Henan is unknown; it cannot be excluded that in the Western Zhōu times, the former fief of Gōng was located in the West, and then it shifted to the East during the turmoil in the turn of the Western and Eastern Zhōu periods, as was the case of many other states. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2444d930-728f-43f1-8d46-5a34bf3e0276"><form corresp="#uuid-61a8b1ce-8dd9-4fac-b2b4-ce006a6152ac">
<orth>冀</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jì</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">krɯls</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ki</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b68f3237-0b49-4cba-847e-f65395f32c55">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Ji</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-a6a88a9b-24b2-4918-9162-0f7b610fb494"><form corresp="#uuid-e20ad981-2111-43d6-a4f6-3d961536094a">
<orth>凡</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">fán</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">blom</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">bi̯ɐm</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1bbbba3a-9cfd-4de0-ab05-a4b6dcc11bdc">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Fán 凡 (also written as Fàn 汎 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 379-382)Clan: Jī 姬. Rank: Bó 伯 (appears in the both CQ and ZUO). Founded: In the Early Western Zhōu period by one of the sons of the Duke of Zhōu 周公 (according to the ZUO, Xi 24; 636 B.C.). Destroyed: Unknown. Location: According to the Du's commentary and Xù Hàn Jùn guó zhì, Fán was located in the modern Huī 輝 district, Henan province. History: The state for the first time appears in the ZUO under Yin 7 (716 B.C.). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-0d1b53be-7c59-4d38-9e7f-47adc1df48a4"><form corresp="#uuid-bf73c9d3-efe5-4310-9122-87929dd110ea">
<orth>原</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yuán</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋɡon</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋi̯ɐn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-14b96fc0-8155-40a2-952d-dcacbf7a7a32">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Yuán 原 (CHEN PAN 1969, 519-521)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Bó 伯 (common in the CQ and ZUO).Founded: The state of Yuán was founded in the early Western Zhōu period by one of the sons of the Zhōu King Wén 周文王 (according to the Shū jīng Jūn Shì zhēngyì and to the Xìng xī). Destroyed: The state is mentioned in the ZUO in the entry for 676 B.C. (Zhuang 18). In 635 B.C. (Xi 25), the state already was not in existence, as in that year the Zhōu 周 king gave the city of Yuán to Jìn 晉. Thereafter, Yuán was shifted by Jìn to Yì 翼 in Shānxī province. Location: According to the Hàn zhì and Dì míng kǎo lyè, Yuán was located in the modern Jǐyuán 濟源, Henan province. On the contrary, Du's commentary to the ZUO and also Tōng zhì suggest that it was located in the modern Qìnshuǐ 沁水, Shānxī province. According to CHEN PAN, Henan Yuán was in fact another Yuán, which is mentioned in the ZUO for 711 B.C. as one of the cities given by the Zhōu 周 King to Zhèng 鄭. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-30232d5e-94e0-468b-b2f5-8507ea844d7c"><form corresp="#uuid-0f38d0bc-76d5-43d4-ac0e-3bb004f85980">
<orth>厲</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">lì</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">b-rads</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">liɛi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-782f47b2-2e74-4063-b582-97a315f91520">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Lì 厲 (probably identical wit Lài 賴 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 611-620)Ruling clan: Uncertain. According to the Hàn 漢 tradition, the rulers of Lì were descendants of Lìshānshì 厲山氏, who (according to the Jìn 晉 tradition) was identical with Shén Nóng 神農. The descendants of Shén Nóng are said to possess Jiāng 姜 surname. However, these legends (mentioned in the late texts) are very unreliable. Rank: Uncertain. In the ZUO (Zhao 4, 538 B.C.), the ruler of Lì is one time referred to as zǐ 子.Founded: Unknown (see Ruling clan). Destroyed: In 538 B.C. (Zhao 4) by Chǔ 楚.Location: Uncertain. According to the one opinion (Gù Dōnggāo quoting Qián Hàn dì lǐ zhì), the state was located in the area of the modern Lìshāndiàn 厲山店, in the northern part of Suízhōu 隨州, Hubei province. According to the other (Bao Xin's commentary to the Xù Hàn shū Jùn guó zhì), Lì was located in the modern Lìxiāng 厲鄉, to the east of Lùyì 鹿邑, Henan province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-455823e0-d0d9-4823-8608-6518e270fa30"><form corresp="#uuid-87cab1f5-d8d7-405a-aa85-7f5f68b557ca">
<orth>向</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xiàng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhaŋs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">hi̯ɐŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f95fae0f-bc94-4b07-83cf-e26fe8b470b5">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xiàng 向 (CHEN PAN 1969, 350-356)Clan: Jiāng 姜 (according to the ZUO - Yin 2 - and to the Shì běn). Probably, there were also two other states of the same name, with ruling lineages bearing Zǐ 子 and Qí 祁 surnames (according to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè and to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì). However, nothing is known about their location and history. Rank: Unknown.Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: In 721 B.C. (Yin 2), the state of Jǔ 莒 attacked Xiàng. Later (in 605 B.C.; Xuān 4), Xiàng is mentioned as a city belonging to Jǔ. As one regards Xiàng with the ruling lineage bearing Zǐ 子 surname (location unknown), it is supposed to be conquered by Sòng 宋, because the Xiàng 向 lineage was later one of the most important lineages in the latter state (being for the first time mentioned in the record for 586 B.C.; Cheng 5). Location: Several possible locations for Xiàng (ranging from Anhui to Henan province) were offered by traditional Chinese historiography. However, with regard to the fact that Xiàng was obviously located in the neighborhood of Jǔ 莒 and Lǔ 魯, the most probable location is the modern Jǔ 莒 district in the southwestern part of the Shandong province. History: Xiàng was a small and unimportant state, which was probably destroyed in the beginning of the early Chunqiu period, and is mentioned only one time (721 B.C.) as an independent state. Other five mentions of Xiàng in the CQ and ZUO refers to it as a city belonging to other states. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-aefd7669-3adb-44d2-949e-aba1fe08d181"><form corresp="#uuid-c7266f09-7684-46c4-ad10-fe2d2f463700">
<orth>吳</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wú</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋʷaa</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋuo̝</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-544995bc-0c0d-4db9-a2d6-29f5241d721b">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of  a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-9888ab63-148b-493c-ab6f-9a3291698c37"><form corresp="#uuid-6f54daf0-aa06-4469-8d5c-52be1bac8d50">
<orth>周</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhōu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tjɯw</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3f156d48-3d83-4190-8972-0823e834f7cc">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a tribe and of a state; name of dynasties</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-e0b9c167-acda-4852-8e3d-4e814c2f9d07"><form corresp="#uuid-ce5dfd21-7d74-4fe9-9abb-f28f250a6144">
<orth>商</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shāng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjaŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɐŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ec91cdff-6ef5-4743-b8a7-8b8ddff98881">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a dynasty and of a tribe</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-748f38a6-2707-4e2a-8966-0085f267ad6f"><form corresp="#uuid-6d7ee858-72a8-4b9c-9c38-959b11142323">
<orth>夏</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xià</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡraaʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɣɛ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-fa245083-ab12-455b-9bd7-a321f4becc6e">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">4</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>the Xià dynasty</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2c16ad96-126d-484b-a74e-c7c9ed95b94b"><form corresp="#uuid-52b69f36-1ac7-4da0-9299-4cfe1b2df5e2">
<orth>宋</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sòng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">suuŋs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">suo̝ŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-fb195a53-38de-47aa-beef-90c8952d38cc">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-1c328ffc-c712-41b8-906d-9e6d1a2c2cea"><form corresp="#uuid-33ab6c76-5aae-4fd1-9ef4-a297b3db7608">
<orth>宿</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sù</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">suɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">suk</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-cf387869-f86e-418d-ac92-3d4205480f7c">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Sù 宿 (CHEN PAN 1969, 291-293)Clan: Fēng 風 (according to the ZUO, Xi 21).Rank: Nán 男.Founded: According to the tradition recorded in the Tōng zhì Shì zú lyè and Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, Sù was established by King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王, and ruled by the descendants of the mythical ruler Tài Hào 太皞.Destroyed: In the ZUO in the record for 500 B.C. (Ding 10), Sù is mentioned as already belonging to Qí 齊. Location: Sù is supposed to be located in the area of modern Dōngpíng 東平, Shandong province. According to the CQ, in 584 B.C. (Zhuang 10), Sòng 宋 shifted the capital of Sù, but its new location is unknown. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-30f65a6a-9e82-4ffa-ab38-3b78eb260f2d"><form corresp="#uuid-04dd5388-2dab-4fd8-9f3f-554c4e967b4b">
<orth>密</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">mì</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">mbriɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">mit</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6af4995e-ee6b-42fe-918d-b0572920ed41">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Mì 密 (CHEN PAN 1969, 629-634)Ruling clan: Jī 姬 (according to the Yan's commentary to the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì quoting Shì běn). This suggestion is supported by the fact that - according to the ZUO (Xi 17) - Lord Huán of Qí 齊桓公 (685-643 B.C.) had the consort Mì Jī 密姬. Rank: Unknown. Founded: Unknown (see History).Destroyed: See History. Location: See History.History: The case of Mì is rather complicated. It seems that there were at least two states of this name. The first one was perhaps located in the modern Mì 密 district, Henan province, and its rulers had Zhōu royal surname Jī 姬. Mì Jī, the consort of the Duke Huán of Qí, mentioned in the ZUO (Xi 17), probably had something to do with this state. However, it is by no means certain that the state was still in existence by that time. The area of that state was perhaps identical with the city of Xīn Mì 新密, which in 654 B.C. (ZUO Xi 6) already belonged to Zhèng 鄭. On this basis, Gāo Shìqí has suggested that the state of Mì was prior to the period recorded by CQ conquered by the state of Kuài 鄶, which was in turn conquered by Zhèng. Mì Jī could come from the former ruling lineage of this Mì, which was preserved within a noble class (according to Chén Qīnhán). Another state of Mì was perhaps located in the area of the modern Língtái 靈臺, Gansu province. It is mentioned in the Shī jīng (poem Huáng yī), according to which it was destroyed by King Wén of Zhōu 周文王. It is also associated with Mì mentioned in the Guó yǔ (Zhōu yǔ), which was later conquered by King Gòng of Zhōu 周共王. According to the Wei's commentary to the Guó yǔ, this Mì was of Jī 姬 origin. However, yet another Mì (also located by Wei to the area of Língtái) is mentioned in the Zhōu yǔ, which was of Jí 姞 surname. According to the Wei's commentary, there were two states of Mì in the Língtái area; but more probable seems to be the view of Wu Zhuoxin, who supposes that the former state of Mì, the rulers of which bore Jí 姞 surname, was that conquered by King Wén, who then gave the area as a fief to the lineage of the Jī 姬 surname (which was later destroyed by King Gòng). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-51083662-94b5-48a5-8edc-660e7b31df36"><form corresp="#uuid-875ca067-c285-434c-91df-40d7f2498d27">
<orth>州</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhōu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kju</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b68a0c6d-1905-4376-b948-23c5b774056d">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Zhōu 州 (also written as 舟; also called Chúnyú 淳于 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 411-416)Clan: Uncertain. According to the Xúnzǐ and Shì běn, the rulers of Zhōu belonged to the Jiāng 姜 clan. Rank: Gōng 公 (according to the ZUO and CQ, Huan 5). Founded: Unknown. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jǐ, the state of Zhōu was founded in the Early Western Zhōu period, during the reign of King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王. Destroyed: Unknown. According to the CQ and the ZUO, in 707 B.C. (Huan 5), the ruler of Zhōu fled to Cáo 曹. Later, the area was occupied by the state of Qǐ 杞.Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, the state of Zhōu was located in the area of modern Ānqiū 安丘, Shandong province. Lù shǐ Guó míng jǐ has suggested that the state was located in the modern Gāomì 高密, also in the Shandong province. According to some of the traditional Chinese scholars (Zhào Péngfēi; Yáo Nài), the state of Zhōu belonged to the eastern royal domain in central Henan (for 712 B.C. - Yin 11 - it is mentioned in the ZUO that the Zhōu 周 king gave the fields of Zhōu to the state of Zhèng). It cannot be excluded that the state of Zhōu was originally located within the royal domain (this can also explain why its rulers had the title of the Duke); however, by the beginning of the Chunqiu period, the state was obviously in the Shandong area. History: Zhōu was a small and unimportant state mentioned only one time (in 707 B.C.; Huan 5) in the CQ and ZUO. It is rather mysterious that on this occasion, its ruler is designated gōng in both texts. Maybe the state of Zhōu was originally located within the royal domain (see Location), and its rulers held some high positions in the Zhōu 周 royal court. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-107b36ce-3ea0-435a-89a9-391d295feb25"><form corresp="#uuid-fe234715-d0db-48e2-8bda-e382d4a20ea8">
<orth>巴</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">bā</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">praa</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">pɣɛ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c598c2d1-474e-4943-95ee-fe61324c50f1">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Bā 巴 (CHEN PAN 1969, 436-446) Clan: Jī 姬 (the wife of the Chǔ king Gōng 楚恭王, which is mentioned in the ZUO, Zhao 13, was called Bā Jī 巴姬 ). In the traditional Chinese historiography, there appear also other opinions concerning the surname of the Bā rulers. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì, the rulers of Bā had Yíng 嬴 surname; in the same text, there is mentioned another Bā with Fēng 風 surname. Yú dì guǎng jì states that Bā was of the same surname as Shāng 商 kings, i.e. Zǐ 子. The matter is complicated, and it is possible that there were more states of that name. Nonetheless, the main Bā in Sichuan should have been of Jī 姬 surname. Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the Huáyáng guó zhì).Founded: Again, there are different opinions concerning the origins of Bā. According to the Huáyáng guó zhì, Bā of Jī surname was established by King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王. Destroyed: In 316 B.C. by Qín 秦 (according to the Shǐ jì - Qín běnjì, Liù guó niánbiǎo, and Zhāng Yí zhuàn chapters - and to the Huáyáng guó zhì). According to the Zhànguó cè (Qín cè), it was conquered in 329 B.C. Location: There are some problems concerning the precise location of Bā, and it is quite probable that its center shifted several times (what is also stated in the Huáyáng guó zhì). Hàn shū dì lǐ zhì and Du's commentary to the ZUO locate the state of Bā into the area of the modern Bā 巴 district in the eastern part of Sichuan province. Lù shǐ Guó míng jì suggested that it was located in the modern Nánchōng 南充 district in Sichuan. According to Mēng Wéntōng, Bā was located in the Lǎngzhōng 閬中 district of the same province. Tóng Shūyè on the basis of the records in the ZUO and Zhànguó cè (which suggest that Bā could not have been too far from the capital of Chǔ 楚 and from the states of Dèng 鄧 and Yōng 庸 ) supposed that the center of Bā was located somewhere in the area of the Hàn 漢 River valley in the southeastern part of Shǎnxī province. This view seems to be quite reasonable; however, we probably should locate a broader area of the Bā activities somewhere between the southeastern Shǎnxī, southwestern Henan, northwestern Hubei, and northeastern Sichuan. History: Bā played not an unimportant role in the history of the Chunqiu and Zhanguo periods, particularly as a rival of the neighboring powerful state of Chǔ 楚. In 676 B.C. (Zhuang 18), armies of Bā even reached the gates of the Chǔ capital, but were defeated in the following year. Another great siege was laid on Chǔ by Bā in 477 B.C., but the result was again the defeat of Bā. In the 4th century B.C., Bā became an ally of the state of Qín against the states of Shǔ 蜀 and Chǔ. However, after the conquest of Shǔ, Qín also annexed Bā in 316 B.C. (or 329 B.C.).  Bā was known as a semi-barbarian or even barbarian state, which differed from the states of Huá Xià 華夏, or Zhū Xià 諸夏 (in spite of its proclaimed Jī 姬 - i.e. Zhōu 周 - origins). It probably had quite distinctive culture and customs, and some archaeological finds from the eastern part of Sichuan are mainly by Chinese archaeologists labeled under the general term of the Bā culture. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-044c42cc-5be8-419b-aac2-71e5f11216a1"><form corresp="#uuid-4c74aa74-6e7e-42a0-9900-df8b330e95cc">
<orth>干</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">gān</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kaan</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɑn</pron></form><form corresp="#uuid-62d5bb00-64cd-4739-b8d9-b10da39dbda4">
<orth>邗</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">gān</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kaan</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɑn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-91993f4b-ac5d-417e-adb6-9337d9c92498">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>ancient state conquered by Wu, the name of this state being used in literary contexts to refer to Wu in the phrase 干越</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2bddaa72-2ce9-46b4-80c3-51e36558c8e0"><form corresp="#uuid-ea6bbf8b-8d9e-4777-9bbb-d46f49e54b5d">
<orth>弦</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xián</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡeen</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦen</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-68716710-6f23-4bc4-bdee-56c3448db865">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Xián</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-51982e24-a322-4791-aa4a-4690521cf65b"><form corresp="#uuid-0b34e21a-662f-4951-82dd-f82b87fe5eb4">
<orth>徐</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xú</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lja</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">zi̯ɤ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d12eaf33-9e88-430a-a368-4e3cfc20e653">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>A state, older even than that of Zhōu, a powerful state at the early stage that was able to challenge the Zhōu, but finally destroyed in 512.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2004251e-998e-4ce6-a409-4aa4bb3eae49"><form corresp="#uuid-1449f71e-9ea1-432c-abb1-f546d4c0b531">
<orth>息</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xī</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sqlɯɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">sɨk</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-295036de-bf58-4d26-8138-a06512ff393e">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xī 息 (CHEN PAN 1969, 388-390)Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the ZUO, Yin 11 - 712 B.C. - and to the Du's commentary to that passage, as well as to the Shì běn). Rank: Hóu 侯 (appears in the ZUO). Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: In 684 B.C. (Zhuang 10) by Chǔ 楚. Location: According to the Zuǒ zhuàn zhēngyì, Xī was located in the modern Xī 息 district, Henan province. History: Xī was a small and weak state, but it is quite remarkable for the curious and rather piquant story about its downfall. Both the rulers of Xī and Cài 蔡 married the daughters of the ruler of Chén 陳; but when Xī Guī 息媯, the wife of the ruler of Xī, passed through the state of Cài, the ruler of Cài detained her. The furious ruler of Xī thereafter proposed to the King Wén of Chǔ 楚文王 to pretend an attack on Xī, in order to enable the ruler of Xī to request a help from Cài, which then could be attacked by Chǔ. The king of Chǔ followed the proposal, defeated Cài, and captured its ruler. Immediately, Chǔ also destroyed Xī following the advice of Xī Guī persuaded by the captured ruler of Cài. Xi Gui eventually became a consort of the King Wén of Chǔ. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-98635c15-bb1b-40f3-b26f-9d203dc2b0a7"><form corresp="#uuid-6dc77d76-089f-4fa7-b54b-2181c503fcc1">
<orth>戴</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">dài</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">k-lɯɯs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">təi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d5cf490b-6abf-452e-bc48-5cdecbef76a4">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Dài 戴 (also written as 甾, 載, or 圪 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 383-387) Clan: According to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì and Fēngsú tōng, the rulers of Dài belonged to the Jī 姬 clan. It is supported by the inscription on the Dàishū Qìngfǔ lì 戴叔慶父鬲. On the other hand, according to the Lù shǐ Hòu jǐ, the rulers of Dài were descendents of Wēizǐ Qǐ 微子啟, and had thus Zǐ 子 surname. Rank: Unknown.Founded: Unknown. Note that Dài or Dài fāng 戴方 is mentioned in the oracle bone inscriptions. Which was the relationship between this Dài and the later Zhōu state is unknown. Destroyed: Uncertain. In 713 B.C. (Yin 10), Dài was subdued by Zhèng 鄭; probably it put an end to its existence. Location: Several locations of Dài within Henan province were suggested by the traditional Chinese historiography. Hàn zhì and Xù zhì suppose that it was located in the Kǎochéng 考城 district. Du's commentary proposed an area of the modern Qǐ 杞 district; and Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè located Dài into the modern Fēngqiū 封丘 district. In Chūnqiū shǐ, the modern Mínquán 民權 district is suggested (is it identical with any place mentioned above???? Check!). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2f68521c-09b5-4bb1-b45b-01f3c1a2ee61"><form corresp="#uuid-4b0e1c9a-44d5-48ef-a7dd-0700e314df76">
<orth>晉</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jìn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tsins</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tsin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-058a748a-e331-43f4-a856-3bede0eacb6e">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-ddf694b3-2d62-4324-954c-d541c7899557"><form corresp="#uuid-9e0e2991-a25d-4d1d-aa7b-26e6150e0e70">
<orth>曹</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">cáo</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">dzuu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dzɑu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-48d3cb70-6ecf-42a2-9de9-c685142cede6">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-0530883e-2469-44d0-9bfa-064bc1175062"><form corresp="#uuid-4d8267de-ab14-4ee7-971f-cc599487401a">
<orth>杞</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">qǐ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">khɯʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">khɨ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b6826d19-6f66-4bda-953a-5ab8803568bd">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-62119cba-7d98-43b1-954a-392d9a13ad1d"><form corresp="#uuid-cd14db55-3f80-4eff-8a10-76d9d20a1cde">
<orth>柏</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">bó</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">praaɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">pɣɛk</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-7ecd3480-0fc7-4858-88b2-32c4272a35af">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Bo</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-0cc4f1e0-814e-4292-bc3c-a70c4f95b031"><form corresp="#uuid-8f4c6fef-a2d0-4f42-84c9-0b140eccd8d6">
<orth>梁</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">liáng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">k-raŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">li̯ɐŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-00f54bf0-afd0-4f1f-b066-1a8280b567b3">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Liáng 梁 (CHEN PAN 1969, 450-453)Clan: Yíng 嬴 (appears in the inscriptions on the bronzes; also written as 盈 or Yǎn 偃 ). Rank: Bó 伯 (common in the ZUO). Founded: Unknown. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì, Guǎng yùn, and to the Tōng zhì Shì zú lyè, the state of Liáng was founded during the reign of the Zhōu king Píng 周平王 (770-720 B.C.) by his son Kāng 康 (what is in contradiction with the supposed Yíng surname of the Liáng rulers). On the other hand, Hòu Hàn shū (quoting Dōng guàn jì), Hàn zhì, and Fēngsú tōng state that the rulers of Liáng were of the same lineage as the ruling house of Qín 秦. Destroyed: In 641 B.C. (Xi 19) by Qín 秦. Location: Modern Shǎo Liáng 少梁 in the Hánchéng 韓城 district, eastern Shǎnxī province (according to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, to the Hàn zhì, and to the Xù Hàn Jùn guó zhì). History: Liáng was a small and unimportant state, destroyed by Qín, which thereafter established there the city of Shǎo Liáng 少梁. In 617 B.C. (Wen 10), the area was conquered by Jìn 晉. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-38fa84de-5fbd-470a-95a4-02f000a4c10b"><form corresp="#uuid-9b080dbb-b943-466d-86c6-1686315584d4">
<orth>極</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jí</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡɯɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">gɨk</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-728338be-0b99-4691-9af9-0c964577ceb8">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Jí 極 (it was suggested that this Jí is Jù 遽 of the bronze inscriptions, but this identification remains uncertain) (CHEN PAN 1969, 357-359)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Dependent state.Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: In 720 B.C. (Yin 2) by Lǔ 魯. Location: In the southern part of the modern Jīnxiāng 金鄉, Shandong province.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-18ecfebe-2086-4de5-8793-8f3d83acd9ea"><form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112">
<orth>楚</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-df6c5067-da39-4458-a55a-9b7b23550faf">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-18019dfe-5655-487f-bc7b-7a1434f64ad1">npr.adV</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>in the manner of Chǔ</def></sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-311645d2-01c9-47ce-92c4-ee1a5935337f">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-8b80662b-7765-487f-9d5f-9b1804fcb416"><form corresp="#uuid-24d52510-cc71-4e20-8ee2-919323a8eede">
<orth>樊</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">fán</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ban</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">bi̯ɐn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-57e8325e-6dd9-4e8a-9b93-da08c46bd6ac">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Fán 樊 (also called Yáng Fán 陽樊 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 548-555)Clan: Unknown. Several opinions concerning the ruling clan of Fán were offered by traditional Chinese historiography. According to the inscription on the stone tablet dating from the Hàn dynasty, the rulers of Fán belonged to the royal Jī 姬 clan; this view is also supported by Tōng zhì and Xìng zuǎn. On the contrary, Hàn shū states that the rulers of Fán were of a different surname from that of the Zhōu royal house, and Qián fū lún attributes to them Fán 樊 surname (which is otherwise unknown from the Chinese Antiquity). In the other place of the latter text, the rulers of Fán are said to be of Jiāng 姜 surname. According to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, the rulers of Fán were descendants of the Shāng dynasty. The most probable seems to be the opinion attributing to Fán the royal Jī surname. This is also supported by the record in the Jìn yǔ chapter of the Guó yǔ mentioning that the rulers of Fán were relatives of the Zhōu kings. It should be noted that in the inscription on the Fán jūn lì 樊君鬲, there is mentioned the women from the ruling house of Fán, which is called Shūnéng Mǐ 叔能羋; it suggest that there was also another state of the same name, the rulers of which were relatives of the ruling house of Chǔ 楚. Rank: According to the Máo shī Dà yá Zhēng mín zhuàn and to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, the rulers of Fán possessed the hóu 侯 rank. ZUO (Zhao 22) mentions Fán Qīngzǐ 樊慶子, but in this case it is not certain whether the title points to one of the Five ranks; it seems that this person had no relation with the ancient state which was destroyed earlier (see Destroyed). Founded: In the traditional Chinese historiography, there is a general consensus that the founder of Fán was called Zhòng Shānfǔ 仲山甫 / 父. However, there are different opinions concerning his origin. Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè states that he was the descendant of Yúzhòng 虞仲 (the son of the pre-conquest Zhōu king Tài wáng 周太王 ) and served as a minister (qīngshì 卿士 ) in the court of Zhōu King Xuān 周宣王 (827-782 B.C.), from which he received his fief. On the other hand, Quán dé Yú jí suggests that this person served in the Zhōu royal court, but that he actually was the son of Lord Xiàn of Lǔ 魯獻公. Hán shū agrees that Zhòng Shānfǔ was a royal minister, but denies that he would have any kin relationship to the Zhōu royal house (what seems less probable; see Clan). Destroyed: In 635 B.C. (Xi 25), Zhōu king gave Fán to Jìn 晉, which then annexed it. Fán Qīngzǐ 樊慶子 mentioned in the ZUO in the entry for 520 B.C. (Zhao 22) had perhaps nothing to do with the former line of the Fán rulers; according to the Guǎng yùn and to the Shuǐ jīng zhù, at that time Fán was a fief of the descendants of the Zhōu king Jǐng 周景王 (544-520 B.C.). Location: According to the Du's commentary, Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, and to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jǐ, Fán was located in the modern Jǐyuán district 濟源, Henan province.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2cb2fed4-bd5b-44fb-92c4-ebcdc3a8c654"><form corresp="#uuid-45ad686c-5637-4415-9838-f6fccab6e682">
<orth>權</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">quán</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡron</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">giɛn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-02d09b5e-ddbf-415e-8bc1-a1ef6ed17816">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Quán 權 (CHEN PAN 1969, 522-524)Clan: Uncertain. According to the Chén Péng's Chūngqiū guó dū jué xìng kǎo, the rulers of Quán belonged to the Yǎn 偃 clan; Táng zāixiàng biǎo suggests that they were of Zǐ 子 surname, and Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè attributes to them Mǐ 羋 surname. Rank: Unknown.Founded: Unknown. According to the Táng zǎixiàng biǎo, the rulers of Quán were descendants of the Shāng 商 king Wǔ Dīng 武丁. Destroyed: According to the ZUO, Zhuang 18 (676 B.C.), Quán was conquered by Chǔ 楚 during the reign of King Wǔ of Chǔ 楚武王 (740-690 B.C.). Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, the state of Quán was located in the modern Dāngyáng 當陽 district in Hubei province. Shuǐ jīng zhù locates it into the modern Zhōngxiáng 鍾祥 in the same province, only 30 kilometers from Dāngyáng. It is possible that the latter location is the place to which Quán was shifted after its conquest by Chǔ. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-c390a09d-0311-41b5-b8c5-73c40f9c2295"><form corresp="#uuid-685c4e7a-dba9-4cce-916a-fcfc4f33753d">
<orth>殷</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yīn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qɯn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔɨn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-16ed5384-5eaa-431a-a380-cd38c1ca7bd1">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a dynasty, the Yīn or Shāng</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-01457132-3625-45cd-862b-d9ba091cb44d"><form corresp="#uuid-b8e4b261-4efa-4136-abc3-e7ffab99730d">
<orth>毛</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">máo</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">moow</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">mɑu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-fbf53e41-6a44-4c8d-a428-729e49452c99">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Máo 毛 (CHEN PAN 1969, 644-646)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Bó 伯 (common in the CQ and ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts and in some transmitted texts (such as Gù mìng chapter of the Shū jīng and the Mù tiānzǐ zhuàn), the rulers of Máo are referred to as gōng 公 (what was perhaps due to the fact that they hold high positions in the Zhōu royal court).Founded: According to the Shǐ jì (Zhōu běnjì) and to the Yì Zhōu shū (Kè Yīn chapter), the first ruler of Máo was Shūzhèng 叔鄭, the son of the Zhōu king Wén 周文王. In the ZUO (Ding 4), the founder of Máo is called Shūdān 叔聃; according to the Shǐ jì zhì yí, it is a mistake, and this person was in fact a younger brother of the founder of Máo. Destroyed: In 516 B.C. (Zhao 26), the ruler of Máo fled from its state to Chǔ 楚.Location: The rulers of Máo were closely associated with the Zhōu royal court and their fief was probably within the royal domain. In the Western Zhōu period, it was perhaps located in the area of the western Zhōu capitals in Fúfēng 扶風, Shǎnxī province, where some bronzes cast by Máo rulers were found (including famous Máo gōng dǐng 毛公鼎 ). In the Eastern Zhōu period, Máo was probably shifted to the neighborhood of the eastern Zhōu capital Chéng Zhōu 成周 (modern Luòyáng 洛陽 ). Qīng scholar Gù Dònggāo has in his Chūnqiū dà shì biǎo suggested that Máo was located in the modern Yíyáng 宜陽, Henan province. History: Máo was a small, but not unimportant state, mainly because of its close relationship with the Zhōu royal house. Some traditional sources (for instance the Gù mìng chapter of the Shū jīng) and inscriptions on the bronze vessels (mainly famous Máo gōng dǐng) document that the rulers of Máo hold high positions in the Zhōu royal bureaucracy. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-a00adcf5-aab4-4d21-a559-5cfdaab41caa"><form corresp="#uuid-593cdf08-9470-4aae-9c30-a98bca4fce9c">
<orth>江</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jiāng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">krooŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣɔŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a7af342f-4088-499c-a446-a7cc817c0552">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Jiāng 江 (CHEN PAN 1969, 571-575)Ruling clan: Yíng 嬴 (according to the Qín běnjì chapter of the Shǐ jì, and to the Shǔi jīng zhù).Rank: Unknown.Founded: According to the Shǐ jì (Qín běnjì chapter), the rulers of Jiāng belonged to the branch lineage of the ruling clan of Qín 秦.Destroyed: In 623 B.C. (Wen 4) by Chǔ 楚. Location: Uncertain. According to the Du Yu's commentary, Xù jùn guó zhì zhù etc., the state was located in the modern Xī 息 district (Taiwanese Zhèngyáng 正陽 district), Henan province.History: The state for the first time appears in CQ and ZUO in the entry for Xi 2 (658 B.C.).</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-60959c3a-e3d6-4e20-8a04-0821ed481c1d"><form corresp="#uuid-8b8528e1-67ae-4d12-8a9d-a41de3411d7b">
<orth>滑</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">huá</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡruud</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɣɛt</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-337a2b12-0dcb-44f7-8cd4-3dddf44cde42">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Huá 滑 (also called Bì [Fèi?] Huá 費滑 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 516-518)Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the ZUO, Xiang 19). Rank: Bó 伯.Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: In 627 B.C. (Xi 33) by Qín 秦. Thereafter, the area came under the control of Jìn 晉; in 574 B.C. (Cheng 17), it was occupied by Zhèng 鄭, and then it came to Zhōu 周. Location: In the modern Yǎnshī 偃師 district, central Henan (according to the Du's commentary to the ZUO). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-5dbedf32-b4ae-41a6-838d-600e14d84d4c"><form corresp="#uuid-6b1bfbc4-5a2e-4e61-9136-e958e2fb2d7a">
<orth>溫</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wēn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">quun</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔuo̝n</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f17b2989-15ff-42c4-9466-1810f9018af2">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Wēn 溫 (also called Sū 蘇 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 587-593)Ruling clan: Jǐ 己. Inscription on the Sū gōng guǐ 蘇公簋 mentions Wáng Jǐ 王己, the daughter of the Duke of Sū (Wēn).Rank: Zǐ 子 (common title of the rulers of Wēn in the CQ and ZUO). In the inscriptions on bronze vessels, rulers of Sū (Wēn) sometimes referred to themselves as gōng 公; it could have been in association with their high position in the Zhōu royal court.Founded: According to the Lì zhèng chapter of the Zhōu shū, the duke of Sū 蘇公 (who held a high position of Sī kòu 司寇, the minister of justice, in the Zhōu royal court) received his fief from King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王. However, the state perhaps existed for a long time before it (see History).Destroyed: In the early Chunqiu period, the state was not already in existence. In 712 B.C. (Yin 11), the king of Zhōu gave twelve fields of Sū Fèn Shēng 蘇忿生 (including the city of Wēn) to the state of Zhèng 鄭. Later, the area again came under the royal control and the Sū lineage was reestablished in Wēn. In 650 B.C. (Xi 10), the state was destroyed by Dí 狄 barbarians. In 635 B.C., the city of Wēn was given by the Zhōu king to the Marquis Wén of Jìn 晉文公. However, in 617 B.C. (Wén 10), the ruler of Sū is mentioned again as participating in the meeting of the states held in Nǚlì 女栗. Location: In the modern Wēn 溫 district, Henan province (according to the Du's commentary).History: According to the Shì běn and Guó yǔ (Zhèng yǔ), the state was established very early by the descendants of the mythical emperor Zhū Róng 祝融 (bearing Jǐ 己 surname) and later it was destroyed by Xià 夏. The Current Zhūshū jìnián states that in the 33rd year of reign of the Xià ruler Dì Fēn 帝芬, the descendant of Kūn Wú 昆吾 (bearing Jǐ 己 surname) was established as a ruler of Yǒu Sū 有蘇. Guó yǔ (Jìn yǔ) mentions that the last king of Shāng 商, Dì Xīn 帝辛 or Zhòu 紂, attacked Yǒu Sū, and the ruler of that state gave him his daughter Dá Jǐ 妲己 (which was in later texts blamed for being one of the main reasons of the destruction of Shāng) as a consort. In the beginning of the Western Zhōu period, King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王 established his high official Duke of Sū as a ruler in Sū (Wēn). The rulers of Sū sometimes (usually?) held high positions in the Zhōu royal court; according to the Shì běn (quoted by Guǎng yùn), Chéng, the Duke of Sū 蘇成公, served in the Zhōu royal court during the reign of King Píng 周平王 (770-720 B.C.). Duke of Sū is also mentioned in the inscription on the Sū gōng guǐ. However, in 712 B.C., the state already did not exist (see section Destroyed).</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f0307ddd-444b-4554-b287-9c2c5cd0356d"><form corresp="#uuid-a2031609-27ec-4759-9770-99d3b4649cfb">
<orth>滕</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">téng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lɯɯŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dəŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-96111bd5-67b6-41d2-ae6c-1fdc48652f65">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a minor state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-e5eeaabf-3c31-4284-b3ee-ed9400caa1cf"><form corresp="#uuid-469a7f78-1e03-4675-bb6f-535f87df6708">
<orth>燕</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yān</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qeen</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔen</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-9fd5f771-34d1-4cf9-8351-090263dc0213">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-69005f9a-1daa-4392-ac3b-97b9791861b3"><form corresp="#uuid-4343a1ca-1070-42ba-b9ea-e49d224811a5">
<orth>牟</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">móu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">mu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">mɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-bde98079-8b66-4763-acbc-af643cd534fe">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Móu 牟 (also written as 侔; probably identical with Gēn Móu 根牟 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 492-496)Clan: Unknown. Rank: Uncertain. According to the Fēngsú tōng and Xìng yuàn, the rulers of Móu were of zǐ 子 rank.Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: Uncertain. Gēn Móu was conquered by Lǔ in 600 B.C. (Xuan 9; recorded in the CQ). However, Hòu Hàn Rú lín states that Móu was destroyed by Lǔ in the end of the Chunqiu period. Lù shǐ Guó míng jì mentions that Móu was conquered by Chǔ 楚. Location: Several locations of Móu were suggested by traditional Chinese historiography. According to the Hàn zhì, Shuǐ jīng Wènshuǐ zhù, Du's commentary to the ZUO, and to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, Móu was located in the modern Láiwú 萊蕪 district, Shandong province. Tōng diǎn locates it into the modern Pénglái 蓬萊 district in the same province, and Tōng zhì into the Móupíng 牟平 district of the same province. Other place names associated with Móu are found in the Yíshuǐ 沂水 district and Ānqiū 安丘 district. It is difficult to decide which of these opinions is correct (the state could shift several times); at least, it is certain that Móu was located somewhere in the neighborhood of Lǔ.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-d1eada57-a18c-4379-861e-aa3c451261b0"><form corresp="#uuid-7c01b4c0-ce62-4903-ac30-c986d64d44a6">
<orth>申</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shēn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lʰin</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-2824e92a-ee02-4674-bbc1-ecd2435b767c">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of She1n</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-a5b2ffc7-89fb-4496-90a5-cfa22d35da86"><form corresp="#uuid-77beb4e8-0ee5-4eeb-a5de-368437ce6c2c">
<orth>祭</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhài</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skreeds</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂɣɛi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3ce83b0e-b906-4130-ae76-81e327017a48">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Zhài 祭 (Sometimes written as Cài 蔡. Not to be confused with another, and more powerful, state of Cài) (CHEN PAN 1969, 294-301)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Bó 伯 (common in the CQ and ZUO).Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by one of the sons of Duke of Zhōu 周公 (according to the ZUO, Xi 24). Destroyed: Unknown. Location: According to the Dì míng kǎolyè, Zhài was located in the modern Zhèngzhōu 鄭州 area of central Henan.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-d4aa3a7b-72b5-4c14-8924-11e0a887cdcd"><form corresp="#uuid-df240981-b177-4217-80fc-52d29d96abd8">
<orth>秦</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">qín</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">dzin</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dzin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d7a1fd2d-8230-492d-98d2-1f0972ae7ebe">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state Qín was a semi-barbarian powerful western state, formally enfeoffed as one of the feudal lord states in the eighth century B.C., came to annex all the other states and created the first united Chinese empire in 221 B.C.. For the history of the capitals see Qū 1991: 159-208.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-56e86f40-767a-4545-a310-ecd46b3126e6"><form corresp="#uuid-2505e2ba-46ac-4f8a-acb2-855aaa26c1af">
<orth>管</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">guǎn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">koonʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kʷɑn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b383f561-59f0-48b1-abb7-02bea81900af">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-ac1e573f-0129-4431-904e-7ee59f2150cf"><form corresp="#uuid-04e24902-331e-4916-ab69-d0c44ca12454">
<orth>紀</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jì</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kɯʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɨ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d5f1f159-2129-47ad-b866-467281b1c507">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Jǐ 紀 (also written - mainly on the bronzes - as 己 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 328-332)Clan: Jiāng 姜.Rank: Hóu 侯 (used in the CQ and ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts, the rulers of Jǐ are sometimes referred to as bó 伯.Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: In 690 B.C. (Zhuang 4) by Qí 齊. Location: In the modern Shòuguāng 壽光 district, Shandong province (according to the Shuǐ jīng zhù, Kuò dì zhì, Dì míng kǎolyè, etc.). Note that some bronzes found in that area and dating from the Late Shāng period were inscribed with Jǐ character. History: The state of Jǐ was rather small and weak. During the reign of the Zhōu King Yí 周夷王, the ruler of Jǐ slandered Duke Āi of Qí 齊哀公 to the King, who in turn had the Duke boiled alive. This incident (recorded in the Zhúshū jǐnián) was later used by Qí as an excuse for its attacks on Jǐ. Jǐ allied against Qí with the states of Zhèng 鄭 and Lǔ 魯, and in 699 B.C. (Huan 13) this alliance managed to defeat the alliance led by Qí (and consisting of Sòng 宋, Wèi 衛, and Nán Yàn 南燕 ); however, Jǐ was eventually conquered by Qí in 690 B.C. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-16c71f7c-d5d7-4c1d-9931-53ceddad11d9"><form corresp="#uuid-f32ad93d-c477-4962-ac38-5ebf1f4bbf44">
<orth>絞</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jiǎo</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kreewʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣɛu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-be06552d-cf7d-4747-916e-b46bdba88723">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Jiǎo 絞 (maybe identical with Jiāo 交 of the inscriptions on the bronzes; also written as Jiǎo 佼 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 477-480)Clan: Unknown. According to the Xìng xī and Lù shǐ Hòu jì, the rulers of Jiǎo were of Yǎn 偃 surname. Rank: Unknown. Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: After its defeat by Chǔ 楚 in 700 B.C. (Huan 12), Jiǎo does not appear in the CQ and ZUO. In an unknown period, it was annexed by Chǔ. Location: According to the Dìlì kǎo shí and other sources, the state of Jiǎo was located in modern Yún 溳 district, northern Hubei province.  A town of the same name (mentioned in the ZUO under Ai 2 - 493 B.C.) existed in modern Shandong and belonged to the state of Zhū 邾. Jiāo 交 of the bronze inscriptions, which are found on the artifacts cast in the eastern states, was perhaps this Shandong Jiǎo 絞. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-856f85c7-baa3-4b1b-8868-23a5c48ff3d4"><form corresp="#uuid-73b6e4e2-147a-4ead-8d0b-386283e2a333">
<orth>羅</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">luó</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">b-raal</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">lɑ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-02d7d392-b9ea-49f8-b385-b26f739a1519">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Luó 羅 (CHEN PAN 1969, 487-490)Clan: Probably Xióng 熊 (according to the Shì běn, Du's commentary, and to the Tōng zhì). According to the Xìng xī, the rulers of Luó belonged to the Yún 妘 clan. Rank: Unknown. According to the Shuǐ jīng zhù and Xìng xī, the rulers of Luó were of hóu 侯 rank. According to the Hàn zhì and Tōng diǎn, they had zǐ 子 rank.Founded: Unknown. According to the Shì běn, the rulers of Luó were of the Chǔ 楚 clan Xióng 熊. Destroyed: After 699 B.C. (Huan 13), Luó does not appear in the CQ and ZUO. In 635 B.C. (Xi 25), the area already belonged to Chǔ 楚.Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, to the Shuǐ jīng Jiāng shuǐ zhù, and to the Tōng zhì Shìzú kǎolyè, Luó was located in the modern Yíchéng 宜城 district in the northern part of Hubei. According to the same sources, it later shifted to Zhījiāng 枝江. After its defeat by Chǔ, King Wén of Chǔ 楚文王 (689-677 B.C.) is said to shift it to the area of the modern Luó district in the neighborhood of Chángshā 長沙, Hunan province (what is stated in the Hàn zhì and Shuǐ jīng zhù). However, I found this statement late and rather problematic, because it is by no means certain that in that early period Chǔ had a control over this remote area. But probably by the end of the Warring states period, Luó was located in the area of Chángshā, as is mentioned in the Tōng zhì. History: Luó was a small and unimportant state, which is remarkable only for its victory over the invading Chǔ army in 699 B.C. (Huan 13).</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f5a22f5b-8da9-4477-b0f1-6eb359b46a43"><form corresp="#uuid-3bb45186-8e82-4097-81a9-03b542817dbb">
<orth>耿</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">gěng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kreeŋʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣɛŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-26192ac6-25b2-4688-83a4-8c38fbefd508">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Gěng 耿 (CHEN PAN 1969, 560-562)Ruling clan: Jī 姬 (according to the Jìn shìjiā jí jiě and to the Du's commentary), or Yíng 嬴 (according to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, Dūchéng jì, and Jùn guó zhì).Rank: Unknown.Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: 661 B.C. by Jìn 晉 (ZUO Min 1).Location: In the south-eastern part of the modern Héjīn 河津 district, Shānxī province.History: A small state destroyed by Jìn. Thereafter, the area became a fief of the Zhào 趙 lineage.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-915ecaf9-938a-48d6-ab98-15ba9b1c84fb"><form corresp="#uuid-e94e9acb-76d1-4687-a34f-cc7246095797">
<orth>聃</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">dān</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">nʰaam</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">thɑm</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-8bfe1533-313e-4842-a63a-a6a35d2855e1">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Dān 聃 (also written as Rǎn 冉, Nán 南, Dān 耽 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 647-650)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Unknown.Founded: According to the Xìng jiě, the first ruler of Dān was Jì Zài 季載, the son of the Zhōu king Wén 周文王. Destroyed: Unknown. According to the traditional Chinese historiography, Dān was conquered either by Chǔ 楚 or Zhèng 鄭 (the latter opinion seems to be more probable; see Location). Location: Unknown. According to some opinions, the former capital of Dān was Nàchù 那處, which is mentioned in the ZUO (Zhuang 18; 676 B.C.) as belonging to Chǔ; if so, the former state of Dān must have been located somewhere in the neighborhood of Chǔ. In the ZUO, Xi 2 (658 B.C.), there is mentioned Zhèng 鄭 aristocrat Dān bó 聃伯, what would point to the fact that Dān was conquered by Zhèng and that it was located somewhere in the area of the latter state; Dì lǐ kǎo shí locates it into the area of modern Kāifēng 開封. This opinion seems more probable than the location of Dān to the neighborhood of Chǔ. Guǎng yùn mentions that the first fief of Dān was in the area of the western Zhōu royal capital, close to the modern Xī'ān 西安. This opinion sounds quite reasonable. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-9b83136b-e343-4d47-a08c-916948a5fe31"><form corresp="#uuid-bd2177c1-35ad-42b6-9595-bf6a59c5694e">
<orth>胡</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">hú</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡaa</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦuo̝</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ecee4449-9358-4a63-ba6f-69bdfa047b33">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>state of Hú</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-c590f12f-4f50-466b-a6c2-79c0469b9cfb"><form corresp="#uuid-d9bca30d-016b-41a6-8420-39aad90b5594">
<orth>舒</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shū</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lʰa</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕi̯ɤ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-bac3f8df-ca2c-48e1-9e14-543fb6f0ebeb">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Shu1</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-05d3d9ee-3369-4436-8a5f-b2f1bcf26a0e"><form corresp="#uuid-4553d2aa-5d96-44fc-8b18-c4158c427118">
<orth>芮</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">ruì</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">njobs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ȵiɛi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-69537f24-6170-49d4-b5c4-c32aa2fa87d7">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Ruī 芮 (also written as 汭; in the bronze inscriptions, it appears as Nèi 內 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 399-407)Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the Shì běn; in the inscription on the Ly wáng hú is mentioned the woman called Nèi Jī 內姬 ).Rank: Bó 伯 (usual in the ZUO).Founded: The state was obviously established quite early in the Western Zhōu period, as in the Gùmìng chapter of the Shū jīng the Earl of Rùi 芮伯 is listed among the persons which attended the Zhōu King Chéng 周成王 in his deathbed. Destroyed: In 640 B.C. (Xi 20) by Qín 秦 (according to the Shǐ jì, Shíèr zhūhóu niánbiǎo and Qín běnjì chapters).Location: According to the Hàn zhì, the state of Ruī was located in the modern Dàlì 大荔 district, Shǎnxī province. Dì míng kǎolyè locates it into the modern Cháoyì 朝邑 district, neighboring with Dàlì district. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-1d5b834e-92c8-4699-9b0d-43be45dce328"><form corresp="#uuid-64506f24-df36-493f-8481-f60ab5bbb0e5">
<orth>荀</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xún</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sqʷlin</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">sʷin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f5d928bb-0a96-4f88-a7b7-1d984bde032e">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xún 荀 (also written as 郇; on the bronzes as 旬 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 454-456)Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the ZUO, Huan 9).Rank: Hóu 侯 (mentioned in the ZUO, Huan 9; in the Máo shī zhuàn; and also in the inscriptions on the bronzes). In Máo shī (Cáo fēng, Xià quán), in the Current Zhū shū jǐnián, and also in some of the inscriptions on the bronzes, the ruler of Xún is also referred to as bó 伯.Founded: The state was obviously already in existence by the Early Western Zhōu period, as in the Wáng huì chapter of the Yì Zhōu shū, Xúnshū 荀叔 is mentioned together with the Duke of Zhōu 周公, Tài gōng 太公, and Kāngshū 康叔. According to the ZUO (Xi 24) and to the Máo shī jiān, the first ruler of Xún (probably identical with the above mentioned Xúnshū) was the son of Zhōu king Wén 周文王. Destroyed: The state is mentioned in the ZUO for 703 B.C. (Huan 9), and then for 636 B.C. (Xi 24). Later, it was destroyed by Jìn 晉. Location: In the area of modern Línyī 臨猗, Shānxī province (according to the Chūnqīu dì míng kǎolyè). History: After the conquest of Xún, the state of Jìn 晉 gave the area as a fief to the Jìn aristocrat Yuánshì Àn 原氏黯, thereafter known as Xúnshū 荀叔. He founded the Xún 荀 lineage (also known as the Zhōngháng 中行 lineage), which was one of the most powerful lineages in Jìn till its final anihilation in the civil war between 497-490 B.C. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f7e30a9d-e613-4ddf-a49c-c33d7d5e489d"><form corresp="#uuid-5b645e44-a1b9-4ba1-bd03-0a684d705f01">
<orth>荊</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jīng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kreŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣaŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f08f52fb-dcfb-4478-9485-bef78867394e">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a city and of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-7699351a-2fab-41c2-a11b-c9b3b80f256a"><form corresp="#uuid-d41a011b-349c-408a-94dd-4806ee5ca811">
<orth>莒</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jǔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">klaʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ki̯ɤ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-9199601d-0a71-42e7-9e07-5284de3f4770">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-56940778-e863-4e3a-b9de-9abfa7aaf41b"><form corresp="#uuid-77335a96-f734-4ac4-b53c-29bd18b9719d">
<orth>萊</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">lái</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">rɯɯ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ləi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-48c8fda4-76af-438d-9b97-667b3e126500">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Lái 萊 (also written as 來, 斄, 郲, 斄, Lí 釐; also called Lái Yí 萊夷, Yí Lái 夷萊, or Lái Yú 萊魚 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 775-786)Clan: Uncertain. On the basis of the ZUO's record for 571 B.C. (Xiang 2), it is supposed that the rulers of Lái were of Jiāng 姜 surname. However, the record is rather problematic. It states that when the consort of the lord of Lǔ 魯 who was of Qí 齊 origin and had thus Jiāng surname (in the text, she is called Qí Jiāng 齊姜 ) died, the lord of Qí called other women of Jiāng surname and those married to the aristocrats of Jiāng surname ( 諸姜宗婦 ) to attend the burial. He also called the viscount of Lái, but that did not come. It is not clear whether the ruler of Lái really had Jiāng surname or was just married to the women of that surname. It is even by no means certain that calling of the participants in the burial on the one hand, and that of the viscount of Lái on the other, were related. According to the Shì běn, to the Shǐ jì (Qí shìjiā), and to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì, the rulers of Lái were affiliated to the Shāng 商 kings and had Zǐ 子 surname. With regard to the fact that Lái is mentioned as a place name already in the oracle bone inscriptions, and that in the early Western Zhōu period it was obviously the non-Zhōu state acting as an enemy of Qí, this opinion seems to me to be more probable. Rank: Zǐ 子 (appears in the ZUO, Xiang 2). In the area of Shandong, there were in the Antiquity place-names containing component Lái wáng 來王 (according to the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì); it is possible that the rulers of Lái also referred to themselves as wáng, as was the case of some non-Zhōu states. In the Shǐ jì (Qí shìjiā), the ruler of Lái is referred to as hóu 侯. In the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts, rulers of Lái are sometimes referred to as bó 伯. Founded: According to the Shì běn, to the Shǐ jì (Qí shìjiā), and to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì, the rulers of Lái were relatives of the Shāng dynasty. Lái was obviously a non-Zhōu state probably closely associated with the Shāng. Destroyed: In 567 B.C. (Xiang 6) by Qí 齊.Location: In modern Shandong, to the East of Qí, but the precise location of the state is uncertain. According to the Kùo dì zhì and to the Du's commentary, the centre of Lái was located in the modern Huáng 黃 district in the northeastern part of Shandong.History: Lái was an ancient state which preserved its independence on the Zhōu realm late into the Chunqiu period. Its inhabitants belonged to the Dōng Yí 東夷 and were obviously in some way associated with the Shāng. According to the Shǐ jì (Qí shìjiā), when the state of Qí was established in the beginning of the Western Zhōu period, its capital was attacked by the Marquis of Lái 來侯. Eventually, Lái was conquered by Qí in 567 B.C. Which was the relationship of this Lái and Lái 來 mentioned as a place-name in the oracle bone inscriptions is not clear. Note that the place-name Lái 來 (or Shí Lái 時來 ) later existed also in the state of Zhèng 鄭 (CQ, Yin 11). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-9a19433b-c70a-4da4-a303-2ad298c9bb05"><form corresp="#uuid-25cf6b80-d173-408c-9b15-04c0cd4a6b5e">
<orth>葛</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">gé</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kaad</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɑt</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a8b0a31f-9f02-425b-b36b-30885427867d">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>name of an ancient state in today's Hénán with ruling clan 嬴</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-8ccc2f5b-094a-4161-8f24-c640210051b7"><form corresp="#uuid-8a88cf03-d448-461d-848a-ee4559411425">
<orth>蔡</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">cài</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhaads</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tshɑi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1f25cbfc-2820-4615-99f7-14831834e834">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-9f55a3db-b303-40ae-8ac3-ad3d62fee023"><form corresp="#uuid-e2ab7755-0ba5-457d-b689-ffa27449af28">
<orth>蓼</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">liǎo</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡ-rɯɯwʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">leu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ea31aa95-c554-4ece-8d85-0e01ee543fa2">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Liǎo 蓼 (also written as Liáo 飂 / 飉 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 484-486)Clan: Unknown. According to the tradition recorded in the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, Lù shǐ Hòu jì, and in the Qián fū lún, the rulers of Liǎo were descendents of the mythical Zhù Róng 祝融, and had Jǐ 己 surname. However, this is maybe legendary tradition, as Lùshǐ Hòu jì states that this Liǎo was destroyed by the Xià 夏 dynasty. Rank: Unknown.Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: Mentioned in the ZUO in the record for 701 B.C. Later (in an unknown period), it was conquered by Chǔ 楚.Location: In the modern Tánghé 唐河 district, Henan province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-2f20d2c6-b8e3-407f-a75d-e5aef5a8fcc7"><form corresp="#uuid-f6cb19ff-1183-4fd6-84e5-458da05b24ad">
<orth>蕭</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xiāo</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sɯɯw</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">seu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-7d53eeaa-d19c-4696-95d6-1dde86f0bb0e">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xiāo 蕭 (CHEN PAN 1969, 508-511)Clan: Zǐ 子 (according to the Yīn shìjiā chapter of the Shǐ jì, to the Hàn zhì, and to the Shì běn).Rank: Dependent state of Sòng 宋. Founded: The founder of the state was the Sòng noble Xiāoshū Dàxīn 蕭叔大心, who received his fief from the ruler of Sòng. According to some later sources (Xīn Táng shū and Guǎng yùn), Xiāoshū Dàxīn 蕭叔大心 was identical with Lè Dàxīn 樂大心 (the descendent of the Duke Dài of Sòng 宋戴公; 799-766 B.C.), and received his fief as a reward for his suppression of Nángōng Wàn 南宮萬 rebellion in 582 B.C. However, there are problems with this statement, because Lè Dàxīn appears in the ZUO in the entries for 535 B.C. (Zhao 7) and 501 B.C. (Ding 9). On the other hand, it cannot be excluded that there were two (or more) persons of this name. Destroyed: In 597 B.C. (Xuan 12) by Chǔ 楚. Later, the area became the part of Sòng.Location: According to the Hàn zhì, the state of Xiāo was located in the modern Xiāo 蕭 district, Anhui province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-4bdadfb6-2afe-4525-b490-ea3e27b91447"><form corresp="#uuid-869d8833-2be2-4eec-89c9-4d4fc574aadb">
<orth>薛</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xuē</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sŋed</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">siɛt</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-16c15a38-5094-418c-a120-d119ddf47aa3">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a small state, became part of Qí</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-fba32c1b-d79e-4921-9a63-2b4d428815aa"><form corresp="#uuid-3058951c-4ea7-4eff-8026-e1722efc9190">
<orth>虞</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yú</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋʷa</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋi̯o</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0119f134-0b44-4096-9400-8b51d60c831f">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-8f360c6f-89f6-4bc5-a698-5433c407d3b2">place</tls:sem-feat></gramGrp>
  <def>Name of state, brother state of Wú, destroyed in 655.</def></sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6673d17c-09cf-405d-923a-0c388e5848e8">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-b62c8bf7-d208-4867-b661-f667a000a08e">"dynasty"</tls:sem-feat></gramGrp>
  <def>also referred to as 虞氏</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-eac5874f-7d9f-4c74-b0cb-be81f8ad8fb9"><form corresp="#uuid-65c6750a-7699-4de6-8753-ffc5ad4175c2">
<orth>虢</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">guó</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kʷraaɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣɛk</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-81354737-df69-422c-b39b-4bd2551c6c36">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Name of an archeologically very important state, destroyed in 656 BC.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-d5fdf205-ec6f-439c-8b12-ed6335f5ceb3"><form corresp="#uuid-73ad8278-86ef-4686-9c35-c03cf37194aa">
<orth>衛</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wèi</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢods</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦiɛi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-5ec50ad2-9289-4d74-ba32-69b09faa81be">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-758dc67c-f351-4b6e-9705-40b16d7b1457"><form corresp="#uuid-cea102cd-f4c1-4145-8afa-fcbd88ec12f1">
<orth>許</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xǔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">hŋaʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">hi̯ɤ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0aaa0122-bb1e-4dd5-88e5-b0c4f34e42e4">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xǔ 許 (in the bronze inscriptions written as 鄦 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 285-290)Clan: Jiāng 姜.Rank: Nán 男 (common in the CQ). In the bronze inscriptions, the rulers of Xǔ are referred to as zǐ 子.Founded: According to the tradition (mentioned in the Zhèng yǔ section of the Guó yǔ and in the ZUO under Yin 11), the founder of Xǔ was Bóyí 伯夷, the descendant of the mythical Tài Yuè 太岳 (or Sì Yùe 四岳 ). Destroyed: Xǔ was still in existence by the end of the period recorded in CQ, and was destroyed during Zhanguo period probably by Chǔ 楚 (according to the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì). However, HFZ mentions that Xǔ was conquered by Wèi 魏. Location: According to the ZUO, the capital of Xǔ shifted several times during the Chunqiu period. The first capital called Xǔ 許 was (according to the Dìmíng kǎolyè) located in the modern Xǔchāng 許昌, Henan province. In 576 B.C. (Cheng 15), during the reign of the duke Líng of Xǔ 許靈公, it shifted to Yè 葉 (modern Yè 葉 district, Henan province), then (during the reign of Duke Dào 許悼公 ), in 533 B.C. (Zhao 9) to Yí 夷, in 524 (Zhao 18) to Báiyǔ 白羽 in the area of the Xiāng 鄉 district in Nányáng 南陽, and in 506 B.C. (Ding 4) to Róngchéng 容城 (location highly uncertain).History: Xǔ was a small state, which is mentioned for the first time in the CQ and ZUO in the record for 712 B.C. (Yin 11). Since the beginning, it was exposed to the attacks of its more powerful neighbors, and in the same year, it was even conquered by Zhèng 鄭. However, the state was re-established later, and it is mentioned again in CQ for 702 B.C. In 531 B.C., Xǔ was annexed by Chǔ, but was again re-established two years later. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-18e32262-4c68-4cfe-8280-6b5e92540b52"><form corresp="#uuid-9c09b7db-b55c-444b-9628-f77d868a1134">
<orth>譚</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">tán</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡ-luum</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dəm</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-cd41cf6b-5404-4952-8d68-18e29ada0fba">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Tán 譚 (also written as 覃 or 郯 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 505-507)Clan: Unknown. According to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì and Hòu jì, the rulers of Tán belonged to the Yíng 嬴 clan; on the contrary, Gu's Chūnqiū dà shì biǎo states that they were of Zǐ 子 surname. Rank: Zǐ 子 (appears in the both CQ and ZUO in the entry for Zhuang 10).Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: In 684 B.C. (Zhuang 10) by Qí 齊.Location: According to the Du's commentary, Tán was located in the area of modern Jìnán 濟南, Shandong province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-e325f4dd-d54d-4173-9f56-a7762ae222fe"><form corresp="#uuid-b1fb13df-3e69-44de-9165-932760aed399">
<orth>貳</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">èr</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">njis</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ȵi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-23de3472-778a-494a-b964-d438a0a9c9b6">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Èr 貳 (CHEN PAN 1969, 465-466)Clan: Unknown. According to the Xìng xī, the rulers of Èr were of Jī 姬 surname. On the contrary, Lù shǐ Hòu jǐ suggests that they belonged to the Yǎn 偃 clan. Rank: Unknown.Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: Unknown. The state is mentioned in the ZUO for the year 701 B.C. (Huan 11). Later, it was destroyed by Chǔ 楚.Location: In the modern Guǎngshuǐ 廣水, Hubei province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-07e6d23a-8b60-429e-ae35-d0c26ef55942"><form corresp="#uuid-d3c2bf49-54bf-49e0-8195-98b1bf32343f">
<orth>賈</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jiǎ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kraaʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣɛ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6bd6c1ce-eb19-47fe-a33d-c93ba32099bc">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Jiǎ 賈 (CHEN PAN 1969, 457-458)Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the Zuǒzhuàn zhēngyì quoting Shì běn, and to the Du's commentary to the ZUO). Rank: Bó 伯 (according to the ZUO, Huan 9). Founded: Uncertain. According to the Xìng yuàn, Tōng zhì shì zú kǎo lyè, and to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, the first ruler of Jiǎ was Gōng Míng 公明, the son of Tángshū Yú 唐叔虞 (the founder of the state of Jìn 晉 ), who received his fief from the Zhōu king Kāng 周康王. Destroyed: The state is mentioned for 703 B.C. (Huan 9) in the ZUO. Thereafter, in an unknown period, it was conquered by Jìn 晉. Location: In the modern Xiāngfén 襄汾 district, southwestern Shānxī (according to the Xù Hàn Jùn guó zhì). History: A small and unimportant state mentioned only one time in the ZUO. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-e4279051-c00d-432f-8ce8-7429ebf839e3"><form corresp="#uuid-7579b6ac-7ba1-4727-b63a-269db5dbeca0">
<orth>賴</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">lài</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">b-raads</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">lɑi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-8b292fdd-c401-47e1-89de-33526d9b4260">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Lài 賴 (probably identical with Lì 厲; see Lì 厲) (CHEN PAN 1969, 491)</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-17d75608-0ece-4e03-856b-1449d6df938d"><form corresp="#uuid-3139f0f4-7da9-4541-afd4-6a412a0a7304">
<orth>越</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yuè</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢʷad</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦi̯ɐt</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-550e0f56-bde6-4f0e-931d-e21f4fddd234">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">5</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-75fabdd0-bb95-48d5-ba7f-6867ae4858a2"><form corresp="#uuid-95cccfbd-389e-4e95-970c-f2b468ef2439">
<orth>趙</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhào</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">rlewʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖiɛu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ca01fdd1-f56b-4120-84bc-6203d035c9fa">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-40df8939-0b1a-4ff8-82ac-8d37a1497c4a">
<gramGrp><pos/>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-2dc23af9-ac81-4a01-9bf7-0f6644145476">npr{2}</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def/></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-a03591c1-6d9e-43c6-b34a-d902c9bb97bb"><form corresp="#uuid-824e249f-a343-4038-9f13-311e247af9e3">
<orth>軫</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhěn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kljɯnʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1227bc58-1c41-4072-8a95-c5c4ee85fc6b">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Zhěn 軫 (CHEN PAN 1969, 467-468)Clan: Unknown. According to the Xìng xī, the rulers of Zhěn were of Yǎn 偃 surname.Rank: Unknown.Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: Mentioned in the ZUO in the entry for 701 B.C. (Huan 11). Later, it was destroyed by Chǔ 楚.Location: According to the Dì míng kǎolyè, the state of Zhěn was located in the modern Yīngchéng 應城 district, Hubei province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-7cdb8936-9056-4e1a-8ba6-aedf7161099d"><form corresp="#uuid-012329d2-8a81-4a4f-ac3a-03885a49d6d6">
<orth>道</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">dào</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡ-luuʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dɑu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a5d543e3-042f-452b-9add-073afb85d6a4">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Da4o</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-6b8177b8-672f-41a8-afe7-20f9c7c35d7b"><form corresp="#uuid-555619ec-d99e-4b55-98eb-7fcd92550c3a">
<orth>邃</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">suì</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sqluds</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">si</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f9eb18e1-fed0-4577-b2be-6a024d9410c0">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Suì 遂 (also written as 隧 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 512-515)Clan: According to the ZUO (Zhao 3, 8), rulers of Suì were supposed to be descendents of the mythical Emperor Shùn 舜, and should thus have been of Guī 媯 surname. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì, there were two states of Suì: one with the surname Guī and another belonging to the Jī 姬 clan. Rank: Unknown.Founded: According to the tradition recorded in the ZUO (Zhao 3, 8) the rulers of Suì were descendents of Shùn, and they were given their surname by the Zhōu kings. Du's commentary states that the fief in Suì was given to the descendants of Shùn by the Shāng 商 kings. Destroyed: According to the CQ, Suì was conquered by Qí 齊 in 681 B.C. (Zhuang 13). The different story is given in the Shǐ jì (Qí shìjiā and Cìkè zhuàn), which says that in that year, Lǔ gave the city of Suì to Qí. With regard to the latter statement, some traditional Chinese scholars suggested that the state of Suì was already prior to 681 B.C. conquered by Lǔ 魯.Location: According to the Hàn zhì, Suì was located in the modern Níngyáng 寧陽 district, Shandong province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-d2cfb277-c36d-46bc-b200-de369c57bda8"><form corresp="#uuid-f94552f5-9ddf-494c-95a0-9ea05d5ac941">
<orth>邢</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xíng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡeeŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦeŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-605e9894-a837-4b79-ba34-a77c1f2b27a0">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xíng 邢 (maybe identical with Jǐng 井 in the inscriptions on the bronzes) (CHEN PAN 1969, 360-368)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Hóu 侯 (in the CQ and the ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronzes, rulers of Jǐng 井 refer to themselves as gōng 公 or bó 伯. Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by the fourth son of the Duke of Zhōu 周公 (according to the Tōng zhì Shì zú lyè; Chūnqiū dì míng kǎolyè quotes Shǐ jì, which says that the name of the son of the Duke of Zhōu enfeoffed by the Zhōu king Chéng 周成王 as a ruler of Xíng was Jìngyuān 靖淵. The sentence is missing in the current text of the Shǐ jì).Destroyed: In 635 B.C. (Xi 25) by Wèi 衛. Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, the capital of Xíng was located in the modern Xíngtái 邢臺 district, southern part of Hebei province. However, other sources suggested other locations, mainly the modern Wēn 溫 district in the Henan province, where the first capital of Xíng, called Xíngqiū 邢丘 should have been located (Shuō wén jiě zì; Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì, Xù Hàn shū Jùn guó zhì). This fits quite well with the record that in 718 B.C. (Yin 5), Xíng together with Zhèng supported the Earl of Qūwò 曲沃 in his attack on Yì 翼, the capital of Jìn 晉 located in the southwestern part of Shānxī province. However, in 661 B.C. (Min 1), when Xíng was attacked by the Dí 狄 barbarians, and was given a support from Qí 齊 and Cáo 曹, the state must have been located already in their close neighborhood, apparently in the modern Xíngtái 邢臺. Then the capital of Xíng shifted to the East of the Yellow River, to the Yíyí 夷儀, probably located in the modern Liáochéng 聊城 district in the western part of the Shandong province (according to Gāo Shìqí). History: Note that the state(s) and place(s) called Jǐng 井 and/or Xíng 邢 existed already in the Late Shāng period. Jǐng fāng 井方 is mentioned in the oracle bone inscriptions; Shǐ jì (Yīn běnjì) records that Xíng 邢 was one of the Shāng capitals (under king Zǔ Yǐ 祖乙 ), and Dìwáng shìjì mentions that the Marquis of Xíng 邢侯 was one of the three high officials in the court of the last Shāng king (however, one should not give much confidence to the last source). Which was the connection between those and the later Zhōu state of Xíng is difficult to decide. In this context it is interesting, that in the site of Xíngtái 邢臺, Hebei province, the continuous settlement dating from the Late Shāng to the Chunqiu period was attested. Note also the inscription on the bronze vessel belonging to the Marquis of Xíng, which can point to the fact that the Xíng was formerly quite strong state. However, in 661 B.C., it was almost exterminated by the Dí barbarians, and in the following year, its capital was shifted under the aegis of Qí to Yíyí (which was one year later fortified by the armies of Qí and Cáo). In 635 B.C., the state was annihilated by Wèi. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-824aa10f-13a4-4610-bc0b-6e6bc7f161c1"><form corresp="#uuid-179f8abc-3a9c-478b-a52a-34925f7f8cb8">
<orth>邠</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">bīn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">prɯn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">pin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0913020c-c519-4a22-809d-ad122375813a">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>small ancient state in today's Shǎnxī</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-b3440883-9bec-4ae3-8339-b8dbfd938758"><form corresp="#uuid-6138cebe-22d3-4bab-babb-202d3f0b13ef">
<orth>邾</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhū</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">to</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈi̯o</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4b68ee72-8ab6-4266-ad0a-a503ec132a33">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Zhu1</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f4e80393-84a9-4022-811f-75f43dea759c"><form corresp="#uuid-e40f1eb5-0ac8-4609-b8c0-698b3762798d">
<orth>郕</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chéng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">djeŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dʑiɛŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e5366ec5-2b3c-4dce-b3eb-c344761e956c">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Chéng 郕 (also written as 成, or 盛; also called Chéngyáng 郕陽 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 369-374)Clan: Jī 姬. Rank: Bó 伯 (occurs in the both CQ and ZUO under Wen 12). Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by Shūwǔ 叔武, the son of the Zhōu King Wén 周文王 (according to the Shǐ jì, Guǎn Cài shìjiā chapter). Destroyed: Unknown. In 686 B.C. (Zhuang 8), the state surrendered to Qí 齊, but the rulers of Chéng are again mentioned in 578 B.C. (Cheng 13) and in 502 B.C. (Dìng 8). By that period, Chéng was still in existence.Location: Uncertain. Several locations of Chéng were suggested by traditional Chinese historiography, all within the area of the western Shandong: in the modern Wènshàng 汶上 (Shāndōng tú jīng), Níngyáng 寧陽 (Dì míng kǎolyè based on the Du's commentary), or in the southeastern part of the modern Pú 濮 district, where the later capital Chéngyáng 成陽 should have been located (Kuò dì zhì; Huán yǔ jì). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-59441e44-4a4d-44a5-aff5-ade686cc480d"><form corresp="#uuid-8a5310e9-d5ae-4861-a79b-9b75432f34fe">
<orth>郜</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">gào</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kuuɡs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɑu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4391c6d2-ca0d-47e0-a5f3-efa3cf68f714">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Gào 郜 (also written as 告 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 391-397)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the CQ).Founded: In the early Western Zhōu period by one of the sons of the Zhōu King Wén 周文王 (according to the Shì běn).Destroyed: Unknown. There are only three references to Gào in the CQ. In 713 B.C. (Yin 10), Lǔ 魯 conquered a city of Gào 郜, which belonged to Sòng 宋. Record for 710 B.C. (Huan 2) says that Lǔ 魯 received a bronze tripod of Gào (Gào dǐng 郜鼎 ) from the state of Sòng. Record for 640 B.C. (Xi 20) refers to the formal visit of the viscount of Gào 郜子 in the court of Lǔ. On the basis of this records, traditional Chinese scholars basically divided into two camps, as one regards the extermination of Gào: one suggested that Gào was conquered by Sòng already prior to the period recorded in the CQ (and Sòng thus got its ritual artifacts), and that its ruler who paid a visit to the Lǔ court was a ruler who lost his state (note a long time which passed between these events); the second propose that the cauldron got to Sòng not by conquest, and that the state of Gào was still in existence by 640 B.C. The record for 713 B.C. would support the first probability, but only if the city of Gào taken by Lǔ was identical with the former capital of the state of Gào, what is not certain (Du's commentary supposes it. On the contrary, Fàn zhì states that later, there were two places of this name distant one from the other about 20 miles; according to the text, one was formerly the capital of Gào and another belonged to Sòng). Generally, it seems to me more probable, that there were two places of this name, and that by 640 B.C., the state of Gào was still in existence. Location: According to the Du's commentary and to the Fàn zhì, the capital of Gào was located in the modern Chéngwǔ 城武 district, Shandong province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-b9cb48ef-2132-4b77-948a-efec647dc832"><form corresp="#uuid-2f3b2c04-8145-4ef3-b351-32654e3e6336">
<orth>郭</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">guō</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kʷaaɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɑk</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3112925c-8b9b-4a07-aa18-aa9c43aa1ffe">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Guō 郭 (CHEN PAN 1969, 525-534)Clan: Unknown.Rank: Unknown. In the CQ, Zhuang 24 (670 B.C.), the ruler of Guō is referred to as gōng 公. In the inscription on the Guō bó guǐ 郭伯簋, the ruler of Guō is referred to as bó 伯. Founded: Unknown. The ruler of Guō (Guō bó) is mentioned in the bronze inscriptions dating from the early and middle period of the Western Zhōu; therefore, the state was already in existence by those times. Destroyed: Unknown. The ruler of Guō (Guō gōng) is mentioned only one time in the CQ (for Zhuang 24; 670 B.C.) in a very unclear context (the larger part of the sentence is obviously missing). According to the Du's commentary, it is a mistake; GONGYANG has suggested that the record refers to the ruler who prior to the date lost his state. Xīn xù (Zá shì chapter) records the story how Lord Huán of Qí 齊桓公 (685-643 B.C.) during a hunt passed the ruins of the Guō capital and asked about the reasons of its downfall. If we should give any credit to this story, by that time Guō already was not in existence. Location: Unknown. According to the later sources, mainly Zá shì chapter of the Xīn xù, the ruins of the capital of Guō were located somewhere in the neighborhood of Qí 齊. The Western Zhōu bronze inscriptions which mention the ruler of Guō (if it is identical with Guō mentioned in the CQ and later sources) also suggest its association with the eastern states.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-bacf73f7-4e1c-45a8-b482-ef4687bcfff5"><form corresp="#uuid-45bd18dc-a2ff-4393-bdd7-b0ad946c95e1">
<orth>鄖</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yún</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢun</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦi̯un</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f7a7f4fd-7766-487f-92f2-38cdeeade20b">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Yún 鄖 (also written as 云, 雲, 伝, 妘, 溳, 運, 員 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 469-476)Clan: Uncertain. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì and to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, the rulers of Yún belonged to the Yún 妘 clan. According to the Shì zú pǔ, they were of Yíng 嬴 surname. Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the ZUO, Xuān 4). Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: Unknown. In 584 B.C. (Cheng 7), the area of Yún already belonged to Chǔ 楚. Location: Uncertain. Several possible locations of the state were suggested by the traditional Chinese historiography. According to the Ménghuì tú, to the Shuǐ jīng Yúnshuǐ zhù, to the Yuánhé zhì, to the Tōng diǎn, and to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, Yún was located in the modern Ānlù 安陸 district, Hubei province. On the other hand, Hàn zhì, Dìlì zhì, and Yītǒng zhì suggested its location in the modern Yún 溳 district in the same province. Commentary to the Hàn zhì and commentary to the Xù Hàn shū Jūn guó zhì located it into the modern Jīngshān 京山 district, Hubei province. In any case, the state of Yún was located somewhere in the northern part of Hubei.It should be noted that there were more places of that name also in the Henan area (one in the state of Wèi 衛 ). The place name Yún already appears in the oracle bone inscriptions together with Hé 河 and Diàn 奠 (Zhèng 鄭 ), what suggests that it was located somewhere in the eastern part of the central Henan. Whether there was any relationship between those place-names and the state of Yún is not known. History: Yún participated in the coalition of the small states located in the area of the northern Hubei and southern Henan, which was in 701 B.C. (Huan 11) badly defeated by Chǔ 楚. Maybe rather quaint is the fact that Zǐwén 子文, the famous Chǔ minister (lìngyǐn 令尹 ) of the 7th century B.C., was born of an illegal relationship of the Chǔ minister Dòu Bóbǐ 鬥伯比 with a daughter of the ruler of Yún (see ZUO, Xuan 4). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-5bfe3500-dd08-475e-b5b3-4a6a04f6a75f"><form corresp="#uuid-cb8b1b85-2025-4cb9-b704-7650f43260b4">
<orth>鄒</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zōu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tsru</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-64322216-50e3-403a-8ff8-e278080bb7b8">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>a small state in today's Shāndōng</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-7bf1385a-4ce5-49c6-8842-51b9b31e642d"><form corresp="#uuid-315874da-9096-4647-9cd0-40298864fdda">
<orth>鄣</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhāng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kjaŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕi̯ɐŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-76ed36f4-096f-403c-877e-a9ef401aa808">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Zhāng 鄣 (also written as 章 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 556-559)Ruling clan: According to the Xìng zuǎn, Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, and Lù shǐ Hòu jǐ, rulers of Zhāng belonged to the Jiāng 姜 clan. Shì běn and Shuǐ jīng zhù say that they were from Rèn 任 clan. According to the Xìng kǎo, the rulers of the Zhāng originally had the Rèn surname, and later, in the beginning of the Zhōu period, the successors of Tài gōng 太公 with the Jiāng surname were established there. Rank: Unknown.Founded: According to the Xìng kǎo, the state existed already in the Shāng period. In the beginning of the Western Zhōu, it was given as a fief to the descendants of Tài gōng.Destroyed: 664 B.C. by Qí (according to the CQ, Zhuang 30).Location: In the modern Dōng píng 東平 district in the Shandong province (according to the Du's commentary and Dì míng kǎo lyè). According to the Duan's commentary, the state was located in modern Jiangsu province, in the northern part of Gànyú 贛榆 district. History: A small petty state, mentioned only one time in the CQ (Zhuang 30).</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-e22d1287-6f9d-44cf-8273-db1b5d70a15e"><form corresp="#uuid-976ef71f-78a2-425c-8e4a-92bbcef00dff">
<orth>鄭</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhèng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">deŋs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖiɛŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-17d89c40-23f0-4244-841a-e5efb3df444a">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-ccc826b9-4174-4aa7-a448-e0ba6e316ab4"><form corresp="#uuid-d8297e7f-9827-4c94-9a64-cff597a946c2">
<orth>鄧</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">dèng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">dɯɯŋs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dəŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-5ebd0406-0b0d-47bd-bab3-d97d35409df4">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Dèng 鄧 (CHEN PAN 1969, 423-430)Clan: Màn 曼 (according to the Shì běn and to the ZUO: Huan 11; the surname also appears in the inscriptions on the bronzes). Also written as 嫚; according to some opinions, it is identical with Mán 蠻 and Mǐ 羋. Rank: Hóu 侯 (common in both CQ and ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts, the rulers of Dèng sometimes refer to themselves as gōng 公 or bó 伯.Founded: Unknown. It seems that the state of Dèng could have been established prior to the Western Zhōu period. According to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, the state was founded by the son of the Xià 仲康 ruler Zhòng Kāng 仲康; according to the Xìng jiě and Lù shǐ Hòu jì, the state was established during the reign of the Shāng 商 king Wǔ Dīng 武丁. According to the Chen Pan, the sources can refer to the two different states of the same name. Destroyed: In 678 B.C. (Zhuang 16) by Chǔ 楚. Location: According to the Hàn zhì, the state of Dèng was located in the modern Dèng 鄧 district, southern part of Henan province. According to the Chǔ shǐjiā zhēngyì and Tōng zhì Shì zú lyè, it was located in the northern part of modern Hubei province, in Xiāngfán 襄樊. History: Since the beginning of the 80ties of the 7th century, Dèng was exposed to the attacks from the side of Chǔ. In 689 B.C., the ruler of Dèng unwisely did not follow an advice of one of his ministers who recommended killing the king of Chǔ who passed the state during a military campaign. In 678 B.C., the state was destroyed by Chǔ.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-8c10fafb-8018-4bc9-8075-63720db51501"><form corresp="#uuid-d817e1d7-b6a9-478a-b1dd-25d57fcd789d">
<orth>鄒</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zōu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skru</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-acf670bb-8183-4735-8b89-b8dc22266c0d">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a very small ancient state near Song and Lu</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-3b12d082-5e8a-4020-bf17-80d766c2c97c"><form corresp="#uuid-ebb764db-bd61-49e7-9aa6-e5410d7af279">
<orth>鄾</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yōu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d09d6dd5-ee3f-4227-815a-1f9e7fccc6cc">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Yōu 鄾 (also written as 優 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 447-449)Clan: Unknown. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì and Guó míng jì, the rulers of Yōu should have been of the Màn 曼 surname. Rank: Uncertain. According to the Tōng diǎn and Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, the rulers of Yōu had zǐ 子 rank. Founded: Unknown. Some traditional Chinese scholars suppose that the rulers of the state of Yōu were of the same ancestry as those of the neighboring and stronger state of Dèng 鄧.Destroyed: Unknown. In 477 B.C. (Ai 18), when the city of Yōu was attacked by the army of Bà 巴, it already belonged to Chǔ 楚.Location: In the area of modern Xiāngyáng 襄陽, northern Hubei province. History: In the ZUO, Yōu is mentioned only one time, in 703 B.C. (Huan 9), when the people of Yōu murdered Chǔ messengers going to the visit to the state of Dèng. Thereafter, Yōu was attacked by Chǔ and - although Dèng sent an army to rescue it - defeated. It is even not certain whether Yōu was an independent state or a petty town of Dèng. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-ca217a67-ebdf-4831-97a9-021a0e447e24"><form corresp="#uuid-58389b10-cdbd-4fbe-86d7-9ccb8f3fde67">
<orth>陳</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chén</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡrliŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e80ce27b-6d4e-4795-8874-192d08791958">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-a7dc5b15-8e6a-4dbb-83d0-0546dcf46d0c"><form corresp="#uuid-42059fc8-74c4-4f7c-97da-47bd441a34e5">
<orth>陽</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yáng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">k-laŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ji̯ɐŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-2c8f81da-16bb-4056-92ac-722c9e551fba">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Ya2ng</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-1ebfa460-7b15-4076-b106-f2812c7b3c5c"><form>
<orth>隨</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin"/><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc"/><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc"/></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-6cb6947a-652a-4eef-aeea-4a5797c29860">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Suí 隨 (with the all probability identical with Zēng 曾 of the inscriptions on the bronzes) (CHEN PAN 1969, 417-419)Clan: Jī 姬 (on the basis of the ZUO, Ding 4).Rank: Hóu 侯 (usual in the CQ and ZUO).Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: In 506 B.C. (Ding 4), the state was still in existence. If we accept that Suí was identical with Zēng, the state still existed by 433 B.C. According to the Chūnqiū dìlì kǎo shí, it was (in an unknown period) annexed by Chǔ 楚. Location: In the modern Suí 隨 district, northern Hubei province.History: In the beginning of the Chunqiu period, Suí was a relatively strong state, the most powerful among the states bearing the Jī surname and located to the East of the Hàn River ( 漢東諸姬姓國 ). The states were established probably during the Middle Western Zhōu period as a basis of the Zhōu 周 power in that area, and also as a barrier against the southern states, mainly Chǔ 楚. Nonetheless, in 704 B.C. (Huan 8), Suí was defeated by Chǔ, and since that time it became its vassal state. The relationship between those two states was obviously quite strong, as in 506 B.C. (Ding 4), when the Chǔ king defeated by the state of Wú 吳 fled to Suí, the ruler of Suí refused to surrender him to Wǔ.  It is mostly accepted that the state of Suí known only from the transmitted texts was identical with the state of Zēng 曾, which was located in the modern Suí district and is known only on the basis of archaeological excavations and inscriptions on the bronzes (for a different opinion see YANG KUAN 1999). One of the most famous archaeological discoveries in China is associated with this Zēng 曾; the tomb dating from 433 B.C. which belonged to Marquis Yǐ of Zēng 曾侯乙, and is particularly remarkable for containing the largest assemblage of bronze bells ever found in China. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-691491cc-43a1-4330-8d2b-07c5e539f708"><form corresp="#uuid-ee54a9f1-f2bd-4b8f-8c21-ab40d9071daa">
<orth>雍</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yòng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qoŋs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔi̯oŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1e6f0bde-35b7-4687-a565-ab6e0dfd6616">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Yōng 雍 (also written as 邕 / 雝 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 651-655)Clan: Jī 姬. It seems that there was also the state of the same name, the rulers of which belonged to the Jí 姞 clan (according to the Huán yǔ jì). One of the consorts of Lord Zhuāng of Zhèng 鄭莊公 (743-701 B.C.) was called Yōng Jí 雍姞 (ZUO, Huan 11). According to the Shǐ jì (Zhèng shìjiā), she was from the aristocratic Yōng 雍 lineage from Sòng 宋. Maybe prior to that period, this second state of Yōng was already conquered by Sòng. Rank: Unknown. In the Hàn shū Rén biǎo, the ruler of Yōng is referred to as zǐ 子. In the inscriptions on the bronzes, the rulers of Yōng (unknown of which of the two states of that name) are referred to as wáng 王, gōng 公, bó 伯, or zǐ 子.Founded: The state of Yōng was founded in the early Western Zhōu period by one of the sons of the Zhōu king Wén 周文王. In the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, and in the Guǎng yùn (quoting Fēngsú tōng), this person is referred to as Yōng bó 雍伯. The rulers of the Yōng bearing the Jí 姞 surname are said to be the descendants of the mythical Yellow Emperor 黃帝 (according to the Huán yǔ jì). Destroyed: Unknown. Location: Uncertain. According to the Du's commentary, Yōng was located in the modern Xiūwǔ 修武 district, Henan province. However, Huán yǔ jì locates it into the modern Ānkāng 安康 district, Shǎnxī province. It is not improbable that the state of Yōng was originally located close to the Zhōu western capital, and after 771 B.C. it shifted to the East (as was the case of some of the other states). The second state of the same name, the rulers of which belonged to the Jí 姞 clan, is located by Huán yǔ jì into the modern Qǐ 杞 district in the eastern part of Henan province.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-9cc5d669-f577-4036-bb3e-e35c9877657a"><form corresp="#uuid-2e96207c-11db-40d4-936a-3ddef1eb95bb">
<orth>霍</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">huò</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhʷaaɡ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">hɑk</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3bc337cc-7229-428e-bf6f-a2754420c9a9">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>State of Huo4</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-1449d3ec-6f32-4137-b9b2-cfe742d5fb14"><form corresp="#uuid-84fa6b1d-1c3e-4b0c-b26a-7b7d049f8bcd">
<orth>韓</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">hán</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡaan</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɑn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-31bf8508-c31b-4510-a225-d5ce2007d011">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-5b5ba5be-fb2f-4fc7-97d9-22b4054ade3f"><form corresp="#uuid-acb87eb1-e18b-435f-be95-747b55476778">
<orth>項</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xiàng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡrooŋʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɣɔŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c7334b53-f1ea-4de4-ba15-754bb18e1296">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xiàng 項 (CHEN PAN 1969, 626-628)Ruling clan: Unknown. According to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, Xìng zuǎn, and Guǎng yùn, the rulers of Xiàng belonged to the Zhōu 周 royal clan Jī 姬. Rank: Unknown. Shǐ jì Xiàng Yǔ běnjǐ zhēngyì (quoting Kuò dì zhì), Huán yǔ jì, and Lù shǐ Guó míng jǐ suggest that the rulers of Xiàng were of zǐ 子 rank. Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: According to the CQ (Xi 17), the state was conquered by Qí 齊 in 643 B.C. ZUO dates the annihilation of Xiàng into the same year, but states that it was occupied by the state of Lǔ 魯. Later the area belonged to Chǔ 楚. Location: In the modern Xiàngchéng 項城 district, Henan province (according to the Huì zuǎn). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f2142743-ab58-4c22-8f9c-3759fc37393b"><form corresp="#uuid-1b11da5c-6d40-42fc-bf5d-fa511ea9acc2">
<orth>頓</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">dùn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tuuns</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tuo̝n</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-bfba4b83-8b13-4dbb-8d06-39c77abfc66a">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Dùn 頓 (CHEN PAN 1969, 640-641)Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì). Xìng yuán states that the rulers of Dùn were of Yǎn 偃 surname, but the source of this statement is unknown.Rank: Zǐ 子 (common in the CQ and ZUO). According to the Xìng jiě, the rulers of Dùn originally possessed hóu 侯 rank, but the source of this statement is unknown.Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: In 496 B.C. (Ding 14) by Chǔ 楚. Location: In the modern Xiàngchéng 項城 district, southern Henan province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-822e8fad-d0bc-4356-a6cc-45cb8233b352"><form corresp="#uuid-c594f343-5936-415e-85a9-957028a67b33">
<orth>魏</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wèi</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋɡuls</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋɨi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-242a4220-692e-48ea-b439-d9be76c5bd62">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-7caf97c6-f066-4c5f-bf8b-bed4cc0e12e7"><form corresp="#uuid-f8f76629-6ed0-44b8-befb-c4ddabf7d6fc">
<orth>魯</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">lǔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡ-raaʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">luo̝</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-aee3f4c7-e0c3-4c7e-bdf0-46e9661a6c0c">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-fbb8b1d9-6b00-4a63-9974-ddf84bb40052"><form corresp="#uuid-fa094907-e396-4c42-8911-4550eb87a638">
<orth>黃</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">huáng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡʷaaŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɑŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c2b428c5-e9ef-4807-a68e-9c3ea88a3a60">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Huáng 黃 (CHEN PAN 1969, 431-435)Clan: Yíng 嬴 (according to the Chǔ shìjiā zhēngyì and Du's commentary to the ZUO. The surname also appears in the inscriptions on the bronzes, where it is sometimes written as 盈 or Yǎn 偃 ). Rank: Uncertain. In the inscription on the Cì dǐng 刺鼎, the ruler of Huáng is referred to as gōng 公. Founded: Unknown. Destroyed: In 648 B.C. (Xi 12) by Chǔ 楚.Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, the state of Huáng was located in the modern Huángchuān 潢川 district, southern Henan province. Two tombs belonging to the lord of Huáng and his consort were also uncovered in this area (see History).History: Huáng was a small and unimportant state. However, it is remarkable for two tombs dating from the mid-seventh century B.C., which were uncovered in Shàngguāngāng 上官岡, Guāngshān 光山. The tombs belonged to Mèng, the lord of Huáng 黃君孟, and to his consort Mèng Jī 孟姬 (see Falkenhausen 1999, 505). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-9a0bb4d7-b7fc-416d-8370-be82380b801b"><form corresp="#uuid-d702c49f-bbe8-4518-9d70-efe165978585">
<orth>齊</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">qí</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">dziil</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dzei</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-7df5aa12-e584-4121-8c2f-deef578c70b5">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-18019dfe-5655-487f-bc7b-7a1434f64ad1">npr.adV</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>in the Qí manner 齊語 "speak in the Qí manner" XINSHU: 生長於齊不能齊語也。</def></sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0270a9e6-3eb2-4ce5-9069-7956e7989b0f">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-a05450b1-8e27-49e5-ad63-dda7449ee588"><form corresp="#uuid-3b81e026-2aee-45cd-b686-7bab8c7046b3 #uuid-4b0e1c9a-44d5-48ef-a7dd-0700e314df76">
<orth>三晉</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">sān jìn</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">saam tsins</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">sɑm tsin</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d51dc5e5-958d-4d0c-b12e-01f72345d076">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-8f360c6f-89f6-4bc5-a698-5433c407d3b2">place</tls:sem-feat></gramGrp>
  <def>the three states of  &gt;Wèi 魏,  &gt;Zhào 趙, and &gt;Hán 韓</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-7f272262-d8f6-41af-bc9f-555dc8ddc837"><form corresp="#uuid-b420baa9-4b24-4965-9a08-7ef933d10f54 #uuid-469a7f78-1e03-4675-bb6f-535f87df6708">
<orth>南燕</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">nán yān</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">noom qeen</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">nəm ʔen</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-985adc4b-7953-4907-ad63-b26140d00016">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Nán Yàn 南燕 (usually called only Yàn 燕; distinguish from the Běi Yàn, which was originally written as 郾 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 375-378)Clan: Jí 姞 (according to the Jìn yǔ section of the Guó yǔ; Yàn Jí 燕姞, the wife of Duke Wén of Zhèng 鄭文公, is mentioned in the ZUO, Xuan 3).Rank: Bó 伯 (occurs in the ZUO). Founded: According to the legendary tradition (recorded in the Jìn yǔ chapter of the Guó yǔ and in the Hàn shū Dì lǐ zhì), the lineages with Jí surname were descendants of the mythical Yellow Emperor 黃帝. In the ZUO (Xuan 3; 606 B.C.), the legendary ancestor of Nán Yàn is called Bóyōu 伯 (or Bóshū 伯儵 ). Destroyed: Unknown. The state is mentioned in the ZUO in 674 B.C. (Zhuang 20) and in 500 B.C. (Ding 10). By that period, it was still in existence. Location: In the northeastern part of the modern Yánjīn 延津 area, Henan province (CHEN PAN locates it into the Henan province, Wèihuī fǔ 衛輝府, Zuòchéng 胙城 district; is it identical????). History: Nán Yàn was a small and weak state, which relied mainly on alliances with its more powerful neighbors. In the beginning of the period recorded in the CQ, we find Nán Yàn participating in the struggles among the eastern and central states, which resulted into a defeat of the armies of Qí 齊, Sòng 宋, Wèi 衛, and Nán Yàn by the coalition of Zhèng 鄭, Lǔ 魯, and Jǐ 紀 in 699 B.C. (Huan 13). Later, Nán Yàn several times appears in the ZUO; for instance, in 675 B.C. (Zhuang 19), it intervened into the struggle in the Zhōu 周 royal court. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-d5f5dcfd-05e8-4cdc-a8c4-146e2d9e4c9f"><form corresp="#uuid-6d7ee858-72a8-4b9c-9c38-959b11142323 #uuid-ea9566f7-609d-4041-8608-1e7d3935d092">
<orth>夏后</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xià hòu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡraaʔ ɡooʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɣɛ ɦu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-35ecac78-a19f-4f42-8290-195d3d076f84">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Lord of Xià &gt; Xià dynasty</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-3532a7e0-075e-43b8-a99a-eabe7c7e3ff0"><form corresp="#uuid-83c7a7f5-03b1-4bfd-b668-386b60478132 #uuid-6138cebe-22d3-4bab-babb-202d3f0b13ef">
<orth>小邾</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xiǎo zhū</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">smewʔ to</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">siɛu ʈi̯o</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ab1ca0cf-272d-469d-8f2e-5f7004be8da4">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xiǎo Zhū 小邾 (also called Xiǎo Zhū 小朱, Xiǎo Zhūlóu 小邾婁, or Ní 郳 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 281-284)Clan: Cáo 曹 (according to the ZUO, Guó yǔ - Zhèng yǔ - and to the Shì běn).Rank: Zǐ 子 (common in the CQ).Founded: The state was founded by Yǒu 友, the son of Duke Wén of Zhū 邾文公 (according to the Dù pǔ). In the Shì běn, the founder of Xiǎo Zhū is called Féi 肥.Destroyed: Xiǎo Zhū was still in existence by the end of the period recorded in the CQ. Six generations later, the state was destroyed by Chǔ 楚.Location: The capital of Xiǎo Zhū is said to be located in the modern Téng 滕 district, Shandong province (according to the Du's commentary to the ZUO Zhuang 5, and to the Guó míng jì). According to the different opinion (Huán yǔ jì Yíchéng xiàn), the capital of Xiǎo Zhū was situated in the northwestern part of the modern Dōngyì 東嶧 district, Shandong province. History: Xiǎo Zhū was a small and weak state, which appears in the CQ for the first time in 689 B.C. (Zhuang 5). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-53d9c996-b254-47dd-b59c-6d271818613d"><form corresp="#uuid-0e7f392c-6168-4551-bcd2-ccf3c110ae44 #uuid-765f4fb2-dafc-4556-b24c-640d0745d13d">
<orth>昆夷</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">kūn yí</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kuun li</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kuo̝n ji</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3c925c0e-709e-4ee2-a57e-ff2a889bf6a9">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func><usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a western barbarian tribe</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-3936dc00-4c7b-476a-b1e9-ce523e014f2e"><form corresp="#uuid-cb338275-8afd-43fc-8914-daeb02c2ce84 #uuid-fb89a673-a23b-40ad-ab82-7b44c4b3995e">
<orth>英士</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yīng shì</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qraŋ dzrɯʔ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔɣaŋ ɖʐɨ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-26bb14a0-1b2c-4e65-9c7f-b187c8bd592f">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Yīngshì 英氏 (also called Yīng 英, Yāng 央 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 622-625)Ruling clan: Yǎn 偃 ( 匽 ) or Yíng 嬴 (according to the Shǐ jì, Xià běnjǐ chapter). Rank: Unknown.Founded: According to the Shǐ jì (Xià běn jǐ), the state was founded by the descendants of the mythical Gāo Yáo 皋陶 during the reign of the equally mythical emperor Yǔ 禹. Destroyed: The state was attacked by Qí 齊 and Xú 徐 in 644 B.C. (Xi 16). Later, it was destroyed by Chǔ 楚 (according to the Shǐ jì, Chǔ shìjiā). Location: In the modern Liù'ān 六安 district, Anhui province (according to the Huì zuǎn). </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-f2f994f7-96e0-403b-908c-f7cc513b264f"><form corresp="#uuid-4e38a05e-2438-4c23-acdd-03ac49223167 #uuid-6f54daf0-aa06-4469-8d5c-52be1bac8d50">
<orth>西周</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xī zhōu</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sqɯɯl tjɯw</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">sei tɕɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3e0d98ac-6507-4bac-923e-a30d69e0f3fc">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-fe00e347-7643-438d-b7d5-a39111709ac4"><form corresp="#uuid-86d435d5-2ec2-42bf-af4d-8c64e5258a94 #uuid-41bedcd4-90a1-4192-9fa7-d1da43f2da22">
<orth>須句</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xū jù</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">so kos</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">si̯o ki̯o</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3166cd44-7517-4735-b8de-f11d5217539d">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Xūjù 須句 (written also as Xūqū 須胊 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 636-637)Clan: Fēng 風.Rank: Zǐ 子.Founded: According to the tradition, the rulers of Xūjù were descendants of the mythical emperor Tài Hào 太皞.Destroyed: The state was conquered in 639 B.C. (Xi 21) by Zhū 邾. In the following year, it was reestablished by Lǔ 魯. Later, it was again destroyed by Zhū, and in 620 B.C. (Wen 7), the area eventually came under the control of Lǔ. Location: According to the Du's commentary, to the Xù Shāndōng kǎogǔ lù, and to the Shuǐ jīng zhù, Xūjù was located in the modern Dōngpíng 東平 district, Shandong province.</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-8a45dc19-f9e2-4cfb-9f19-d2e671e9951e"><form corresp="#uuid-bb9b4425-bfeb-4951-aba2-3f7e29a9bf1f #uuid-d29db0d9-a966-4e2c-942e-9bd6b402a7c1">
<orth>顓奧</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhuān ào</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tjon quuɡs</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕiɛn ʔɑu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a433a8ad-6745-47e3-aeaf-9381ff31330e">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Zhuānyú 顓臾 (CHEN PAN 1969, 638-639)Clan: Fēng 風.Rank: According to the Lún yǔ (Jì shì chapter), Zhuānyú was a vassal state of Lǔ 魯. Lù shǐ Guó míng jì attributes to its rulers zǐ 子 rank, but the source of this statement is unknown. Founded: According to the tradition, the rulers of Zhuānyú were descendants of the mythical emperor Tài Hào 太皞.Destroyed: The state is mentioned in the ZUO in the entry for 639 B.C. (Xi 21). By the time of Confucius, it was obviously still in an existence.Location: In the modern Bì 費 district, Shandong province. </def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-292e63dc-029f-4b80-923e-371134bb3ead"><form corresp="#uuid-fb67b697-a7f5-4e27-8090-d90ec205fd5c #uuid-d5b99e1b-b77c-4787-af6c-4dbe81f7ef19 #uuid-1e24a96a-b3b4-4016-ab95-0acdb72d45d7">
<orth>於餘丘</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yú yú qiū</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qa la khɯ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔi̯ɤ ji̯ɤ khɨu</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-59958b02-5b68-44d6-99dc-06c2058c6a08">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>Yúyúqiū 於餘丘 (CHEN PAN 1969, 502-504)Clan: Unknown.Rank: Unknown. Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: Unknown.Location: Very uncertain. According to the Dì míng kǎo lyè, Yúyúqiū was located in the modern Línyí 臨沂 district, Shandong province.History: Yúyúqiū is mentioned only one time in the CQ (Zhuang 2; 692 B.C.). It is even not certain whether it was a state (as is suggested by the Du's commentary) or only a dependent town (as is suggested by the GONGYANG and GULIANG).</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-35ec438a-91c6-4635-a6b6-4998c8af56a9"><form corresp="#uuid-23b47fd8-2929-424f-b8bc-482da10682d6">
<orth>寒</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">hán</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɡaan</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦɑn</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-2b7df0eb-8b08-4ef7-b353-b27fd3652761">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>name of a very ancient state said to have been enfeoffed in Xia dynasty times...</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-76d2d90b-6642-4b90-bac3-93b416f27728"><form corresp="#uuid-f74875f5-786d-4a10-888d-9a5d8fb1324d">
<orth>微</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wēi</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">mɯl</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">mɨi</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4d845b8e-98ad-4984-8b40-90f77b3439c3">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>1. small early Shang state in Shanxi; 2. Zhou state in Sichuan;</def></sense>
</entry>
<entry type="word" xml:id="uuid-ffc08509-e151-4c16-bfa3-5675ef84c57c"><form corresp="#uuid-4cd056cc-384e-4e60-8350-ecc739a264ad">
<orth>應</orth><pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yīng</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qɯŋ</pron><pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔɨŋ</pron></form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0b4aee49-c2b4-4d50-89b6-4a0674b2d0f9">
<gramGrp><pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func></gramGrp>
  <def>ZUO: small state in Henan Province</def></sense>
</entry></div></div>
