<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-de68ed0b-f6e2-477b-ae4b-2f58005a6f91">
<head>STUDENT</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>DISCIPLE</item>
<item>SCHOLAR</item>
<item>UNDERGRADUATE</item>
<item>GRADUATE</item>
<item>GRAD STUDENT</item>
<item>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW</item>
<item>FRESHMAN</item>
<item>SOPHOMORE</item>
<item>JUNIOR</item>
<item>SENIOR</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">學生</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>ADULT who is TEACH:taught PERSONALLY by a TEACHER OR who is STUDYING.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current general word for a disciple of any kind, or a follower of a school or any line of thought, is tú 徒.</p>
<p>2. Mén rén 門人 stresses the physical abode near a master.</p>
<p>3. Dì zǐ 弟子 refers rather intimately to disciples of a master as the object of his affection.</p>
<p>4. Shǔ 屬 is a cold general word referring to someone who belongs to a certain group and under a certain leadership.</p>
<p>5. Cóng zhě 從者 like the English "followers" primarily focusses on the idea of following a master wherever he goes, but this nuance is weakened with time so that the term comes to mean quite abstractly "follower".</p>
<p>6. Xiǎo zǐ 小子 is an affectionate term only used in the vocative.</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>EDUCATION 41.</p>
<p>生， “ 先生 ” 的省稱，轉指學生，特指儒生。</p>
<p>徒，泛指學生。</p>
<p>役，儒生之外的學生。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>學生 is the current modern word for a student or pupil or disciple.</p>
<p>學徒 is a current formal word for a disciple, and typically the subject studies is a basic handicraft.</p>
<p>徒弟 is a general slightly formal word for a disciple of any kind, scholarly or otherwise.</p>
<p>門徒 is a slightly more formal word referrring to a disciple within a dignified area of scholarship.</p>
<p>學童 focusses on low status and young age.</p>
<p>桃李 (lit) focusses politely on the high quality of disciples, main in addressing their teacher.</p>
<p>門人 (lit) refers to one of many disciples of a distinguished teacher, typically of some age.</p>
<p>門生 (lit) refers to disciples of a distinguished teacher who are typically still of low scholarly status.</p>
<p>門下 (lit) is a polite word to use in order to identify oneself as belonging to a distinguished school of scholarship.</p>
<p>後學 (lit) is a polite way of focussing one's belonging to the younger generation in a scholarly tradiiton.</p>
<p>受業 (lit) is a periphrastic way of referring to oneself as a humble disciple.</p>
<p>學子 (lit) is classificatory term referring to disciples as opposed to teachers.</p>
<p>弟子 (lit) is the classical term for a disciple which is still current.</p>
<p>徒眾 (lit) focusses on the large number of disciples.</p>
<p>徒屬 (lit) focusses on the appurtenance of disciples to their teacher or school.</p>
<p>及門 is always plural and refers to co-disciples.??</p>
<p>生徒 (lit, obs) refers to students or disciples.</p>
<p>諸生 (lit, obs) is always plural and refers to the students of a master as a group.</p>
<p>門弟子 (lit, obs) is always plural and refers to the students as belonging under one tradition.</p>
<p>門下生 (lit, obs) is always plural and refers to the students as belonging under one tradition.</p>
<p>生 is (obs) a classical expression for a disciple which is obsolete.</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="antonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-99d50267-f112-4b2e-ac96-d8a1b59aa1ad">TEACHER</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-17c5977a-0682-43c0-97c9-80813ff8ad67">ADULT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">17.26</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-dcdec461-c248-4809-a141-385e6610d74c">FINSTERBUSCH 2000</ref>
<title>Verzeichnis und Motivindex der Han-Darstellungen</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">800</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>Schueler:</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>DISCIPULI</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-65cb3fa8-ba3e-4eef-b23e-5b43a8bb8651">JONES 2005</ref>
<title>Encyclopedia of Religion</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.59:43</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ELEVE.DISCIPLE.ECOLIER</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">



































    </div>
</div>