<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-40ce2fe2-1e89-48ec-9381-f56af49ae111">
<head>SURVEY</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>LOOK AT</item>
<item>LOOK OVER</item>
<item>OBSERVE</item>
<item>VIEW</item>
<item>CONTEMPLATE</item>
<item>REGARD</item>
<item>GAZE AT</item>
<item>STARE AT</item>
<item>EYE</item>
<item>SCRUTINIZE</item>
<item>EXAMINE</item>
<item>INSPECT</item>
<item>SCAN</item>
<item>STUDY</item>
<item>CONSIDER</item>
<item>REVIEW</item>
<item>TAKE STOCK OF</item>
<item>INFORMAL SIZE UP</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">通觀</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>LOOK at so as to INVESTIGATE MANY THINGS.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. Guān 觀 is to try to get a detailed careful overview of something and to survey something complex with careful analytic attention.</p>
<p>2. Lǎn 覽 is to look over something (often with pleasure, and typically from a highe perspective) with careful aesthetic and analytic attention and in order to get a full survey of all there is.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>綜觀</p>
<p>通觀</p>
<p>縱觀</p>
<p>展望</p>
<p>瞻望</p>
<p>向前看</p>
<p>觀察</p>
<p>觀測</p>
<p>察看</p>
<p>相</p>
<p>觀</p>
<p>察</p>
<p>體察</p>
<p>考察</p>
<p>審察</p>
<p>洞察</p>
<p>著眼</p>
<p>察言觀色</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-9061b621-93dc-47b4-a4cd-feeb3ee4b3db">INSPECT</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-17a8f308-dca1-4db9-8cbb-de2d495a577f">LOOK</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1252</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>觀，覽，望</p>
<p>1. WL finds that the focus of gua1n 觀 is on the subjective attention and la3n 覽 on comprehensiveness of coverage.  In fact the main difference is that la3n 覽 is typically downwards from a higher perspective, and that la3n 覽 clearly tends to emphasise an aesthetic dimension of gaining a full view of something whereas gua1n 觀 typically emphasises detailed information gained through observation.</p>
<p>2. WL sees wa4ng 望 as referring to viewing something from a distance.  This is true enough, but it is my impression that an important general nuance of the word is complementary to la3n 覽 "gaze down all over", so that wa4ng 望 often comes to mean "look up to from afar", although there are generalised uses where wa4ng 望 refers to looking down into the distance e.g. from a mountain, and at sheep, with no nuances of admiration whatsoever.</p>
<p>3. Note incidentally that la3n 覽 is extremely common from Han times in the meaning "to read with proper appreciation" which is lacking in WL.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">



    </div>
</div>