<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-afbdd6b9-b5e4-42ff-a8ae-7bf4522b1f4f">
<head>TEACH</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>TEACHING</item>
<item>EDUCATE</item>
<item>INSTRUCT</item>
<item>SCHOOL</item>
<item>TUTOR</item>
<item>COACH</item>
<item>TRAIN</item>
<item>ENLIGHTEN</item>
<item>ILLUMINATE</item>
<item>VERSE</item>
<item>EDIFY</item>
<item>INDOCTRINATE</item>
<item>DRILL</item>
<item>DISCIPLINE</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">教化</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">教</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>ADDRESS OTHERS so as to TRY to CAUSE them to HAVE SKILLS OR TALENTS.</p>
<p>*Teaching by the teacher X, to learner Y, of content Z.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current general word for training, instructing, and disciplining others is jiào 教 (ant. xué 學 "study") and the standard main aim of jiào 教 is unquestioning obedience, professional skill, and intellectual conformity to the standard set by the teacher, and the word connotes use of authority and sometimes even coercion. The primary aim of jiào 教 is action conforming to a standard, and the word is commonly nominalised.</p>
<p>2. Huì 誨 (ant. xí 習 "study persistently") refers to systematic and persistent efforts to teach and inculcate intellectual or practical skills ( 誨之琴 "taught him to play the zither") and moral understanding of students ( 誨女知之 "I will teach you so you understand"), and the word never implies coercion or any threat of force. Huì 誨 can be mutual, or refer to equals teaching equals, even subordinates teaching superiors 諫誨 "remonstrate with and instruct". The word is not commonly nominalised. The primary aim of huì 誨 is understanding.</p>
<p>3. Huà 化 refers to successful disciplining and teaching, typically on a large social scale. See INFLUENCE</p>
<p>4. Qǐ 啟 and fā 發 refer to the opening up of new intellectual and moral dimensions for others.</p>
<p>5. Xùn 訓 refers in a rather abstract way to formal strict instruction and training aimed primarily at professional skill.</p>
<p>6. Zhào 詔 refers to instruction by means of useful information or warning.</p>
<p>7. Fēng 風 is occasionally used to refer to teaching by example.</p>
<p>8. Liàn 練 refers specifically to military training and only occasionally to other forms of drill.</p>
<p>9. Dào 道 refers to the content of what is taught, and is largely restricted to postnominal position, as in 儒道 "Confucian teaching".</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>EDUCATION 11.</p>
<p>教，用正面的事例讓人效法。</p>
<p>誨，上對下，長對幼、尊對卑的教導。</p>
<p>訓，重在疏通事理，使人理解順暢，獲得教益。</p>
<p>啟，重在啟蒙。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>教書 is current modern Chinese word for (book-oriented or not-book-oriented) teaching.</p>
<p>教 is a current word for teaching of any kind, and the word is always verbal, always transitive.</p>
<p>講課 focusses on the concrete classroom situation.</p>
<p>授課 focusses on the transmission of curriculum.</p>
<p>講授 focusses on transmission of knowledge.</p>
<p>講解 focusses on intellectual disentaglement for students.</p>
<p>教授 (lit) focusses in a formal way on the transmission of traditional learning.</p>
<p>教學 focusses on paedagogical method.</p>
<p>講學 focusses on expounding curriculum content.</p>
<p>執教 focusses on the conduct of professional duty as a teacher.</p>
<p>上書 (obs, arch) teach a new lesson.</p>
<p>上堂 focusses on the physical present "confronting" the students.</p>
<p>主講 focusses on leadership in the teaching process.</p>
<p>上講台 is periphrastic for beginning to teach.</p>
<p>上講臺 is periphrastic for beginning to teach.</p>
<p>設帳 (lit) is a traditional idiom for setting up a school.</p>
<p>授徒 focusses on the students as the recipients of teaching.</p>
<p>下帷講誦 (prov) is a periphrastic idiom for traditional teaching.</p>
<p>傳授</p>
<p>感化</p>
<p>教導</p>
<p>輔導</p>
<p>教唆</p>
<p>教訓</p>
<p>教育</p>
<p>指導</p>
<p>指點</p>
<p>指教</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-0c933384-0748-47e6-98c6-81ebe6b2f89c">EDUCATE</ref>
            </item>
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-b6aa80b9-f076-4e31-89c0-7a2878a048eb">REVELATION</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
        <list type="see">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-99d50267-f112-4b2e-ac96-d8a1b59aa1ad">TEACHER</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-ffe85849-0547-451b-8952-d32067596c12">ADDRESS</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">17.25</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b8242ce-9fc6-4b7b-bd52-14c744308409">COMENIUS 1665</ref>
<title>De Rerum Humanarum Emendatione</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">514</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>DOCERE est quod qvis scit, ut alter sciat, efficere.</p>
<p>Ubi tria rez. 1. qvis docendus: discipulus; (1) discendi idoneus (2)avidus. 2. Per qvem? per Doctorem, cujus reisita Scire, posse, velle docere. 3. Qvomodo? per Doctrinam qui comprehendit, Exempla, Praecepta, Usum.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>EDUCATE</p>
<p>erudire refers positively to parental action designed to educate and acculturate a child, and particularly reducing the child's ignorance.</p>
<p>formare refers positively to concerted, typically  parental, action designed to prepare a child for a certain task to be performed as an adult, inculcating a bent for the performance of this adult task.</p>
<p>instituere refers positively to a formal education preparing someone for a certain type of employment.</p>
<p/>
<p>homines non nascuntur sed effinguntur (Erasmus)</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">209</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-0e53b7a8-3acd-4859-ac83-596e75d42e7d">LANGIUS 1631</ref>
<title>Anthologia sive Florilegium rerum et materiarum selectarum</title>
                <note>
<p>EDUCATIO</p>
<p>INSTITUTIO</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-f2c59ecb-bbff-4004-8e45-5fc7f92ed0da">Mel'cuk 1984</ref>
<title>Tolkovo-kombinatornyj slovar' sovremmenogo russkogo jazyka. Explanatory Combinatorial Dictionary of Modern Russian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">943</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-e65dd863-ccd1-4064-8fac-710a1be058a0">Mel'cuk I</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire explicatif et combinatoire du francais contemporain, vol. I</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">93</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-56dd8ede-a572-47bc-8a1b-70c846775874">MENGE</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonymik</title>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.524</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-3cf76dec-e8bc-4732-bde9-e5ca60e7fb1a">SCHMIDT 1889</ref>
<title>Handbuch der lateinischen und griechischen Synonymik</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">82</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-be4461ef-350c-4c36-b3f4-aa5d10e78e12">STAIGER 2003</ref>
<title>Das grosse China-Lexikon</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">751</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ddc8dc41-e703-448c-9f61-6db9445685a7">UNGER SACH</ref>
<title>"Sachwoerterbuch zum Alten China"</title>
                <note>
<p>ERZIEHUNG/UNTERRICHT</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1279</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>教，誨</p>
<p>1. WL claims that both mean 教導 and that the special feature of jia4o 教 is the element of coercion qia2ngzhi4 強制. In fact, one is practical instruction and training, not normally focussing on the coercion or even the threat of force, and the other is intellectual teaching. </p>
<p>Occasionally, jia4o 教 does have a general meaning where even a subordinate can jia4o 教 a ruler, the point being not coercion or even power, but rather professional or technical (rather than moral) authority:</p>
<p>HF 13.03:01; jiaoshi  297; jishi 238; jiaozhu 123; shiping 467</p>
<p>昔者吳起教楚悼王以楚國之俗曰： In ancient times Wu2 Q taught King Da4o of Chu3 the customs of Chu3, saying:</p>
<p>HF 32.15:01; jiaoshi 486; jishi 631; jiaozhu 375; shiping 1094</p>
<p>客有教燕王為不死之道者， A foreigner was teaching the King of Ya1n the way of immortality.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-5058f490-4d8b-43b1-a3da-a7f078897c3d">POIRIER 1991</ref>
<title>Histoire des moeurs</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">2.309-375</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-b425a52b-7c3a-4b26-a4a5-8c5a55eaf19b">GRACE ZHANG 2010</ref>
<title>Using Chinese Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">221</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ad3bdc83-0b1c-471f-b1ef-28c098e55626">BARNARD AND SPENCER 2002</ref>
<title>Encyclopedia of Social and Cultural Anthropology</title>
                <note>
<p>EDUCATION</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-6b365858-64c1-4190-8019-802d035d58ee">GIRARD 1769</ref>
<title>SYNONYMES FRANÇOIS, LEURS DIFFÉRENTES SIGNIFICATIONS, ET LE CHOIX QU'IL EN FAUT FAIRE Pour parler avec justesse</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.53.38</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ENSEIGNER.APPRENDRE.INSTRUIRE.INFORMER.FAIRE SAVOIR</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-bbf731db-f5e8-4da6-9d88-b10c69b707ad">PILLON 1850</ref>
<title>Handbook of Greek Synonymes, from the French of M. Alex. Pillon, Librarian of the Bibliothèque Royale , at Paris, and one of the editors of the new edition of Plaché's Dictionnaire Grec-Français, edited, with notes, by the Rev. Thomas Kerchever Arnold, M.A. Rector of Lyndon, and late fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">no.174</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-e8e00c8c-6f7d-429d-82a5-84721abe7cc7">T.W.HARBSMEIER 2004</ref>
<title>A New Dictionary of Classical Greek Synonyms</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">NO.176</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">




























































    </div>
</div>