<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-6106f200-6c09-483d-b636-68f140442ca0">
<head>THIS</head>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">這</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>The NEAR OBJECT.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. The current anaphoric or deictic purely referential demonstrative pronoun "this" is cǐ 此.</p>
<p>2. Shì 是 has a pregnant use meaning "such a" and characteristically refers to something by virtue of its quality (in which function it is not replaceable with cǐ 此 ), but in many contexts the word is used as a more generalised referential pronoun.</p>
<p>3. Sī 斯 is currently considered as a dialect variant of cǐ 此, but this raises many problems.</p>
<p>4. Zhī 之 is a an archaic deictic demonstrative pronoun restricted to adnominal position. It stands to reason that the other meanings of this word may be plausibly derived from this archaic meaning.</p>
<p>5. Zhě 者 is a highly specialised pronoun always modified by a preceding phrase.</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／ LU JIANMING</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="taxonymy">
<item>
                <ref target="#uuid-72833a4e-d1ec-471f-806c-64c1e3317aaf">ONLY</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-dc83b43b-a977-4566-92b5-33c421e80029">NEAR</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ab831347-9626-498d-aa1e-eb43eae72d05">DOEDERLEIN 1840</ref>
<title>Lateinische Synonyme und Etymologien</title>
                <note>
<p>THIS</p>
<p>hic refers to this one that is here.</p>
<p>iste refers to this one that is yours.</p>
<p>ille refers to that one that is his.</p>
<p>is refers to an absent person or thing.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">228</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>實，寔</p>
<p>1. Note that the two characters are NOT homophonous in classical Chinese.  The reminder of this in WL 227 is useful.  However, it stands to reason that WHEN 實 is used as a loan character for 寔 it should perhaps all the same be read in the pronounciation of the latter word.  The point needs systematic investigation.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ecfe1810-16d7-46f0-901d-6fc0c0808a34">HONG CHENGYU 2009</ref>
<title>古漢語常用詞同義詞詞典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">589</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">
































    </div>
</div>