<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/tls.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" type="concept" xml:id="uuid-151bb426-967a-4048-b112-aadda275b7de">
<head>TOOTH</head>
    <list type="altnames">
<item>FANG</item>
<item>TUSK</item>
<item>MOLAR</item>
<item>INCISOR</item>
<item>ZOOLOGY DENTICLE</item>
<item>INFORMAL PEARLY WHITE</item>
<item>(TEETH) INFORMAL CHOPPERS</item>
    </list>
    <list type="translations">
        <item xml:lang="zh">牙齒</item>
        <item xml:lang="och">牙</item>
    </list>
<div type="definition">
<p>HARD WHITE THINGS in the MOUTH which are USED FOR BITING AND CHEWING.</p>
    </div>
<div type="notes">
<div type="old-chinese-criteria">
<p>1. Chǐ 齒 refers to the visible front teeth, thus when one smiles one shows one's chǐ 齒, xiàn chǐ 見齒, and only if one were vampire-like would one show any yá 牙. Chǐ 齒 does not typically refer to the teeth as weapons of aggressive action. The teeth by which one judges age are always chǐ 齒, and the teeth with which one commonly chews tend quite as often to be chǐ 齒. The front teeth that get cold when the lips are gone, are chǐ 齒 in classical Chinese, and they are not seen in that common saying as aggressive weapons. The admirable white teeth of a lady are the chǐ 齒, only in the case of vampires yá 牙. We have goǔ yá 狗牙 but mǎ chí 馬齒. One grinds one's chǐ 齒, 切齒, not one's yá 牙. The first teeth of a child are never yá 牙 and regularly chǐ 齒, and similarly for the teeth that an old man loses, when chǐ duò 齒墮 "the teeth fall out". Interestingly, the elephant has chǐ 齒, never yá 牙, presumably because these tusks were taken to be a threat to his own survival, not to man.</p>
<p>2. Yá 牙 can occasionally generally refer to teeth, even the exquisite teeth of a woman, but the word typically refers to the large side teeth or fangs of an animal with which it bites, and which are seen as a threat. The threatening teeth of an animal, the teeth with which a rat attacks one's home, are yá 牙. Thus one speaks of the zhuǎ yá 爪牙 "the claws and fangs" as metaphors for weapons. Theses are sharp like fangs, and as such they lend themselves to metaphorical use to indicate dented patterns in ornaments.</p>
        </div>
<div type="huang-jingui">
<p>HUANG JINGUI 2006</p>
<p>HUMAN BODY 35.</p>
<p>齒，口內諸齒的總稱。</p>
<p>牙，犬齒。</p>
        </div>
<div type="modern-chinese-criteria">
<p>牙</p>
<p>牙齒</p>
<p>齒</p>
<p>乳齒</p>
<p>奶牙</p>
<p>rough draft to BEGIN TO identify synonym group members for analysis, based on CL etc. 18.11.2003. CH ／</p>
        </div>
    </div>
<div type="pointers">
        <list type="hypernymy">
            <item>
                <ref target="#uuid-fb6d18a8-a42b-4cc9-bfbf-7b0597a2b084">N/A</ref>
            </item>
        </list>
    </div>
<div type="source-references">
        <listBibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-60d39cc0-d76b-4275-8490-886ace4204be">BUCK 1988</ref>
<title>A Dictionary of Selected Synonyms in the Principal Indo-European Languages</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">4.27</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-57350e2c-978e-4013-b566-812ce1ea8cbf">FRANKE 1989</ref>
<title>Bibliographisches Handbuch zur Sprachinhaltsforschung. Teil II. Systematischer Teil. B. Ordnung nach Sinnbezirken (mit einem alphabetischen Begriffsschluessel): Der Mensch und seine Welt im Spiegel der Sprachforschung</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">7</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>ZAEHNE</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-8a7b3e79-a326-45b5-8419-1ea3245117f8">HANFEI TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>韓非子同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-a8850689-f070-43c6-ae94-2ae9d4341a27">IORDANSKAJA 1996</ref>
<title>A Russian-English Collocational Dictionary of the Human Body</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">137</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-abc2f8ad-0bc4-4663-a70c-806e480d7081">LUNHENG TONGYI 2004</ref>
<title>論衡同義詞研究</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">23</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-d905dccd-9c5f-458e-b56c-c2a7c09e2d72">REY 2005</ref>
<title>Dictionnaire culturel en langue francaise</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">1.2259</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-646c8ed8-a923-41d0-a298-a39924ff494d">WANG FENGYANG 1993</ref>
<title>古辭辨 Gu ci bian</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">120</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ebe4710d-bf7c-496a-8815-9e6f1c15c1a9">WANG LI 2000</ref>
<title>王力古漢語字典</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">681</biblScope>
                <note>
<p>牙，齒</p>
<p>1. WL follows received opinion in claiming that the front teeth are chi3 齒 whereas the side teeth are ya2 牙: 門牙稱齒，其餘的稱牙.  But as Ko3ng Yi3ngda2 already pointed out, primarily the large agressive teeth like the fangs of a fierce dog are ya2 牙, and even the front teeth of a rat, because of their prominence, are ya2 牙.  Ko3ng's definition, which WL quote, is right: 頷上大齒謂之牙, and the trouble is that WL do not realise that this explanation is quite inconsistent of with the traditional explanation of ya2 牙 as all teeth other than front teeth.</p>
                </note>
            </bibl>
<bibl>
                <ref target="#uuid-ceec1ff7-e9e2-4e81-8c76-a29b231e6074">WU SANXING 2008</ref>
<title>中國文化背景八千詞 Zhongguo wenhua beijing ba qian ci</title>
                <biblScope unit="page">61</biblScope>
                <note>
<p/>
                </note>
            </bibl>
        </listBibl>
    </div>
<div type="words">







    </div>
</div>