<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-d0136f31-a2ca-4f14-936f-31a2cadf14e4" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>鄣</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-7bf1385a-4ce5-49c6-8842-51b9b31e642d" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-315874da-9096-4647-9cd0-40298864fdda">
<orth>鄣</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhāng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kjaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Zhāng 鄣 (also written as 章) (CHEN PAN 1969, 556-559)

Ruling clan: According to the Xìng zuǎn, Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, and Lù shǐ Hòu jì, rulers of Zhāng belonged to the Jiāng 姜 clan. Shì běn and Shuǐ jīng zhù say that they were from Rèn 任 clan. According to the Xìng kǎo, the rulers of the Zhāng originally had the Rèn surname, and later, in the beginning of the Zhōu period, the successors of Tài gōng 太公 with the Jiāng surname were established there.

Rank: Unknown.

Founded: According to the Xìng kǎo, the state existed already in the Shāng period. In the beginning of the Western Zhōu, it was given as a fief to the descendants of Tài gōng.

Destroyed: 664 B.C. by Qí (according to the CQ, Zhuang 30).

Location: In the modern Dōng píng 東平 district in the Shandong province (according to the Du's commentary and Dì míng kǎo lyè). According to the Duan's commentary, the state was located in modern Jiangsu province, in the northern part of Gànyú 贛榆 district.

History: A small petty state, mentioned only one time in the CQ (Zhuang 30).
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-76ed36f4-096f-403c-877e-a9ef401aa808">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Zhāng 鄣 (also written as 章 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 556-559)Ruling clan: According to the Xìng zuǎn, Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, and Lù shǐ Hòu jǐ, rulers of Zhāng belonged to the Jiāng 姜 clan. Shì běn and Shuǐ jīng zhù say that they were from Rèn 任 clan. According to the Xìng kǎo, the rulers of the Zhāng originally had the Rèn surname, and later, in the beginning of the Zhōu period, the successors of Tài gōng 太公 with the Jiāng surname were established there. Rank: Unknown.Founded: According to the Xìng kǎo, the state existed already in the Shāng period. In the beginning of the Western Zhōu, it was given as a fief to the descendants of Tài gōng.Destroyed: 664 B.C. by Qí (according to the CQ, Zhuang 30).Location: In the modern Dōng píng 東平 district in the Shandong province (according to the Du's commentary and Dì míng kǎo lyè). According to the Duan's commentary, the state was located in modern Jiangsu province, in the northern part of Gànyú 贛榆 district. History: A small petty state, mentioned only one time in the CQ (Zhuang 30).</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>