<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-d10da0ae-834e-40c9-8da0-ae834e20c9f0" n="3">
    <form>
        <orth>州</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="CONTINENT" tls:concept-id="uuid-10161d8c-7fd1-4b42-940f-369612b03fc6" xml:id="uuid-737f0dfc-2c2e-4894-bc88-36118970a982" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-875ca067-c285-434c-91df-40d7f2498d27">
<orth>州</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhōu</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kju</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕɨu</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-48a4db70-808f-4312-88d1-ea2d6d4d1bab">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">4</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>continent, subdivision of the world 九州</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="REGION" tls:concept-id="uuid-d2308761-87e9-44b9-8b7d-1e24876a5924" xml:id="uuid-c5e43e67-f42d-4c1b-8d2a-9376cb5ce2b6" n="5">
            <form corresp="#uuid-875ca067-c285-434c-91df-40d7f2498d27">
<orth>州</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhōu</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kju</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕɨu</pron>
            </form>
            <def>The general old word for a region is zhōu 州 as in jiǔ zhōu 九州 "the Nine Regions of the World". Especially from Three Kingdom times onwards this word came to regularly replace the term jùn 郡 as the designation of a province. In Han times, under emperor Wǔdì, the leader of a zhōu 州 is called cì shǐ 刺史.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a8274dfd-e7c8-4649-b7df-68d7bed94130" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>region</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ee5cd184-a78a-41a8-824e-fa4ee608de61" resp="#CH" tls:created="2019-10-17T16:00:55.353+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>N</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-20a87134-926d-4be7-8815-246c1f7a9ca7">n[adN]</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>the people of the region</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-51083662-94b5-48a5-8edc-660e7b31df36" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-875ca067-c285-434c-91df-40d7f2498d27">
<orth>州</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhōu</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kju</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕɨu</pron>
            </form>
            <def>1. Zhōu 州 (also written as 舟; also called Chúnyú 淳于) (CHEN PAN 1969, 411-416)

Clan: Uncertain. According to the Xúnzǐ and Shì běn, the rulers of Zhōu belonged to the Jiāng 姜 clan.

Rank: Gōng 公 (according to the ZUO and CQ, Huan 5).

Founded: Unknown. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì, the state of Zhōu was founded in the Early Western Zhōu period, during the reign of King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王.

Destroyed: Unknown. According to the CQ and the ZUO, in 707 B.C. (Huan 5), the ruler of Zhōu fled to Cáo 曹. Later, the area was occupied by the state of Qǐ 杞.

Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, the state of Zhōu was located in the area of modern Ānqiū 安丘, Shandong province. Lù shǐ Guó míng jì has suggested that the state was located in the modern Gāomì 高密, also in the Shandong province. According to some of the traditional Chinese scholars (Zhào Péngfēi; Yáo Nài), the state of Zhōu belonged to the eastern royal domain in central Henan (for 712 B.C. - Yin 11 - it is mentioned in the ZUO that the Zhōu 周 king gave the fields of Zhōu to the state of Zhèng). It cannot be excluded that the state of Zhōu was originally located within the royal domain (this can also explain why its rulers had the title of the Duke); however, by the beginning of the Chunqiu period, the state was obviously in the Shandong area.  

History: Zhōu was a small and unimportant state mentioned only one time (in 707 B.C.; Huan 5) in the CQ and ZUO. It is rather mysterious that on this occasion, its ruler is designated gōng in both texts. Maybe the state of Zhōu was originally located within the royal domain (see Location), and its rulers held some high positions in the Zhōu 周 royal court.

2. Zhōu 州 (also written as 舟; do not confuse with the state of the same name located in the Shandong province) (CHEN PAN 1969, 481-483)

Clan: Unknown. According to the Xìng xī, Lù shǐ Guó míng jì and Hòu jì, the rulers of Zhōu had Yǎn 偃 surname. Tōngzhì Shìzú lyè suggested that they were of Jiāng 姜 surname (this suggestion is based on the supposed relationship between the southern Zhōu and Shandong Zhōu). According to the record in the Shuō yuàn, Zhōu rulers belonged to the Jī 姬 clan. 

Rank: Unknown. Zhànguó cè (Chǔ cè) mentions the ruler of Zhōu as hóu 侯. However, the record refers to the person of the 3rd century B.C. who was a favorite of the Chǔ king, and possibly had nothing to do with the former Zhōu rulers. 

Founded: Unknown.

Destroyed: Mentioned in the ZUO in the record for 701 B.C. Later (in an unknown period), it was conquered by Chǔ 楚.

Location: According to the Chinese traditional historiography, Zhōu was located either in the area of the modern Zhōulíngchéng 州陵城, Jiānlì 監利 district, Hubei province, or in the modern Hónghú 洪湖 in the same province.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-b68a0c6d-1905-4376-b948-23c5b774056d">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Zhōu 州 (also written as 舟; also called Chúnyú 淳于 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 411-416)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>