<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR2p0028-en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>郭店楚簡-語叢一(en)</title>
            <editor role="translator">Christoph Harbsmeier</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
                <edition>
                    <idno type="kanripo">KR2p0028-en</idno>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published electronically</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Generated from the TLS textfiles as exported on 2020-02-21. First source reported:GUODIAN, YUCONG 1, ed. Liu Zhao 2003,</p>
            <p>Translation of <bibl corresp="#KR2p0028">
                  <title xml:lang="och">郭店楚簡-語叢一(en)</title>
               </bibl> into <lang xml:lang="en">English</lang>.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-1a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-04-19T20:00:24.487+09:00">As a matter of principle, things originate coming from their absence&gt; where they were absent. [slip 104]</seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-1a.1">Li Ling transcribes literally 望, which is manifestly correct. The question is what word is intended. What makes the reading 亡 problematic is the fact that this word is current in Yucong, and always written differently in the rest of the text. On the other hand, nothing suggests that anything like hope is at issue in this repeated statement.The repetition of this line does suggest that this may be intended as the title of the collection of slips known as Yucong 1.凡 is not a universal quantifier, it is in fact a modal particle announcing abstract untensed discourse. The word does not mean "all", but marks a statement of principle, a generalisation of an abstract kind. The translation "All things..." "一切東西 is thus logically misleading.亡 should be read like 無. The reference cannot be to "nothingness" as such. Ice, for example, does not arise from nothing but from water. And children arise not from nothing but from their parents. The discourse, here, is not descriptive of how things arise. It is logical in that it focusses on the fact that for something to arise it has to have been absent. The concept of arising logically presupposes anterior absence.It is an interesting fact of epigraphy that 亡 is here written as 望. Spelling was not only unstandardised but also irregular within a given text, here as in the German works of Leibniz, whose very name even was of uncertain orthography (Check details)."Arising" is thought of in analogy to birth. But note that 物 regularly means living "creature" as well as 'things".Note that this slip comes twice. There have been different views on this, but I consider it to be the title of the collection of slips.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-1a.1">This is certainly not a very "Confucian" dogma, closely relating as it does to LAO 有生於無. Note the constant preoccupation with 生 "arising, originating", the question from what things arise. Compare the Greek preoccupations with ultimate beginnings.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-1a.1">The reading of 亡 as "nothing" makes no satisfactory sense and does not get any better by being universally accepted: things do arise from whatever they arise from, as ice from water, and what they arise from is not nothing. The origination of the whole universe is a different matter, but that is not at issue when 物 is the topic.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-1a.1">Note that the strips in YUCONG 1 are preoccupied with 生 "origination", and the character 生 occurs no less than 23 times in the 66 strips. This theorem, whether intended as opening or not, repeated in strips 1 and 104, characterises origination by the deliberately paradoxical statement that things arise from what they are not. A logically entirely valid point.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-1a.1">The graph for 由 is disconcertingly complex, but there is general agreement on the reading.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-2a.1" xml:lang="en">Heaven originates ?moral standards?; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-2a.2" xml:lang="en">man originates transformation (according to these standards)&gt; education. [strip 3] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-2a.1">The use of 倫 to refer to something like basic human standards designed by heaven would seem to argue against the position that these are inventions by the sages.In contradistinction to 化 "transformation&gt;ecucational transformation&gt; education" which is by human effort, what is transmitted or inculcated by such educational transformation, the 倫 "moral standards" themselves are given, as from Heaven/Nature.The emphasis here is probably not to be taken to be on Heaven as a legitimising metaphysical force, but rather on the non-man-made nature of moral standards.The transcriptions here are problematic and in need of detailed epigraphic discussion. My interpretation is based on the transcription as in Liu Zhao.Li Ling transcribes 倫 literally as 魚＋系, which is manifestly correct, but leaves open the question being what the intended word is. 倫 is conjectural, and Liu Zhao attempts to justify the plausibility of this conjecture phonologically.　Li Ling also refuses to transcribe the character Liu Zhao reads as 化. There is good reason for this reticence: the character recurs and does not generally allow for the reading 化.Moral standards are derived from Heaven or Nature. The "wherefrom" of these lún 倫 is Heaven, not human initiatives. Obligations deriving from these lún 倫　are not merely human conventions. They are Heaven-given. a matter of Nature.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-2a.2">化 "education" is contrasted with the cosmically justified basic standards, the association is with 教化, but 化 alone is currently used to refer to education insofar as it is efficacious.化 "education" inculcates those moral standards which have their origin in Heaven, and it has its "wherefrom" in man. The opposition 天、人 is topical in Warring States philosophy. But its subtle application to the basic concepts of moral philosophy here seems original.人 takes its generic abstract reference from 天. It is possible to read this is as "Humans originate transformations". But that would destroy the parallelism. The question is: is such precise interpretation of the nuances in 人 appropriate in the first place, or is Chinese vague. I believe in this case it is not vague.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.1" xml:lang="en">There being Heaven there is what is ordained by Heaven&gt; fate, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.2" xml:lang="en">there being Earth there is physical form (of mundane earthly objects); [slip 12] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.3" xml:lang="en">there being things there is outline&gt; physiognomy (of these things), </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.4" xml:lang="en">there being an exhaustible there is extension (of that exhaustible). [slip 14] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.5" xml:lang="en">There being Earth there is physical form, (although there could be form on a different basis, the moon?) </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.6" xml:lang="en">only there being an exhaustible [slip 6] will there be extension (of that exhaustible). [slip 7] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.1">Fate depends for its existence on Heaven. It is a natural function of the very existence of Heaven. Given that there is Heaven there will be fate, just as given that there is earth, it follows logically that there is physical shape 形. There is no 生 in this passage. This is not about the origination of things, but about the logical relation between categories.The pattern 有x有y recurs throughout Yucong. Li Ling's glosss "方" does not explain the contrast with 然後. The point of the present passage hinges on that distinction.天 is definitely not the sky. And yet it is the sky that is conceived as the physical manifestation of that more abstract revered entity we translate as "Heaven" which is here interpreted as the metaphysical source for Fate, which is taken to emanate from Heaven. The sequence that follows establishes a system of dependencies. The notion of Fate depends on that of an abstract "metaphysical" Heaven rather than on the mere spatial notion of a sky above.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.2">地 is perhaps not conceived as just the lump of earth, but on analogy with 天 as an agent. Earth differs from Heaven in that it involves concrete physical shape, it logically entails the existence of physical shape. It may also be taken as an agent giving shape.形 must refer to terrestrial physical form, abstractly. The patterns in Heaven are not 天形 but 天文. Contrast also the notion of xiàng 象 "abstract image".</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.3">容 are the individualised characteristic physical physiognomy of things/creatures. The existence of things logically entails the existence of such a 容 "physiognomy". 容 must refer to the concrete outlines and physiognomy of individual things, as opposed to form as such. See GD.YUCONG 1.28 其體/有容，</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.4">This line claims that there being an exhaustible is a sufficient condition for there being something extended/extension. Thus 厚 does not refer to the feature of being thick: thin things also have thickness, namely a small thickness. The point that needs to be emphasised is that the text clearly rises above the simple feature-abstraction "thickness" to a higher level of abstraction in the direction of "thickness&gt;extension".盡 is used as a technical term here, referring to exhaustibility&gt;finiteness, abstractly. The nominal nature of the use of this word here is made explicit by the fact that 盡 comes after 有. Now there is room for controversy whether what comes after 有 is the object or the subject of 有, but there can be no question that what comes after 有 is nominal.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.5">Earth is the sufficient real cause for physical shape to appear in this world. It is NOT a necessary condition, since the statement 有馬有形 would also be true.The concluding opposition here makes a highly abstract subtle point: the parallelism between 有地有形 and 有盡有厚 is systematically misleading: given terrestrial conditions there is form, but ONLY when there is finiteness is there extension. In other words: one can imagine non-terrestrial form, but according to this text one cannot imagine anything hòu 厚 "extended" that is not finite.The repetition of this proposition is itself a way of not just asserting it again: it is a way of holding the proposition up for abstract consideration.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-3a.6">This line claims that there being something exhaustible is a necessary as well as sufficient condition for there being something extended.Note the repetition of the unmarked abstraction in the terms 盡 and 厚. These are abstract terms of the philosophy of nature. They are not abstract terms of Confucian moral thinking, but they clearly formed part of the theoretical discourse of the present bundle of bamboo slips - which will turn out to show clear signs to belonging to a broadly "Confucian" tradition.If we understand this correctly, the text declares the "exhausibility" of something to be a nessessary condition for there to be "extension". Not only does exhaustibility give rise to extension, it is a necessary condition for the existence of extension.而後: from the point of view of rhetorical analysis, this repetition with the addition of two characters might seem to be a case of auto-correction, but the truth of this expanded version does not invalidate the truth of the shorter version.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.1" xml:lang="en">There being Heaven there is what is ordained by Heaven&gt; fate, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-04-19T20:23:31.426+09:00">there being things there are names (defining/delimiting these things); [slip 2]</seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-04-19T20:25:25.489+09:00">there being things there are outlines&gt; physiognomies (marking out these things as the the things they are),</seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.4" xml:lang="en">there being designation, there is a name (applied to things designated by it). [slip 13] (Desingation must be by names.) </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-04-19T20:31:49.288+09:00">There being what is decreed (by heaven, there is meaningful pattern (made meaningful by what is is byHeaven),</seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.6" xml:lang="en">and only when there are names are there moral standards. [slip 5] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.1">The present sequence takes the same point of departure as the preceding. But it proceeds differently</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.2">Down below we learn the paradoxical truth that 有生乎名 that "(claimed) existence has its origin in names". We need to be able to reconcile these two statements, or we need to acknowlege that Yucong 1 contains contradictory dicta.The text LAO pretends that one can be nameless and still exist. This text takes as its (hard-nosed Donald Davidsonian) point of departure that for a thing to (be said to) exist it must have a name. Without a name identifying it it cannot be said to exist. The ineffable is, by being called the ineffable, eo ipso a dictum. The Way that cannot be told has just got its name, and because of that can be said to exist or not to exist.The text establishes the epiphenomenal nature of names: these arise on the basis of pre-existing things. The point is natural enough in the case of names for natural kinds and natural phenomena. But we note quietly that it does not apply to such abstract programmatic concepts (or figments of the political imagination) as that of "democracy". Concepts need not be descriptive of what is. They can, for example, be programmatic of what one works towards. This was not a point recognised in the present text.Note that the rhyme is cacophonic: the first rhyme has the level tone, the second the falling tone (or whatever the Warring States antecedents were of the tones).</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.4">稱 is a general term for predication by words, or to identifying reference. Whenever there is successful predication, there is a name. 無名, if it makes any sense, is a name of something, whatever the expression itself may seem to pretend or imply.稱 is linguistic reference to things. By the nature of things this must be by the use of names.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.5">命 involves meaningful pattern (of development and action) intended by Heaven.命 is what is ordained, hence the translation "fate". Given this ordained cosmological context there is 文 "meaningful pattern". (But meaningful patterns could come have come about in other ways: there is no 而後 "only then" here. There may be meaningful pattern 文 by mere sú 俗 convention.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-4a.6">Assuming Liu Zhao's transcription is correct, this would be a remarkable statement. Moral standards 倫 can and will only crystalise when there are names to designate them. Inarticulate, unnamed or unarticulated standards seem excluded by this formulation.Li Ling is not committed on the reading of 倫, as in 1.2.Here comes the paradox: the human moral standards depend, for their existence, on the existence of names for them. Thus the study of names, the study of concepts and of their interrelations becomes a central concern for Confucian moral philosophy. 正名 becomes an important discipline in Confucian thought. To put it anachronistically: the philosophy of language should be a core discipline in Confucian moral thinking. Thus, IF we assume Liu Zhao's reading 倫, the present sequence would turn out to provide a fundamental justification of the 儒經 method applied throughout Yucong 1.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-5a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-04-19T21:29:26.402+09:00">When there being things (i.e. a subject matter) there is a "wherefrom" and a "tail&gt;whereto" (when their beginnings and ends are understood)</seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-5a.2" xml:lang="en">only then does teaching arise. [slip 11] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-5a.1">Teaching arises when reasons and purposes are under discussion with relation to things. Of course, most teaching today consists in inculcating politically or culturally correct attitudes and opinions, just as in ancient China much teaching consisted in inculcating traditional values and attitudes as well as information. But the present text is programmatic: "Proper teaching" arises only when reasons and purposes are at issue. If we understand this correctly, then slip 11 is again a highly charged programmatic statement in support of the methodology of a rújīng 儒經 to parallel the Mòjīng.物 is again highly abstract here: for teaching to arise, the existence of something as a subject as such is not enough. The subject must be circumscribed by a 由 and a 尾, it must have head and tail, it must be well-defined enough to be transmitted in teaching.The figurative use of 尾 which we must assume here is surprising enough to make one suspicious of the identification of the character. Our interpretation must remain tentative.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-5a.2">The pregnant use of jiào 教 to refer to "teaching that deserves the name of teaching" is an example of a common rhetorical device in classical Chinese.而後...生: Note the recurrent theme, which is the necessary conditions for the arising of something, or of something originating. The "thing" that arises here is the abstract practice of 教 "teaching". Note that this abstract practice by humans itself is said to "orginate", so that teaching is not only regarded as a human act, but also as a social phenomenon with an origin of its own.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-6a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-04-19T21:32:17.903+09:00">When there being life there is cognition,</seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-6a.2" xml:lang="en">only then is there liking and disliking. [slip 8, last character on slip 9] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-6a.1">It appears that the two existential clauses here might have to be taken as coordinate. But it is also true that 知 "awareness" depends on life.Li Ling links this with a preceding 有仁有智，有義有禮.Compare XUN: 人有氣、有生、有知，亦且有義，故最為天下貴也。There is no question here of two conditions having to be fulfilled: life and awareness. There being life, there may come to be awareness. And only when this condition is met can there be any liking and disliking of things. The logic is this: one must be aware of what one wants to like or dislike. Without awareness no liking/disliking.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-6a.2">Appetitive behaviour depends on the subject being endowed with both life and (depending on life, on) awareness of what is aimed for or avoided.Adding the final 生 from slip 9 is pleasing as part of the puzzle and links this theorem tightly into the context of the discussion of conceptual 生 "origination/genealogy"This theorem opposes again cases of interdependent existence with origination of something on the basis of these.好惡: one is of course free to interpret this literally as "fondness and hatred", but in the argumentative context at hand, the idea is much more likely to be closer to "likes and dislikes", "preferences".</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-7a.1" xml:lang="en">There being (a sense of) kindheartedness, there is proper (empathetic) understanding, [note the changing meaning of this keyword] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-7a.2" xml:lang="en">there being (a sense of) rectitude, there is ritual propriety; [slip 16] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-7a.3" xml:lang="en">there being a (sense of) what is admirable, there is excellence. [slip 15] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-7a.1">These implicit linkings between the existence of various abstract dimensions require careful classification. In this instance the proposition is that kind-heartedness presupposes awareness.知:　We must assume that 知 here is not simply "awareness" as before, and certainly not "factual knowledge": the reference here is to "proper understanding", which is the most current of the meanings of the word.知:　Proper understanding is based on empathetic kind-hearted concern. Without such concern, no "proper understanding", which for "Confucians" is especially and primarily of moral principles.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-7a.2">禮:　Ritual propriety arises from, and concretises into social custom, what is appropriate and right. The logical point is this: the conventional social norms of ritual propriety derive their normative obligatoriness not from any social authority prescribing these conventional norms, but from yì 義 "the standard of what is right and appropriate" which itself is not merely conventional but part and parcel of the lún 倫 "moral principles" , which we learn are Heaven-given and not merely human-invented. Rules of ritual propriety, on the other hand, are human-instituted.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-7a.3">Beauty presupposes excellence and is a special kind of excellence.Excellence in humans is an ability up to standards of 美 "admirableness&gt;beauty". There is first a standard of what is admirable, and then - given this standard - one may succeed in living up to that standard so as to become shàn 善. The appraisal of something as 善 "excellent" depends on an ability to 美 "appreciate as admirable".</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-8a.1" xml:lang="en">There being sages&gt;sagehood there is excellence (living up to the ideals of that sagehood). [slip 17] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-8a.1">Excellence derives from the kind of standard of what is admirable that ontogenetically derives from sages and their sageliness or sagehood. Excellence derives from the exemplary existence of paradigmatic sages. These sages create those standards by their exemplary conduct. Thus in a sense, these sages themselves do not live up to those standards, they create the conditions for their existence.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-8a.1">善: The word cannot here refer to excellent individuals, I think. It is the very notion of excellence that is at issue.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.1" xml:lang="en">When Heaven originated all the different kinds of creatures </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.2" xml:lang="en">man counted as the noblest of these. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.3" xml:lang="en">As for the Way [slip 18] of man, (which gives him this dignity) </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.4" xml:lang="en">in some cases [slip 19] it emerges from the inside (of man)/is endogenic, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.5" xml:lang="en">in other cases it enters from the outside (of man)/is exogenic. [slip 20] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.1">Heaven alone as the source of the existence of the creatures in this world is a surprising notion. Ordinarily it is Heaven and Earth that are taken to engender the myriad creatures or things. Is Heaven taken here to fashion the myriad things in the mode of a partly personalised creator? The phrasing does not exclude this reading, but it certainly does not enforce it.The first line does not argue for any theory of the origin of all the different kinds of things/creatures: it assumes that Heaven originated these creatures. There is no discourse about Earth originating all kinds of creatures here. The terestrial world of things/creatures is a supra-terrestrial heavenly product, according to this way of speaking.The implication is that it is by 天命 that of all the different kinds of creatures man is the noblest: Heaven engendered things thus. There is no implication that Heaven 造 "created" the creatures thus.百物: This variant for 萬物 does come 6 times, for example in LIJI, and also 11 times in ZHOULI. The difference between the two terms needs investigation. Note that 物 in these constructions is generic. Thus, literally, we should read "the myriad kinds of things" rather than the "10 000 things".</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.2">為 creates a superlative with 貴, i.e. with all graded "adjectival" verbs like 大,小,賤. The thought is standard throughout Confucian literature.This important notion of the "nobility" of man needs close attention. There is no 馬道 "way of the horse". Horses do have patterns of behaviour. Even desired patterns of behaviour. What they do not have is rules or commended obligatory norms of behaviour. Yucong 1 is concerned not with those general patterns, but with these obligatory norms.貴: The superlative marked with 爲 is of course common. The important point is that the superlative meaning does not come from context. 為貴 always makes superlative phrases.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.3">道 is used in a way that brings it close to a plural, an abstract plural "proper standards of behaviour". We note that 義 "notions of what is right" are being counted in Warring States China.Consistently with its general methodology, the text asks about the "wherefrom". The analytically important issue is the non-homogeneous nature of the Way: it has endogenic and exogenic parts. In this sense it is not one homogeneous way.道: the Way is here construed as consisting of separate parts of different provenance. This is probably not a case of 道 being used as a count noun in the plural, but the question needs to be raised, exactly how we are to construe the semantics of 道, and the way 或 quantifies into this semantic domain.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.4">These uses of 或 do bring the word close to meaning "or". But one never knows whether this is just a translation effect.中 refers to the figurative psychological inside of man: the autogenous norms generated by man as given birth to by Heaven.由: Note the way in which 由 functions as a sustained recurrent theme in this material. It is not a coincidence that neither 自nor 從 are used here.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-9a.5">外 refers to the figuratively psychological outside of man, that is to say norms imposed from the social context man lives in.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-10a.1" xml:lang="en">As for those that emerge from the inside/the endogenic ones these are: </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-10a.2" xml:lang="en">these are kind-heartedness, devoted effort, and good faith. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-10a.3" xml:lang="en">As for those [which enter from the outside </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-10a.4" xml:lang="en">they are ritual propriety, music, and punishment.CONJECTURAL EMENDATION] [slip 21] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-10a.1">This continues 1.9. The three virtues are identified as endogenic.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-10a.3">The text is so coherent that one can indeed venture fairly confident conjectures on missing parts of the text.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-10a.4">禮樂刑 See 禮樂刑政 from LIJI.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-11a.1" xml:lang="en">(Kind-heartedness-and-rectitude&gt;) morality one takes as a target&gt;norm. [slip 93] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-11a.1">仁義, here as elsewhere, is probably not a coordination of two concepts but one abstract concept of morality referring in a general way to all the virtues.臬 would be a worryingly recondite word to use in this context.The mode of existence of morality is to serve as a standard, its form of existence is as something to go by. Not as a model 法 because humans are not virtues, they take virtues as their standard and the sages as their model. It is this subtle but crucial distinction which motivates the avoidance of 法 and the choice of the rare word 臬 (if indeed our transcription is to be trusted).Li Ling places this after slip 103 禮不同，不豐不殺。仁義 does not refer to these two virtues but to moral virtues in general, here as very often in Warring States literature.臬 refers to a target in Han times. Here it must be what one aims for and morally aspires to, tries to conform to, a norm. The logical analytical point is again straightforward and stringent. 仁義 is not a concept that describes or refers to commendable action. Also, it is not a psychological concept that refers to moral sentiments of any kind. This is identified, by a very strange word, as a very strange concept which must be likened to a moral target, something one feels obliged to aspire to conform to, a norm.One may wish to deplore the enigmatic nature of this statement, but if we understand it properly it is an honest attempt to identify conceptually the special nature of normative concepts.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-12a.1" xml:lang="en">Loving (moral) excellence is kind-heartedness [slip 92] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-12a.1">愛善 is not a currently attested combination, and it is surprising to find it in this definition. Could this be part of a discussion concening the proper object of the kind of love involved in kind-heartedness? In that case we would translate as in the bracket.The moral ecellence in question here is that of which the ontogenesis is in the emulation of the sages, as we have seen above (slip 17), and which logically depends on an appreciation of what is admirable (slip 15).One notes that this logical analysis of the concept of kind-heartedness&gt;Goodness formally derives the concept from two concepts that of moral excellnce on the one hand, and the figurative moral love/affection for this.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-13a.1" xml:lang="en">The funeral/mourning for deceased </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-13a.2" xml:lang="en">is the starting-point of kind-heartedness. [slip 98] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-13a.1">The real-life psychological basis of kind-heartedness in crucial family rituals is asserted.One's love for moral excellence, 仁, has its paradigmatic origin in the moral obligations one feels on the occasion of funerals one is responsible for, such as funerals for one's parents.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-13a.2">端 refers to the incipient psychological manifestation of something, as in Mencius. This incipient manifestation, while crucial, must not be confused with the origin which is discussed in terms of 由 "the wherefrom", and 生 "origination".</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-14a.1" xml:lang="en">When those above and below all take up their proper places that is called good faith. [slip 65] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-14a.2" xml:lang="en">[But] good faith is by no means gets to the stage of equality. [slip 66] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-14a.1">The discussion of good faith as relating to status differences is highly original. This seems to be part of a debate about the distinct ways in which good faith applies differently to people of different status, but applies also to people of different status. 忠 is trusty loyal effort for those above, and 信 is typically interprete as good faith among friends as well as keeping one's word in general.Good faith is customarily defined with a focus on an obligation of subordinates. Not so here: trustiness is required of all and is conceived in an original manner as living up to the moral obligations implied by one's place in society.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-14a.2">至 "reach; perfect" is puzzling here. The philosophical point seems to be that good faith between two persons is not a way of achieving full equality between them.Having made this anti-hierarchical definition, the next slip points out that this equal (qí 齊) obligation by no means implies that those who equally have such obligations are themselves equal.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-14a.2">齊 is used here in an intellectually exciting way, not just as "evened out, level", but apparently referring to the(non-applicable) absence of distinctions between 上 and 下, something very much like equality.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.1" xml:lang="en">As for the engendering/originating of things it is not a purposeful action! </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.2" xml:lang="en">The (outward) punishment [slip 62] engenders (inward) virtue&gt;a strong sense of what is morally right, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.3" xml:lang="en">(inward) virtue engenders (outward) ritual propriety, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.4" xml:lang="en">ritual propriety engenders music/dance, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.5" xml:lang="en">and from the music/dance [slip 24] one understands the punishments. [slip 25] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.6" xml:lang="en">slip 63. See 1.16 for translation </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.1">If I understand this correctly, the thought is again unusual: 無為, normally "non-action&gt; non-assertive action" is used here to refer to "non-deliberate action, non-intentional action". Engendering, then, in the cases here under discussion is not a naturalistic process.This opening rhetorical question is extraordinary. It constitutes an emphatically maintained proposition, which in this case is not only stated, but the rest of the passage must be read as justification for this emphatic proposition. It is line 5 which explains the argument.The aim of punishment is the punishing of misdeed, and yet this originates virtue. Virtue is unconcerned with ritual, but it brings about a sense of ritual propriety. Ritual propriety is not concerned with music and dance, and yet it is at the origin of it.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.2">Again, the thought that virtue is engendered by the (threat of) punishment, though not so far-fetched, is unusual when stated in this stark way. Meanwhile, it is not alien to "legalist" thought.Li Ling does not link slip 62 to slip 24. See Yucong 1.67 for his solution.德 cannot be elevated charismatic power here. The reference seems to be to the sense of decency that puts one on the way towards decency.德 is the psychological disposition as opposed to the norms of morality 仁義. This psychological disposition is coldly, unsentimentally diagnosed engendered by (the threat of) punishment, if we understand this text correctly: an extraordinary case, if so, of Confucian psychological realism.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.3">德 as a commitment to virtuous behaviour is a natural source for its concretisation in the ritual propriety.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.4">The birth of music from the spirit of ritual propriety is a natural thing to postulate, given the role of music/dancing in ritual.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.5">It is important to remember that this item is pieced together form separate strips. But if we follow this ingeneous move, the final line would contain the usual surprising twist: an indirect link demonstrated by the genealogy above between music and what is punished, i.e. aesthetically exorcised by music.The intellectual mode changes. The discourse is not about conceptual genealogy but intention and cognitive structure. It is the intentionality in the processes of 生 here discussed which enables one, starting out from the music, to understand the punishments which originally were introduced in order to lead first to virtue, then to ritual and finally to music.From the music/dance which celebrates a higher sensibility vis-a-vis ritual and ritual propriety one understands the function of punishments which in a realistically described causal chain triggers of the moral-normative-behaviour syndrome.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-15a.6">It is only when one properly understands the importance of ritual propriety, that one can understand the importance of punishments which are designed to promote - indirectly - just that sense of ritual propriety. I take the text to try to make something of an excuse for assigning to punishments such a central role in the pragmatic ontogenesis of ritual and musical elegance. (One notes in passing, that there is no focus or even mention of fǎ 法 "law', so that there is no manifest "legalist" influence to be diagnosed here.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-16a.1" xml:lang="en">Only after one properly understands ritual propriety does one properly understand what is to be punished. ... [slip 63] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-16a.1">On the one hand punishment itself has to follow ritual, and on the other hand what is punished must be what infringes ritual propriety and cannot be dealt with by ritual means alone.This is another proposition concerned with cognitive structure. One only understands punishments and their purpose if one understands the intentional structure of ritual propriety. For punishments are designed/intended to originate/produce a sense of ritual propriety and a practice in accordance with ritual propriety. This passage is quite correctly linked with YUCONG 1.15.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-17a.1" xml:lang="en">Punishment is by no means a matter of severity. [slip 64] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-17a.1">Li Ling's reading of the third character as 嚴 seems plausible.The text distances itself from "legalist" insistence on strictness of punishments. What matters is not strict prevention of transgression but soft encouragement of the moral sensibility 德.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-18a.1" xml:lang="en">Ritual </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-18a.2" xml:lang="en">one practises in accordance with basic human instincts [slip 31] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-18a.3" xml:lang="en">it is what moderates and gives meaningful pattern to (these instincts). [slip 97] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-18a.1">The link of ritual propriety with basic moral instincts/sensibiliies is traditional.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-18a.2">There are no less than six close echoing passages to this one in TLS alone. We need to know why this particular passage was found worthy to be included as a proposition in the present set. The reason is that this is an example of analytic definition which is in the spirit of YUCONG 1. Ritual propriety is taken to reconcile two things: natural sentiments 情 and moderated elegance 文節.One performs ritual in accordance with basic human instincts. However, ritual does not simply express and serve these instincts: and it is through this ritual that human instincts/basic emotional tendencies are culturally patterned and moderated. Civilised, one might say. Our text problematises the conceptual place of ritual propriety in the overall scheme of conceptual schemes.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-19a.1" xml:lang="en">It is only after excellence is sorted out that music/dance arises. [slip 32] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-19a.1">This proposition identifies a logical precondition of the emergence of music 樂, the ontogenesis of music is said to presuppose goodness, and a patterning of it. The patterning of goodness is not in itself music. It is the crucial precondition of music which is identified in this proposition.Elswhere, the link music is to the idea of a regular measure 度 (See 1.21 below). Here, the focus is on the moral connection, and the patterning of this moral dimension which must be at the bottom of (proper) music. Note that frivolous or lascivious music like the music of Zheng is not intended to be accounted for by this definition.Music/dance is here interpreted as a result of the ordering of that excellence which in turn has its source in the emulation of sages or sageliness. The essence of the logical analysis is in the recognition that music/dance does not simply celebrate goodness as such. Music and dance depend on an overall ordering and patterning of this excellence which gives it an aesthetic dimension.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-20a.1" xml:lang="en">The man of worth is able to sort out things. [slip 54] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-20a.1">理 is to impose desirable pattern on what does not have such a pattern. In 1.19 the patterning of goodness was placed at the origin of music. Here, the origin of this patterning itself is brought out: the patterning is due to the 賢者 "person of talent; worthy" who is capable of realising this patterning. What is needed for proper and relevant patterning is the ability of the man of talent or the worthy.How, one may ask, does the man of talent fit into this conceptual scheme: his part is to achieve this ordering and sorting out of the excellence with which the sages have inspired him, so that this excellence can become an inspiration for music/dance on the one hand, but also, on the other hand, so that its practice can become an important aid to government.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.1" xml:lang="en">Propriety arises from being serious about action; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.2" xml:lang="en">music arises from proper measure. [slip 33] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.3" xml:lang="en">When ritual is evenly adjusted, and when music is taken to have the supernatural power, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.4" xml:lang="en">then there is intense intimacy; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.5" xml:lang="en">when the music is over-elaborate [slip 34] and the ritual is taken to have the supernatural power, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.6" xml:lang="en">then there is mutual disrespect between people. [slip 35] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.1">The origin of ritual propriety in seriousness could also be expressed as seriousness being the necessary condition for a sense of ritual propriety to arise. No sense of ritual is a sense of ritual if it does not include a certain sense of seriousness regarding ritual behaviour. The nature of this seriousness may be disputed, as it is by Kristoffer Schipper, but the general principle cannnot be in doubt, even by those (like my very good friend Frits Staal) who would assert the meaninglessness of ritual.These conceptual analyses focus on the anthropological bases of ritual propriety and music. The basis for ritual propriety in the human make-up is identified as the non-flippant, non-frivolous, non-indifferent emotional engagedness in what one is doing which may be called seriousness.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.2">Pythagoreans will heartily agree that quantified measure is of the essence, and we must hope that the transcription is correct.It is the proportionality of things that already fascinated the Pythagoreans and which inspired in them a keen interest in music. "Measure, proper measure" in this context, is essentially proportional measure, proper measure, non-arbitrary proportionality. These indeed may be regarded as among the important sources from which music grows.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.3">When music elevates and sanctifies what is even and plain, it promotes sanctioned and confirmed intimacy.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.5">Elaborate music, lacking in the proper measure 度, where the the efficacy of the whole procedure lies in the physical ritual itself, and where ritual efficacy is unsupproted by psychologically efficacious neasured music leads ultimately to mutual disrespect.Li Ling provides no current-character reading for 繁.Over-elaborate music impairs seriousness and results in informal impoliteness. Similarly, when ritual itself is taken to be self-sufficiently and suprnaturally efficacious, then this leads to inappropriate informality outside that ritual. The text may be hard to understand, but it is not incomprehensible.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-21a.6">The numinous efficacy of ritual as such, seems to be identified here as a source of 慢 "ritual negligence" in real relations between people. If this is the meaning of the text, we have again a highly original thought: sacred/numinous/efficacious music is taken to be at the source of close and intimate social cohesion.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-22a.1" xml:lang="en">[slip 112] </seg>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-23a.1" xml:lang="en">Rituals do differ, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-23a.2" xml:lang="en">but they should be neither too multifarious nor too scanty. [slip 103] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-23a.1">This coincides with LJ 10.1.26. Cf also HN 7: 故四夷之禮不同. The proposition that ritual practices differ fits well into the pattern of provocative sayings in YUCONG 1. Since these differ, they are in some sense arbitrary.Rituals being conventional, they will differ from one social group to another. One might conclude that they are not only conventional but entirely arbitrary.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-23a.2">But there are constraints on acceptable differences between ritual prescriptions: they must be neither too multifarious nor to scanty. So this they have in common. It is this subtle paradox which may have qualified this phrase for inclusion. It remains, of course, an open queston whether the LJ passage quotes from this, or the other way around, or whether both text quote from a third common source. (The third possibility strikes one as perhaps most likely.)In spite of the presence of a paragraph mark, Li Ling links this up with strip 103 仁義為之？？But this is not so: they have this in common that they manage to keep a proper measure.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-24a.1" xml:lang="en">Only when one understands oneself does one understand others, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-24a.2" xml:lang="en">only when one understands others does one [slip 26] understand ritual propriety, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-24a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-05-03T10:26:33.654+09:00">only when one does ritual propriety does one understand proper conduct/know how to act. [slip 27]</seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-24a.1">This chain of cognitive presuppositions begins with the Socratic gnothi sauton "know thyself". It ends in the practical aim of knowing HOW TO act.One only understands others on the analogy with oneself.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-24a.2">The mediation between understanding of oneself and knowledge how one should act is ritual propriety, which must be based on a proper understanding of others, because ritual propriety essentially involves interaction with others whose feelings and interests one must understand.Empathy with others, understanding of other's needs and desires, is a necessary condition for understanding ritual propriety which is the regulation of one's formalised and ritualised relations with others.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-24a.3">行 must refer to action in general, not action as part of ritual propriety. The proposition is that knowing how to act in general presupposes an understanding of the alternatives left open by ritual propriety in the first place.Understanding proper conduct and proper behaviour depends on a proper appreciation of those ritualised relations to others. Thus the proper logical analysis of action involves not only an agent and an action. Action is essentially interpersonal, interactive with others, involving an appreciation of ritual propriety.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.1" xml:lang="en">Only when one understands what Heaven working towards, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.2" xml:lang="en">and when one understands what man is working towards, [slip 29] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.3" xml:lang="en">does one understand the Way; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.4" xml:lang="en">and only when one understands the Way does one understand fate. [slip 30] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.5" xml:lang="en">Only when one's knowledge is broad does one understand fate. [slip 28] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.1">One notes again the omission of Earth in this new cognitive genealogy. The Way is a matter between Man and Heaven.As elsewhere in Yucong 1, the focus is on the distinction between Heaven/Nature and Man.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.3">Note that understanding the Way properly is not the same as 得道 "attaining to it", which is a practical matter.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-25a.4">命 "fate" comes close in these contexts to meaning "one's place in the world, cf. die Stellung des Menschen im Kosmos (Max Scheler)"</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.1" xml:lang="en">The Songs </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.2" xml:lang="en">are that wherein one has collected together the aspirations of former and present [slip 38] times. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.3" xml:lang="en">The Documents </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.4" xml:lang="en">.... [slip 44] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.5" xml:lang="en">The Rituals </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.6" xml:lang="en">are records of the conduct of interaction. [slip 42] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.7" xml:lang="en">The Music </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.8" xml:lang="en">either produces or transforms (moral sensibilities) through education. [slip 43] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.9" xml:lang="en">The Changes </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.10" xml:lang="en">are that wherein one has collected together the ways of Heaven and the ways of [slip 36] man. [slip 37] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.11" xml:lang="en">The Spring and Autumn </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.12" xml:lang="en">are that wherein one has collected the significant [slip 40] events of all times. [slip 41] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.1">This is a very important early discussion of the six classics.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.4">One suspects that the Documents were also explained in terms of 會 "making a collection".</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.5">Note that ritual propriety is explained in terms of the conduct and proper ordering of 交 "interaction", rather than in terms of action as such. The explanation seems to be about the matter of ritual rather than the book of ritual, just as the explanation of 樂 is about music rather than about classics of music.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.6">Liu Zhao has 序 for 述.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.7">The explanation of the significance of music has a puzzling opposition of 生 with 教 which - as noted - seems one has to take to refer not to any classic about music, but to music itself.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.8">Yet another case in which 或 comes close to being disjunctive in this small set.Note the concept of 化 elsewhere in Yucong 1. 教化 is a current combination, and the essence of 教 is indeed the transformation of existing attitudes and sensibilities.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-26a.11">This is a comprehensive interpretation and rationalisation of the significance of the 六藝, or the 六經. Indeed, this is probably the earliest evidence we have of this systematisation of the classics, avant la lettre.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-27a.1" xml:lang="en">One investigates the Way of Heaven in order to transform the spirits of the people. [slip 68] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-27a.1">This explicit rejection of a "scientific" cognitive purpose of the study of the Way of Heaven, suggests perhaps that there were those who studied the Ways of Heaven for their own sake.氣 is indeed what links the human world into the natural world. The diction here is disciplined and precise.This is a deliberate paradox: in order to transform the ways of the people, what is studied is not the ancient sages or human affairs of any kind, but the Way of Heaven (probably because it is Heaven who is is the source of the existence of the people in the first place.I have to take the reading 察 on trust.The philosophy not of the Way of Man but of the Way of Heaven is assumed as being part of the philosophical inquiry, and is justified by reference to the educational transformation of the vital spirits of the people.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.1" xml:lang="en">Generally, whatever has blood and breath/vital spirits </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.2" xml:lang="en">always has joy [slip 45] and anger, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.3" xml:lang="en">and it has careful attention and seriousness(?); </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.4" xml:lang="en">its body [slip 46] has a characteristic physicognomy, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.5" xml:lang="en">it has colour and it makes sounds, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.6" xml:lang="en">it has a smell [slip 47] and it has a taste, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.7" xml:lang="en">it has vital energies (a personal style?) and (psychological) aspirations. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.8" xml:lang="en">Generally, in things/creatures [slip 48] there is what is inalienable-and-basic, and there are transformations, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.9" xml:lang="en">they have what they end in, and what they begin. [slip 49] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.1">The opposition between what has blood and vital energy/breath on the one hand, and things/creatures in general does seem intended, since the passage beginning 凡物 does not begin a new bamboo slip.有血氣者 is a current term in Warring States scientific discourse. It involves a reading of 氣 which is different from that in the 1.27, but not entirely unrelated. In line 7 the passage reverts to someting like the reading in 1.27: vital spirits&gt;personal style.The present passage, as well as the one that follows, are concerned with something like philosophical anthropology. And it makes a basic distinction between living creatures with blood and breath on the one hand and creatures generally.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.2">The identification of 喜 and 怒 as representative of the emotions/passions is traditional.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.3">The collocation 慎／莊 is surprising.If we read the character 莊 correctly, our text does attribute seriousness - a concept that is important elsewhere in Yucong 1 - to all animate beings.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.4">This inventory of what is in a physical body has an almost Aristotelian flavour: it constitutes what seems to aspire to be a catalogue of categories of features present in a body.Note the recurrent theme of 容 "physiognomy" at this point.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.5">Note that these 有 ... 有 phrases are coordinate and quite unlike the conditional sequences we have seen above.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.7">Since the subject is 有血氣者, claiming that these 有氣 is odd, unless one takes the meaning to be affected by that of 志 "aspiration" to mean something like "personal style".In conjunction with 志 the always puzzling term 氣 must have a different meaning from that at the beginning of this passage.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.8">The opposition 本／化 distinguishes between what is essential and what is subject to essential change or transformation. When used in this way, 本 refers to what is inalienably present and thus essential in something.The text draws a distinction between an immutable essence 本 and what can change 化 in every creature.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-28a.9">This would seem to claim not only that nothing is ever-lasting in the future, but that everything has beginning. One would need to know whether 天 and 地 are things, and whether indeed the 宇宙 is or is not a thing. Without delimitation of the range of things over which one is generalising here it is difficult to assess the range of what is being said.The text speaks as if all things have a finite life span, which is true of all creatures but not in any obvious way for mountains and planets. Perhaps, in this context, the term 物 does indeed refer to finite creatures of all kinds rather than to objects of any kind. They die, and while alive they procreate, when dead they are the beginnings of what they are transformed into.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.1" xml:lang="en">Physiognomy and facial expression are the domain of the eyes; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.2" xml:lang="en">the sounds are the domain of [slip 50] the ears; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.3" xml:lang="en">the smells are the domain of the nose; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.4" xml:lang="en">the taste is the domain of the [slip 51] mouth; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.5" xml:lang="en">the vital spirits are the domain of the physiognomy; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.6" xml:lang="en">the aspirations are the domain of the heart. [slip 52] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.1">The categories are subsumed under the metaphorical "administration" of organs. Just as Heaven and hell are interpreted in terms of bureaucracies, so is the internal organisation of the person. In particular, the metaphorical use of 司 suggests thatThis passage looks trivial until one realises that it is part of a project of systematic physical anthropology.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.5">When the author gets to the 氣 he runs into an apparent spot of trouble: but in attributing this to the metaphorical administration of the 容 is to locate the control of personal style in the physiognomy, the physiognomy itself being controlled by the eyes.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-29a.6">The absence of 也 in the last line seems fortuitous.Note that apparently 志 never refers to an organ of the will.The text provides a draft of the systematic anthropology of basic human functionalities.Li Ling adds a 也 AFTER the punctuation mark.(!!)</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.1" xml:lang="en">If one makes a point of showing filial piety, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.2" xml:lang="en">then that is not filial piety; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.3" xml:lang="en">if one makes a point of showing brotherly love, [slip 55] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.4" xml:lang="en">then that is not brotherly love. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.5" xml:lang="en">These things one cannot make a deliberate point of practising, [slip 56] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.6" xml:lang="en">and yet they must not be left unpractised. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.7" xml:lang="en">If one deliberately makes a point of practising them, [slip 57] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.8" xml:lang="en">this is not it(right); </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.9" xml:lang="en">and if one refuses to practise them, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.10" xml:lang="en">that is (also) not it(right). [slip 58] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.11" xml:lang="en">Rectitude one can in no way deliberately make a point of acting out. [strip 53] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.12" xml:lang="en">The person one is one can in no way deliberately make a point of being. [slip 83] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.1">The pregnant use of 為 "practice as a deliberate strategy" is characteristic of this set of strips. Compare the opening passages in HF 20 where this reasoning is applied to 無為.If we follow the text as it stands, this remarkably coherent passage makes a revolutionary and paradoxical statement to the effect that virtues cannot be practised, and that what one is one can never go about being, as a deliberate act.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.2">此 seems used very much like the Lu dialect 斯 "then".孝 is genuine filial piety only when it is morally spontaneous and not part of a deliberate family strategy or moral strategy. Filial piety must "come from the heart".</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.4">悌 is primarily the devotion one owes to one's eldest brother - particularly in view of the fact that after the death of one's father he is destined to become the formal head of the family/household.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.5">The text continues with a play on words: one CANNOT go about these things through a strategic course of action; and one MUST NOT fail to practice these things.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.7">Lines 7 to 10 explain the word-play: cultivating these virtues strategically is wrong. So is refusing to practice them. The crux is in the difference between negated and unnegated 為.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.9">Note that 弗 "refuse to" is used instead of 不 "not". The characteristic nuance of 弗 is crucial for the interpretation of this passage.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-30a.10">This piece connects directly with what follows.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-31a.1" xml:lang="en">The person one is one can in no way deliberately make a point of being. [slip 83] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-31a.1">This is an explosive proposition. Being what one is can never be a matter of deliberate strategic action 為. "Be thyself" is an injunction that is not just hard to live up to: it is If one is what one is, one mus be spontaneously what one is, 沒有做作地. The person one is is not the person one "puts on".Alternatively: "The person one is" no one can deliberately make a point of being.Li Ling appends this to slip 58 in spite of the fact that there is a punctuation mark at the end.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-32a.1" xml:lang="en">[slip 76] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-32a.2" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-32a.3" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-32a.2">It has been impossible so far to fit this slip into any context of the remaining slips in Yucong 1.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.1" xml:lang="en">If one acts being in a precise fit with what is so </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.2" xml:lang="en">then that is simply good government. [slip 59] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.3" xml:lang="en">If what is in a precise fit does not attain to being dignified, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.4" xml:lang="en">this arises from one not attaining to [slip 60] what is so. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.5" xml:lang="en">To study (or: to teach) </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.6" xml:lang="en">is to study (or: to teach) this (what prevails/obtains). [slip 61] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.1">然 does not normally mean "be true&gt;morally right", the relevant word being 是 "right". The translation is highly tentative.Li Ling transcribes: 政其然，而行怠焉爾也。We noted pragmatic realism elsewhere. Here good government is explained as a pragmatic conforming to reality as it is: good government does not aspire to change the world, but gives it its due.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.4">What if the reality turns out less than dignified/elegant/worthwhile? This situation arises from a failure to appreciate properly what is the case.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.5">The graph repeated in lines 5 and 6 is written with a repetition sign. It can be read either as 學 or as 教, but is one entitled to read the repeated graph once as 學 and at the other time as 教? In any case, the meaning remains opaque.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-33a.6">As it stands this line looks simply ungrammatical: 其 has to be pre-nominal, I would have thought. 學斯也 would have made sense, but may be epigraphically totally unacceptable for all I know.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-34a.1" xml:lang="en">If one adapts to what prevails/obtains and acts thus, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-34a.2" xml:lang="en">then there will be good government. [slip 67] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-34a.1">This repeats the YUCONG 1.33 without the accumulation of the final particles, and the reasons for these overlaps remain unclear.This repeats the message in the preceding pasage.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-35a.1" xml:lang="en">Rectitude one can never deliberately make a point of acting out. [strip 53] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-35a.1">Rectitude belongs to the set of things which must be uncontrived to be real. Thus when one does the right thing in order to be seen to do the right thing then one is not in the relevant sense doing the right thing.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-36a.1" xml:lang="en">From (the case of) father and son </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-36a.2" xml:lang="en">one becomes familiar with the relation between superior and inferior. [slip 69] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-36a.3" xml:lang="en">From (the case of) elder and younger brothers </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-36a.4" xml:lang="en">one becomes familiar with (the relation of) precedence. [slip 70] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-36a.1">This, again, is a simple effort in realistic moral ethnography: it is on the basis of one's relations with one's father and mother that one becomes familiar with the notion of hierarchy because one must subordinate oneself under them.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-36a.2">This developmental genealogy of the concept of superior/inferior is significant in that it is concerned not with meanings as such but with their recognition. This clearly belongs together with YUCONG 1.37</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-36a.3">The case of the eldest brother taking precedence over the others, as the prospective heir, but as someone not yet exercising actual hierarchical control, is neatly distinguished from that of plain hierarchy. Again, the conceptual distinction between hierarchy and order of precedence is not well known from the Warring States literature. Perhaps I have overlooked it.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-37a.1" xml:lang="en">From (the case of) elder and younger brothers </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-37a.2" xml:lang="en">one becomes aware of who takes precedence. [slip 70] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-37a.1">The distinction between superiority (1.36) and precedence is subtle and significant.It seems that slips 36 and 37 should be treated as one double theorem.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-38a.1" xml:lang="en">No creature fails to act as the thing it is. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-38a.2" xml:lang="en">they all get to the point of doing this, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-38a.3" xml:lang="en">and [slip 71] none are such that they are not the kind that have themselves made their choice. [slip 72] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-38a.1">The graphs are clear: our text is clearly making a highly abstract point which involves a most unusual theoretical use of the noun 物 as an action verb.No creature fails to act out its part. Every tree does what that kind of tree is supposed to do: it acts itself out.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-38a.2">Everything reaches the point of acting as the thing it is. The flavour of this statement is very much like that of the dialectical chapters of the Mojing.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-38a.3">Again, the point is highly abstract: in no case is the source of something acting as the thing it is anything other than the thing itself. 取 is to make a choice for oneself, and it is very clear in the use of this word, what is evident already in our interpretation of line 1, that these theoretical analyses do involve a considerable degree of personification, i.e. attribution of action to what are essentially non-agents. Metaphysics is dramatised.Nothing external forces the tree to act out itself, to be itself. It is so by itself, of itself, 自然 "causing itself to be so". This causing oneself to be so is what is here spelt out as "choosing it itself".</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-39a.1" xml:lang="en">Kind-heartedness arises from (within) a person, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-39a.2" xml:lang="en">rectitude arises from the Way. [slip 22] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-39a.3" xml:lang="en">The one arise from within, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-39a.4" xml:lang="en">the other arise from without. [slip 23] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-39a.1">Note that it appears likely that whereas 仁 and 人 are reconstructed as homophones there was in fact a distinction which our reconstructions are not subtle enough to capture.The use of 人 to mean not "others" but "man/person" is theorising and unidiomatic.Goodness of heart is not imposed on man by some pragmatic external strategic rule. It comes from within. The sense of what is right and proper, on the other hand, is something one learns in the process of social interaction. The standards of what is right and proper are part of a Way that is external to one, and which one learns to follow as something external.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-39a.2">It is significant that the Way is taken to be something extrinsic, not something intrinsic. The context is clearly that of the debate whether 義 "rectitude" is extrinsic or intrinsic in MENG. YUCONG summarises theorems and does not argue anything, here as throughout.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.1" xml:lang="en">[If one emphasises kind-heartedness </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.2" xml:lang="en">and one deemphasises] rectitude, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.3" xml:lang="en">then one will be close to others, but [slip 77] not revered; </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.4" xml:lang="en">If one emphasises rectitude </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.5" xml:lang="en">and one deemphasises kind-heartedness, [slip 82] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.6" xml:lang="en">then one will be revered but not close to others. [slip 79] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.1">The first four characters are reconstructed with confidence on the basis of context. The confident reconstruction of this is aided by the pervasive parallelism.厚versus 薄 are a standard pair of antonyms. However, here these terms are used to refer to the setting of relative priorities.Again, the conjectural suggestion of the opening in this passage is plausible indeed. The context does allow us to predict the missing four characters.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.2">Again, this passage shows a remarkable moral pragmatism regarding the two main cardinal virtues of Confucianism.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-40a.3">親 "empathetic closeness" goes with the intrinsic, internal.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.1" xml:lang="en">[In distinguishing between ruler and] father </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.2" xml:lang="en">there is blood relation versus elevated status. (or: there is affection versus reverence) [slip 78] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.3" xml:lang="en">Treating with fraternal respect </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.4" xml:lang="en">is a Way among blood relatives. (or: is a Way involving affection) </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.5" xml:lang="en">Among friends, and between ruler and minister [slip 80] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.6" xml:lang="en">there is no blood relation (or: affection). [slip 81] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.1">The missing characters must have specified the loving relationship by a son to his father, perhaps involving 孝.The conjectural addition 【別君】is by Li Ling.The text is interested in the different modes of authority in a father and a ruler: the semantic distinctive feature is delared to be the contrast between blood relation within the hierarchy in the case of the father, and dignity of position in the case of the ruler.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-41a.6">This belongs to the systematic analysis of human relations in terms of 尊 and 親 attempted in YUCONG 1.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-42a.1" xml:lang="en">Relations between ruler and minister, and between friends, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-42a.2" xml:lang="en">are presumably the sort that are elective relationships/matters of choice. [slip 87] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-42a.1">These relations are not determined by blood relations.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-42a.2">This still belongs to the systematic analysis of relationships. In this case relationships without the element of either 親 or 尊.Note the pregnant use of 擇 "select" rather than 取 "pick for oneself, choose".Note that not only does the ruler choose ministers, but potential ministers do choose to serve or not to serve a ruler.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-43a.1" xml:lang="en">Guests </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-43a.2" xml:lang="en">are adornments of the Temple of Purity (and the musical rituals therein performed). [slip 88] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-43a.1">It seems that this is a paradoxical statement emphasising the fact that without distinguished guests on distinguished occasions the Temple of Purity with all its elegance is still lacking the crucial adornments which come into view only when the temple is actually used.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-43a.2">This may be taken as commending hospitality as adding elegance to one's home. But it may also refer to the maintaining of a retinue of retainers or followers, as they were asembled by several Warring States dignitaries.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-44a.1" xml:lang="en">There is such a thing as investigating goodness, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-44a.2" xml:lang="en">but one can never deliberately go about being excellent. [slip 84] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-44a.1">有 comes to mean "there are cases of&gt; it is possible that" in contrast with 無 "there are no cases of&gt; it is impossible that".</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-44a.2">為 must be taken in its heavy pregnant sense "contrive, make a special point of, have as a deliberate strategy. It is plainly possible both to be good and to do good things. But this theorem maintains that goodness/excellence must be spontaneous to be goodness/excellence.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-45a.1" xml:lang="en">One should investigate what one understands, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-45a.2" xml:lang="en">and one should investigate what one does not understand. ... [slip 85] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-45a.1">Here, as elsewhere, the text shows a taste for paradox. The investigation will have to be conducted in contrasting ways.One must know what to investigate, in order to investigate it, but in order for it to make sense to investigate it, one must not know what one tries to ascertain. Here as elsewhere the text enjoys the paradox.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-45a.2">察: the wordplay is on two kinds of investigation: in one case one investigates what one has under consideration and wants to know more about, and in the other case one seeks to find out what something is in the first place.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-46a.1" xml:lang="en">Position of power and reputation count as being open to investigation. [slip 86] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-46a.1">In YUCONG 1.45 we saw word-play and hence problematisation of the concept 察. Here, what is problematised are the possible objects of investigation. In particular, it is pointed out that investigation can be of intangibles such as sound/reputation, and also of such abstract things as power.勢／聲: the juxtaposition is unusual and not traditional. It is clearly motivated by theoretical/conceptual considerations of the analytic system.Position of power and reputation are public and over, therefore - unlike motivations, attitudes and he like - open to investigation.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-47a.1" xml:lang="en">When someone supplies what is necessary one calls him a sage/Making proper provision of what is necessary is called sagehood. [slip 94] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-47a.2" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-47a.3" xml:lang="en">Submitting obediently is called listening/obeying. </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-47a.1">This is a highly abstract, untraditional and egg-headed perspective on sagehood. The sage is considered a sage because he is a provider of essential necessities.聖 is used as an abstract noun here, not as a generic noun referring to sages.It might appear that 備 here must be taken to be a necessary condition for being a sage. But this is not made explicit by the formula 之謂.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-47a.3">The epigraphic uncertainty is uncomfortable.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-48a.1" xml:lang="en">When one fills out (?) sagehood one is called a sage. [slip 100] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-48a.1">The reading ¨’ is conjectural and highly tentative.The idea seems to be that sagehood is something one can only be in a consummate fashion. There is no way of being something of a sage. Compare, however, 半仙.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-49a.1" xml:lang="en">Lack arises from not yet or not quite having got something. [slip 91] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-49a.1">生乎 does not naturally apply to such things as 決 "determination": one can only be determined with respect to what one has not got to realise.The concept of lacking something, 缺, is complex. One is said to lack something when one has not quite got it, or when one has not yet got it. Also, one might add, when one would be expected to have it.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-49a.1">Liu Zhao reads 缺 for Li Ling's 決. This also yields a feasible interpretation.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-50a.1" xml:lang="en">Existence arises from having a name. [slip 96] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-50a.1">有 "existence" is problematised, and the theorem states that for something to have existence it must have a name. When it has a name it may be said to exist. Without a name it cannot be said to exist. A highly advanced abstract point.For something to be said to exist, it must have a name by which one can refer to it to claim that it exists. Th paradox is, then, that existence comes to depend on whether or not something has a name. The matter is notorious in the case of diseases: a disease only begins to exist, legally and politically, after it has received a name that can serve in diagnosis.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-51a.1" xml:lang="en">Determination and good faith </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-51a.2" xml:lang="en">are (fragile) implements. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-51a.3" xml:lang="en">Each in their own way, by loose [slip 107] talk, can be destroyed by loose talk. [slip 108] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-51a.1">決 "determination"</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-51a.2">器 are not eponymically fragile. This</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-51a.3">The reading 譫(?) is conjectural.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-51a.3">This is again a witticism: decisiveness and good faith in action are so fragile that mere loose talk can destroy them.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-52a.1" xml:lang="en">It is when the appellation concords with the physiognomy </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-52a.2" xml:lang="en">then this appellation becomes something current ?????. [slip 109] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-52a.1">呼 is given an unusual theoretical nominalised and abstract reading. Cf. Plato's Cratylos.容 "characteristic shape" is current in YUCONG 1.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-52a.2">The figurative use of 行 to mean "become current" has cognate parallels in the MOJING, where A.C. Graham translates it as "proceed" in a logical sense.Li Ling links this to slip 109 in spite of the punctuation mark which is perfectly acceptable since there is no more rooom on the slip.the punctuation mark.The interpretation of this must remain highly tentative.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-53a.1" xml:lang="en">If in matters of food one is wicked, or in matters of sex one is wicked, then this is an acute defect. [slip 110] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-53a.1">This theorem is a reflection on 食色性也: not only are these part of nature, they represent what are urgent concerns.Compare Mencius 食色性也 "Desire for food and beautiful women is a matter of human nature." Wickedness in these departments is acute because it concerns one's essential nature.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-54a.1" xml:lang="en">When one grieves in the right place </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-54a.2" xml:lang="en">one is in no case wrong. ... [slip 73] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-54a.1">Assuming the problematic reconstruction is right, this can be read as a theoretical comment on sadness about something not admitting of being wrong. Just as one cannot be wrong about a smell when one finds it repellent.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-55a.1" xml:lang="en">[slip 74] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-55a.1">The sentence final 弗 is would be surprising.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-56a.1" xml:lang="en">????[slip 75] </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-56a.2" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-56a.3" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-56a.2">Entirely conjectural transcription.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-57a.1" xml:lang="en">He who prefers many </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-57a.2" xml:lang="en">is one who prefers none. [slip 89] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-57a.1">Another deliberate paradox, this time plainly inspired by Laozi. So much for the "Confucian" nature of YUCONG 1.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-57a.2">Preference involves singling out and exclusion of what one does not prefer. Preference must be selective. When one prefers many things one preference is weak, and one might even say that there is nothing one prefers.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-58a.1" xml:lang="en">In counting </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-58a.2" xml:lang="en">one does not reach an end. [slip 90] [or: Numbers are inexhaustible.] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-58a.1">This is a plain mathematical theorem which does not apply that the Chinese language has names for all numbers, but that counting will never end in spite of this.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-59a.1" xml:lang="en">Poetry is created with reverence as a point of departure. [slip 95] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-59a.1">This theorem views 詩 poetry as having been 作 "created, made", as indeed it is viewed in SHI itself.敬 "reverence; diligence"</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-60a.1" xml:lang="en">As for seeking </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-60a.2" xml:lang="en">there never is a case of it (the things sought) coming of itself. ...[slip 99] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-60a.2">While one is seeking the thing sought cannot be coming to one of itself, for if it was on would not be seeking any more.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-61a.1" xml:lang="en">As for power???, </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-61a.2" xml:lang="en">one may eschew it, or one may rally to it. [slip 101] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-61a.1">The issue is the mobility of abstract items like power.Li Ling is still not sure about what to do with this character.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-62a.1" xml:lang="en">In general, what has something in common interacts. [slip 102] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-62a.1">There is evident word-play here on kh-looN通/looN同. Interaction is said to result from points of commonality. One suspects that the notion of 通 here is generalised and not limited to that of linguistic communication or even others forms of semantic communication. It is as almost if the text discussed something like "communicating testtubes".</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-63a.1" xml:lang="en">Each creature rests in its proper place (in the scheme of things); </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-63a.2" xml:lang="en">but I/we, engage in deliberate action ... [slip 105] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-63a.1">Many things/creatures move. But abstractly, in a metaphysical sense, they each remain in their place. We have another deliberately implicit paradox.Li Ling links this to slips 75 and 101.Non-human creatures each fill their roles instinctually.所: this cannot refer to the physical space occupied, since things move. It refers quite abstractly to an assigned fixed immutable role. Through deliberate planned action, humans come to differ from this fixed-pattern paradigm, as agents responsible for their actions.</note>
               <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-63a.2">I suspect there was another paradox appended here</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-64a.1" xml:lang="en">...all have it. [slip 106] </seg>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-65a.1" xml:lang="en">stop it. [slip 111] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-65a.1">Li Ling links this to slip 73: 無非是止之。</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-66a.1" xml:lang="en">Generally, things originate from their own absence. [TITLE] [slip 1] </seg>
                    <note target="#KR2p0028_tls_001-66a.1">Repetition in such a small set raises many questions: does this statement enter twice into different arguments, or does it enter twice into one sequence? So far, no explanation is forthcoming. Scribal carelessness somehow seems unlikely.Li Ling regards this as a repeated title.</note>
                </p>

            <p>
                    <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-67a.1" xml:lang="en">strips 24 and 25 as reconstructed and supplemented in Li Ling 2002. </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-67a.2" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-67a.3" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-67a.4" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-67a.5" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-67a.6" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR2p0028_tls_001-67a.7" xml:lang="en"> </seg>
                </p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>