<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-2b9f9aa9-c805-4d5d-aa03-8d71142ceaa3" subtype="PC">
  <head>沙證</head>
  <div type="definition">sand condition</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="shazheng-63458" n="shazheng沙證">
      <form>
        <orth>沙證</orth>
        <pron>Sha zheng</pron>
        <usg n="3">[3]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>sand condition</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Pathological Condition of an affection by external evil with headache and high fever, cold fingers and toes, and abdominal pain. Shi yi de xiao fang 世醫得效方 2: 艾湯，試沙證。江南舊無，今所在 有之。原其證古方不載，所感如傷寒，頭痛嘔噁，渾身壯熱，手足指末 微厥，或腹痛煩亂，須臾能殺人。先濃煎艾湯試之，如吐即是。右用五 月蠶蛻紙碎剪，安碗中，以盤蓋之，以百沸湯泡艾碗許，仍以別紙封裹 縫良久，乘熱飲之，就臥，以厚被蓋之，汗出愈 , “Decoction with ai to test a sand condition . In former times [this condition] did not exist in the Jiangnan region. Nowadays it is present there everywhere. This condition was not listed in ancient recipes. It feels like harm caused by cold, with headache and vomiting and nausea. The entire body is very hot. The ends of the fingers and toes experience slight recession. In some cases there is abdominal pain, with vexation and confusion. After a short time it will kill the [afflicted] person. First one prepares a thick decoction of ai [and has the patient ingest it] as a test [whether he has a sand condition]. If he vomits, this is it. [For the indications listed] above one uses paper on which silkworm moths have laid their eggs in the fifth month, cuts it and places it into a bowl. This is to be covered with a plate. Then soak ai with approximately a bowl of boiling water and add it [to the paper]. Now close the seams with additional paper and wait a while. Eventually have [the patient] drink this as long as it is still hot. Then he is to lie down and to be covered with a thick quilt. When he sweats, he is cured”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>