<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-a14f6d72-faed-470e-9303-2fba763c1abf" subtype="TA">
  <head>斷產</head>
  <div type="definition">to cut birthing; to sterilize; sterility; to end pregnancy</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="duanchan-56025" n="duanchan斷產">
      <form>
        <orth>斷產</orth>
        <pron>Duan chan</pron>
        <usg n="13">[13]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>to cut birthing; to sterilize; sterility; to end pregnancy</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>① Therapeutic Approach of severing a fertile woman’s productive capacity so that she may lead a normal life and yet cannot become pregnant. Qian jin bei ji fang 千金備急方 3: 婦人斷產方：蠶子故紙 方一尺，燒為末，酒服之，終身不產 , “Recipe to sterilize women: 1 square chi of old paper made from silkworm seeds is to be burned and made to powder. After it has been ingested with wine it will prevent [a woman] from having offspring for her entire life”.</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>② Therapeutic Approach of prematurely ending a pregnancy; abortion. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry fuzi 附子 quoting Wai tai mi yao 外台秘要 34: 療妊身欲去之，並斷產方。…又方：附子二枚搗為屑，以 淳苦酒和塗右足，去之大良， “Recipes to treat pregnant woman who wish to rid themselves of it, and also to cut birthing . …Further recipe: grind two pieces of fu zi to crumbs, mix with pure wine and apply to the right foot. Very good to remove it”, writes: 斷產下胎：生附子為末，淳酒和塗右足心，胎下去之。 小品方 . “ To cut birthing and bring a fetus down: grind fresh fu zi to a powder, mix this with pure wine and apply to the sole of the right foot. Remove again once the fetus has been aborted. Xiao pin fang ”. The meaning of “abortion” conveyed by the use of duan chan 斷產 in this Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 quote is a departure from the meaning of “sterilization” conveyed by the original use of the term in the Wai tai mi yao 外台秘要 . ③ Illness Sign of infertility. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry yin zhi 印紙 , quoting Ben cao shi yi 本草拾遺 : 主令婦人斷產無 子。剪有印處燒灰，水服之一錢匕，神效 , “It is capable of cutting a woman’s birthing resulting in that she will not have children. Cut out the location with the seal on it, burn it to ashes and ingest on qian on a spoon with water. Wondrously effective”, from Zhenglei bencao 證類本草 , Substance Entry yin zhi 印紙 , writes: 婦人 斷產無子，剪有印處燒灰，水服一錢匕，效。藏器 , “If a woman’s ability to give birth is cut and she has no children, cut out the location with the seal on it, burn it to ashes and ingest one qian on a spoon with water. Effective. [Chen] Cangqi”. The meaning conveyed in this Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 quote is opposite to the original meaning intended by the Ben cao shi yi as quoted in the Zheng lei ben cao .</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>