<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-a67484ee-a9b8-4309-bc3f-48c5814363e3" subtype="PC">
  <head>氣鬱</head>
  <div type="definition">pent-up qi</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="qiyu-67412" n="qiyu氣鬱">
      <form>
        <orth>氣鬱</orth>
        <pron>Qi yu</pron>
        <usg n="24">[24]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>pent-up qi</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>① Pathological Condition one of liu yu 六郁 , the six types of pent-up [matter in the organism]. Refers to accumulation disease brought forth by mental depression, with a feeling of fullness and pain in the chest and abdomen, and a deep and rough movement in the vessels. Su wen 素問 71: 民病氣鬱中滿 ; “People suffer from pent-up qi and central fullness”.</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>② Etiological Agent. of a blockage of the qi dynamics inside the organism, possibly bringing forth all types of disease. Sheng ji zong lu 聖濟總錄 1: 寒氣時至，民乃和，其病淋，目瞑目赤， 氣鬱於上而熱 , “When cold qi arrives in time, the people feel well. Their diseases include dripping, the eyes do not open, and [when open] they are red. [This is] pent-up qi above with heat”. Qi zhang 氣脹 , qi distension [24]</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Illness Sign of an uncomfortable feeling of distention brought forth by qi stagnation. Su wen 素問 17: 上盛則氣高，下盛則氣脹 , “If it is abundant above, the qi is [situated] high [in the body]. If it is abundant below, this is a qi distension ”. Qi zhi 氣滯 , qi sluggishness [31]</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Alternative Names qi yong 氣壅 , qi obstruction</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>Etiological Agent. Pathological Mechanism of qi dynamic hindered in its free flow, which in turn may cause disease. Shi liao ben cao 食療本草 Substance Entry cu 醋：氣滯風壅，手臂、脚膝痛。炒醋糟裹之，三兩易，當差 , “In the case of qi sluggishness and wind obstruction, the hands and arms, legsand knees ache. They are to be wrapped with the dregs produced in the course of making vinegar. Change three times or twice. This should bring the cure”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>