<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-3e507cd7-5319-4a44-907c-d753195a44d9" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>范睢</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="MALES OF WEI" tls:concept-id="uuid-36857758-ce57-47a6-b878-8f6e8f42f399" xml:id="uuid-fbce93c5-cfb2-48e9-ad82-d5e17bdd01fd" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-651615a0-d362-4391-b7fa-1d6d286bf652 #uuid-e255ed67-f119-41cf-972b-112e6628d468">
<orth>范睢</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">fàn huī</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">bomʔ qhlul</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">bi̯ɐm hiɛ</pron>
            </form>
            <form corresp="#uuid-651615a0-d362-4391-b7fa-1d6d286bf652 #uuid-82f66dd7-c2b0-4670-ac0e-84e0d76eb83d">
<orth>范雎</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">fàn jū</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">bomʔ skha</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">bi̯ɐm tshi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a7474469-9d94-40e0-9f45-59e3b27266a3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2020-04-18T21:10:30.972+09:00">Fàn Jū 范雎 (范且) (died 255) from Wei 魏 also became known as the Marquis of Ying 應侯. He served under the dignitary Xu Jia 須價 who had him almost caned to death when Xu Jia 須價 had made false accusations against him. [LH 43] He was saved by the efforts of Zheng Anping 鄭安平 and escaped to Qin where he was enfeoffed in the city of Ying 應, served as Prime Minister to &gt;King Zhao of Qin 秦昭王 from 266-256, and from where he ran intrigues against his own compatriots. He argued for appeasement of the formidable general &gt;Bai Qi 白起, when the latter had killed as many as 400 000 people from Zhao, having won the decisive battle at Changping 長平 in 262. Around 256 Fan Ju had his supporter Zheng Anping appointed general to fight against Bai Qi, and when the latter lost a major battle at the capital of Zhao, Fan Ju was terrified of the results of this for his own person and hastened to return his seal of office as prime minister so as to retire from office. Soon after these dramatic events he fell ill and died. His story is told in great narrative detail in SJ 79. Fàn Suī/Huī 范睢, also written Fàn Jū 范雎(Died 255) Unger no. 138</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>