<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-3c94a52c-6e92-480f-94a5-2c6e92480f01" n="3">
    <form>
        <orth>鄭</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="UNRESTRAINED" tls:concept-id="uuid-c4f93107-fffa-48b8-b468-e12e83bac180" xml:id="uuid-46c7d89e-c6f1-4957-9040-aa70948b963e" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-976ef71f-78a2-425c-8e4a-92bbcef00dff">
<orth>鄭</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhèng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">deŋs</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖiɛŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f100fb05-24ef-4c2d-aaf1-038c7c3191a9">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>be licentious (in the style of the poetry of Zhe4ng)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="EARNEST" tls:concept-id="uuid-f5710eb1-3fea-4aed-a300-c4f242751c1a" xml:id="uuid-645626dc-4b5a-4667-8194-5216599bd1f4" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-976ef71f-78a2-425c-8e4a-92bbcef00dff">
<orth>鄭</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhèng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">deŋs</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖiɛŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e2b59e11-1bbd-41d2-a5c8-332f0e174f36" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>earnest</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-e22d1287-6f9d-44cf-8273-db1b5d70a15e" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-976ef71f-78a2-425c-8e4a-92bbcef00dff">
<orth>鄭</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhèng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">deŋs</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖiɛŋ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Zhèng 鄭 (CHEN PAN 1969, 99-142)

Clan: Ruled by the Jī 姬 clan.

Rank: Bó (common in CQ and ZUO).

Founded: The first ruler of Zhèng was &gt;duke Huán (Zhèng Huán gōng 鄭桓公), by the personal name Yǒu 友 (or Duōyǒu 多友; in the Current Zhúshū jìnián Duōfǔ 多父), the son of the king Lì of Zhōu 周厲王 (according to SHI, Zhèng shìjiā) and the brother of the king Xuān of Zhōu (&gt;Zhōu Xuān wáng 周宣王; 827-782 B.C.). According to the Current Zhúshū jìnián, Yǒu was the son of the king Xuān and not his brother.

Destroyed: In 375 BC, Zhèng was eliminated by the state of &gt;Hán 韓.

Location: The state of Zhèng was originally located in modern Shǎnxī province. Among traditional Chinese scholars, there is not agreement on its precise location there, but basically it was located not very far from the Zhōu western capital.
During the turmoil at the turn of the Western and Eastern Zhōu periods, the state of Zhèng shifted to the East, into the area of the eastern part of central Henan. The precise date of this shift is problematic. It seems that the part of eastern areas was occupied already by Duke Huán prior to the downfall of the Western Zhōu in 771 B.C. (according to the Zhèng shìjiā chapter of SHI and to the Zhèng yǔ section of the Guó yǔ; Zhú shū jìnián dates this event to the second year of the Marquis Wén of Jìn 晉文侯, i.e. 779 B.C.), but the state was shifted by his successor the duke Wǔ 鄭武公 (770-744 B.C.). The capital of Zhèng in the East was Xīnzhèng 新鄭, identical with modern Xīnzhèng 新鄭 in Henan. This capital is under excavation.

History: After the shift to the East, duke Wǔ of Zhèng succesfully intervened into the struggles for the royal succession . The height of its power Zhèng reached under duke Zhuāng (&gt;Zhèng Zhuāng gōng 鄭莊公, 743 - 701 BC), who is sometimes even called the small hegemon of the feudal lords. After his death, Zhèng lost its power, and since the thirties of the seventh century it was pressed between the powerful states of &gt;Jìn 晉 and &gt;Chǔ 楚. In 375 BC, Zhèng was eliminated by the state of &gt;Hán 韓.
Zhèng was famous in Chunqiu times as the main trading centre in China, and merchants represented in the capital very important part of population.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-17d89c40-23f0-4244-841a-e5efb3df444a" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0fe99259-17ec-4766-a992-5917ec27662e" resp="#zadrapa" tls:created="2022-05-22T04:46:16.169+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>N</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-af99c48b-0543-4b6e-99c4-8b0543eb6ee9">npr.adN</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>of Zheng4</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
</superEntry>