<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-33a09e14-5d5e-4850-a09e-145d5ed850a3" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>無情說法</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="ZEN PHRASES" tls:concept-id="uuid-039dd702-55e3-48cb-9de5-9c9a24d234d4" xml:id="uuid-e9b83d01-45d9-4e47-825d-c5c74ac0e2b9" n="4">
            <form corresp="#uuid-5de002ac-c1a1-4519-a177-4a3afcc155bb #uuid-fe0dbc1f-2ca0-4174-9787-b9511e7f67fb #uuid-08ee826a-8ac2-45df-9f16-72515d87430c #uuid-bcc31133-8ffb-45d4-aeeb-442e8943f17e">
<orth>無情說法</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wú qíng shuō fǎ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ma dzeŋ lʰod pab</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">mi̯o dziɛŋ ɕiɛt pi̯ɐp</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-3691e1cc-c71f-4ff9-9d8c-7050903e8562">SHARF 2002</ref>
<title>Coming to Terms with Chinese Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">247, 335</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>As Robert Sharf has pointed out the question whether inanimated objects possessed Buddha-nature was a source of controversy in the medieval period and especially in the debates between the northern and southern factions of Cha2n. The theory that also inanimated objects possess Buddha-nature is possibly based on the writings of Ji4ngyi3ng Hui4yua3n 淨影慧遠 (523-592) who "[...] distinguished between the buddha-nature that abides at all times in all places and the buddha-nature that is actualized in enlightened sentient beings. But Hui4yua3n stopped short of explicitely claiming that inanimate objects possess budha-nature. The first person to do so appears to have been the Sa1nlu2n 三輪 exegete Ji2za1ng 吉藏 (549-623), who argued that the very distinction between sentient and insentient is illegitimate, and thus, if budda-nature can be said to exist at all, then it must be possessed  by both the sentient and the insentient." (Sharf 2002: 247) The doctrine was also taken up by members of the Tia1nta2i school, escpecially Zha4nra2n 湛然 (711-782). Many adherents of the early Cha2n school seem to have supported the doctrine, e.g. the Fourth Patriarch Da4oxi4n 道信 (580-651), the Fifth Patriarch Ho2ngre3n 弘忍 (601-674), possibly also She2nxiu4 神秀 (605?-706); see ibid.: 247-248. References on secondary works on this doctrine see in ibid.: 335, fn. 55.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-62983690-74db-400b-8af4-172716fbdf20" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>S</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-0527dea4-756f-489b-8843-0ebc52441e20">V{S}</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: non-sentients expound the dharma (this phrase became very popular in Zen texts from the 10th century onwards and became the subject of many discussions; for the first time it was elaborated on in ZTJ (952 A.D.); the phrase is usually connected to the teaching of Huìzhōng 慧忠, but also became an important topic in the teachings of Dòngshān 洞山)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>