<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR1h0001" type="notes">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Research Notes for 孟子</title>
                <editor role="creator">TLS Project</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</p>
                <availability status="2">This work has been licensed for use in the TLS</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Research Notes</title>
                </bibl>
                <p>Comments and notes to <bibl corresp="#KR1h0001">
                        <title xml:lang="och">孟子</title>
                    </bibl>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#crone.thomas">Initially created: <date>2022-02-22T17:39:12.847+09:00</date> by crone.thomas</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Comments</head>
                <p xml:id="KR1h0001-start">
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_014-1a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2023-02-02T02:55:40.244+09:00">extrapolates from those he cares for to those he does not care for CH</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_014-2a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2023-02-02T02:55:16.324+09:00">extrapolates from those he does not care for to those he does care for.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_013-16a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2023-11-06T17:39:53.279+09:00">"words of benevolence" is the relevant reading, I think. Humans are benevolent. Properly speaking, men are not benevolent.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_006-29a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2023-11-07T10:25:37.757+09:00">“In ancient times, when someone was not one's subordinate, one would refuse to receive a visit from them (because one would insist to be polite enough to insist to pay one's respectful visit to the visitor's home instead.)"  This is probably madness, but it would fit the context of the examples that follow. 待考。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_013-19a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2024-02-28T17:27:56.017+09:00">Note 故君子欲其自得之也。 "The true gentleman wants them to get it for themselves." in the Mencius. The 其 does NOT have to refer to the subject here.        Lyall: Mencius said, “Do nothing they do not do, wish nothing they do not wish; that is all!” (1932,208).    Ware: “Do not have done what you yourself would not do; do not have de*sired what you yourself would not desire. It is as simple as that” (1960,151).    Hattori (Japanese): Mencius said, “Let one not do what he does not do; let one not desire what he does not desire. It is simply like this” (1922,252).</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_008-31a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-23T18:09:42.564+09:00">伊川：故者，本如是者也。　　天下之言性者，止説得故而已矣。(Korean II.533)    注南軒曰：「故者本然之理」Korean II.670</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_008-31a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-23T20:02:19.008+09:00">「然其所謂故者，又必本其自然之勢。Korean IV.301  許益之曰： 「求人之故,則(見)e父慈子孝，君仁臣忠．  Korean III.557a</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-28a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-23T22:12:36.895+09:00">Any sound reading of this sentence musst explain the force of 無 versus the also possible 不: What is the nuance expressed? 待考。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-29a.26" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-24T00:42:09.976+09:00">如云r我固有之也，非由外鑠我也j。 蓋義本於心，不自外至。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-25T21:29:10.414+09:00">《廣雅·釋詁》:“賴,善也。”《吕氏春秋·離俗覽》“則必不之賴”高誘《注》:“賴,善也。”       《墨子·七患》“時年歲善,則民仁且良;時年歲凶,則民吝且惡”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-25T23:18:23.712+09:00">free creation of abstract antonymic terms</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.25" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-25T23:32:31.868+09:00">know the properties of</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.30" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T00:43:50.185+09:00">Strikingly, nobody discusses the fact that people have different culinary preferences. But note that below 其性與人同 shows awareness of the problem.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.33" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T00:42:24.06+09:00">varied in nature from one person to another</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.34" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T00:46:10.963+09:00">我 refers neither to the speaker, nor to the group constituted by his speaker and his audience: that is the logic of the matter. Translation is secondary in importance.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.49" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T01:11:12.166+09:00">Thus one may sumarise...</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.58" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T01:24:40.125+09:00">What human basic sensibilities  have in common,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.60" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T01:51:57.164+09:00">is known as he "moral principle"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-30a.61" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T01:33:46.023+09:00">i.e. the sense of what is morally right.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-31a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T04:54:23.152+09:00">can they (still) be found beaufiful?</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-31a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-26T04:59:26.556+09:00">But such as they were</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_011-6a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-02-29T01:25:50.105+09:00">退溪全書今註今譯　vol. 5, p. 504: 生之謂性：天生的本性叫做性。　Compare:《荀子丨正名篇》云：“生之所以然者謂之性。’《春秋繁露丨深察名號篇》云广如其生之自然之資謂之性。’”唐韓愈《原性》性也者，與生倶生也。”　　The idea that Gaozi only can focus on material 氣 and never rises to the moral 理 is not relevant in this particular contexts.  The creation by Heaven is also not relevant.  Han Yu has it nicely: 與生俱生的. That is what this is about.  And Mencius sets a logical trap for Gaozi:  the colour 白 has a similar concrete reference in all that has the colour 白, but the feature 性 does not have a similar concrete reference in all that has the feature 性.      儒藏。韓國 vol. 3, p. 288 shows the hermeneutic helplessness nicely: 。然生之謂性四個字內，語無破綻，其以為所以生底是性與？抑以為生便是性與？    See also ibidem p. 403: 嚕濬對：性有超形氣而論之者，有兼指氣而言之者，有合而看之者，有分而析之者。孟子所謂「形色，天性」之「性」即就氣上指出理來，而非告子所謂「生之謂性」、「食色，性也」之「性」</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_013-3a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-03T02:33:37.793+09:00">The reference, here, is to the fundamental principles of moral orientation, the 四端. Being part of the primordial nature, these are at hand, as soon as they are sought.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_013-3a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-03T02:34:30.987+09:00">捨 is to not to carelessly neglect, but to abandon, and philosophically that distinction is important.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_013-3a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-03T02:35:50.346+09:00">Note here as so often elsehwere, that 我 does not refer to the speaker or to the "we" of him and his audience.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_013-3a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-03T02:36:34.691+09:00">Marcus Aurelius would say that the seeking is up to you.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_013-3a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-03T02:37:51.677+09:00">The success of this is not up to you, as the Stoics have it.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0001_tls_003-13a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-12T23:35:16.698+09:00">邵邵永海 continues: 在一般的理解中，勇是有膽量，無所畏懼。但是，孔子多次强調，一個無所畏懼的人，假如沒有仁愛之心，沒有道義之心，那麼對他人而言恐怕是災難。“勇而無禮則亂。”“好勇疾貧，亂也。”“好勇不好學，其蔽也亂。”亂，即是無道，是胡作非爲。可見勇這種德行需要有更高層次的德行制約，如孔子所言：“仁者必有勇，勇者不必有仁。”“君子義以爲上。君子有勇而無義爲亂，小人有勇而無義爲盜。”孔子給“勇”這個概念賦予了新的內涵。他說：“見義不爲，無勇也。”看到應該做的事情不敢去做，這就是沒有勇氣。孔子用否定形式來論斷“勇”的含義，正足以使人明白，“勇”並非指什麼都敢做，而是首先要懂得什麼該做、什麼不該做；當道義上應當挺身而出的時候，絕不猶豫，更不會退縮；反之，不符合道義的事情，寧肯付出生命的代價也絕不去做。這才是真正的勇者。孟子繼承了孔子關於“勇”的觀念，并進一步發展出“養勇”的表述，說明勇并非人如仁義禮智等德行之與生俱來，而是需要後天培養。他闡述北宫黝、孟施舍和曾子三人養勇的不同原則。《韓非子·顯學》稱孔子之后，儒家分爲八派，其中有漆雕氏一派：“漆雕之議，不色撓，不目逃，行曲則違於臧獲，行直則怒於諸侯，世主以爲廉而禮之。”《陶淵明集》中有《集聖賢群輔録》，言“漆雕氏傳禮爲道，爲恭儉莊敬之儒”。可見這一派儒學堅守禮法原則，在任何情況下絕不妥協退讓。不妥協、不退讓，需要大無畏的氣慨和堅定的意志。</seg>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>