<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="T47n1986A" type="notes">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Research Notes for 筠州洞山悟本禪師語錄</title>
                <editor role="creator">TLS Project</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</ab>
                <availability status="2">
                    <ab>This work has been licensed for use in the TLS</ab>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Research Notes</title>
                </bibl>
                <p>Comments and notes to <bibl corresp="#T47n1986A">
                        <title xml:lang="och">筠州洞山悟本禪師語錄</title>
                    </bibl>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#chris">Initially created: <date>2023-12-19T15:53:22.236+09:00</date> by chris</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Comments</head>
                <p xml:id="T47n1986A-start">
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1986A_CBETA_001-0515a1701.s34" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2023-12-19T16:18:08.627+09:00">The ancient Chinese philosophy of change is known for its main    scripture Ijing  (I-ching). According to its teaching, there are eight    basic situations—qia,  dui, li, zhen, xun, kan, gen, and kun, which    correspond to heaven,  lake, fire, thunder, ground, gorge, bound,    and field. Each of these  situations is represented by a trigram—a    combination of three  horizontal lines: solid, or broken into two with    space in between. For  example, the third situation, li, is    represented by a broken  line stacked between solid lines: A    solid line is usually  related to yang, and a broken line, yin. But    Dongshan relates the  former to zheng (nonduality) and the latter    to pian (duality). (See  the entry for five, below.) In the philosophy    of change, the eight  situations are combined two-fold, which    makes sixty-four  situations, represented by sixty-four hexagrams    that are trigrams stacked  one top of another. One of them,    “double fire,” is an intense  situation of duality contained within    nonduality.</seg>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>