<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-46c75ee1-6cf2-44a9-88e8-37c60330a824" subtype="PC">
  <head>痰逆</head>
  <div type="definition">phlegm counterflow</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="tanni-67062" n="tanni痰逆">
      <form>
        <orth>痰逆</orth>
        <pron>Tan ni</pron>
        <usg n="5">[5]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>phlegm counterflow</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>① Pathological Condition of a qi dynamic ascending contrary to its regular direction with nausea, vomiting and an inability to ingest beverages and food, resulting from blockages of regular qi dynamics caused by phlegm abundance. Tai ping sheng hui fang 太平聖惠方 51: 夫痰逆不下 食者，由胸膈壅滯，津液不通，痰水結聚，不能消散，流行於脾，脾性 惡濕，得水則脹滿，心胸不利，多痰而逆，故令不下食也 , “Now, phlegm counterflow and an inability to ingest food results from obstruction and [qi] sluggishness in the region of the chest and diaphragm, with body liquids being unable to pass. Phlegm and liquid form nodular collections that are unable to dissolve and disperse and flow into the spleen. The spleen hates moisture, and if it takes in liquid it distends and has a feeling of fullness. The heart and chest are no longer open for passage. There is much phlegm moving contrary to its regular direction. Hence this makesa person incapable of ingesting food.</def>
      </sense>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>② Illness Sign Combined Designation of throwing up phlegm saliva. Tai ping sheng hui fang 太平聖惠方 11: 治傷寒邪熱傷心，恍惚 狂言，時有痰逆，不欲飲食，宜服人參散方 , “To cure harm caused by cold, and evil heat harming the heart, with absent-mindedness and crazy talking, as well as occasional phlegm counterflow and loss of appetite, the recipe to ingest the powder with ren shen is advisable”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>