<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CH1d0955-en-13a1a51a" type="comment">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Comments to 傷寒論</title>
                <editor role="creator">Li Guohui</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org<seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-1a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T09:11:31.076+09:00">1.Aversion to wind means a mild cold sensation on the skin at times or upon exposure to wind or draft. It could abate when the patient is not exposed to wind. Both aversion to wind and aversion to cold are common symptoms seen in tai yang disease. Both of them would occur regardless of the presentation of external wind or cold. Neither of them would diminish by adding extra clothing or blankets. The cause for both of them are the failure of the defensive qi to warm the body surface due to attack of wind-cold.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-1a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T09:14:53.08+09:00">2.A moderate pulse in this line is a literal translation of “緩脉 huán mài,” which is usually done in modern textbooks in Chinese medicine. Jiang Jian-Guo and Li Shu-Pei point out: \nThe application of relativity in the pulse diagnosis is one unique approach to the pulse diagnosis in Discussion of Cold Damage; the term “緩脉 huán mài” is the opposite of the term “緊脉 jǐn mài (tight pulse).” [Zhang] Zhong-Jing originally wanted to elucidate the feature of clinical presentation and etiology for shang han syndrome and zhong feng syndrome in tai yang disease by comparing “緩脉 huán mài (a moderate pulse)” with “緊脉 jǐn mài (a tight pulse).” Any pulse that isnot tight can be called “緩脉 huán mài (a moderate pulse).In summary, the moderate pulse (緩脉 huán mài) in this line just implies that the force of the pulse felt is not as firm as the tight pulse is. Clinically, any pulse that is felt as neither tight nor firm can be considered a moderate pulse (緩脉 huán mài).</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-1a.10" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T09:16:04.787+09:00">3.Zhong feng syndrome is one of the syndromes in tai yang disease. It is caused by wind-cold attack, in which wind is predominant. The character “證 zhèng (syndrome)” is added to the term “中風 zhòng fēng” as it is actually a syndrome of tai yang disease. The term “中風 zhòng fēng” in this line is a quite different wind-stroke, which is also called “中風 zhòng fēng” but it is a disease in zang-fu organ differentiation in other literature of Chinese medicine. That kind of zhong feng is caused by internal wind from stirring up from the liver due to either extreme heat or yin deficiency in the liver and kidney.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-1a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T09:17:42.035+09:00">1.This line is called the outline of tai yang disease, a name that has been agreed by contemporary scholars and practitioners, because it summarizes important features of the exterior syndrome in tai yang disease in regard to clinical manifestations based on understanding of the direct relationship between the exterior syndrome in tai yang disease and the distribution of tai yang channels. Likewise, the first line of other diseases in Discussion of Cold Damage, apart from yang ming disease, is called outline of such disease. Wu Qian and colleagues explicitly pointed out that “putting this line on the first one is to serve as the outline of tai yang disease. Whenever tai yang disease is discussed in the three sections of tai yang conformation, all refers to symptoms, signs and the pulse in this line.”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-1a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T09:18:29.493+09:00">2.Among these four symptoms and signs, only the stiff nape can be considered one that is an exclusive indicator for tai yang disease, as the urinary bladder channel runs along the nape. Ke Qin, a physician and well-known commentator for Discussion of Cold Damage in the seventeenth century, explained that “the floating pulse can be felt in all three yang diseases. Headache can present in all three yang diseases, so can aversion to cold. Only headache that is associated with stiffness on the nape exclusively belongs to tai yang disease.”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-2a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T09:53:11.882+09:00">1.Fever might not present at the very beginning of shang han syndrome in tai yang disease because wind-cold, in which cold predominates, will move slowly to encounter the defensive qi and slowly stagnate the defensive qi while generating a hot feeling on the body surface at the very beginning. Fever will present soon afterward as long as wind-cold completely engages in the defensive qi and obstructs it. Fang You-Zhi offered an insightful explanation for the pathomechanism of fever due to attack of cold in this line. He wrote: Cold is a yin pathological factor that does not generate fever alone. When it invades yang channels of the body, however, it will become stagnated and fight with yang qi, which results in fighting and steaming of yang qi. Thus, fever ensues. Presentation of fever indicates that there is such stagnation, fighting and steaming for a while. And absence of fever indicates that there is no such stagnation, fighting and steaming at the very beginning.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-2a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T09:54:25.055+09:00">2.Vomiting is a translation of the term “嘔逆 ǒu nì” in this line. Literally, vomiting and rebellion of qi, rather than vomiting only, should be the translation of this term in this line. In Chinese rhetoric, especially in the medical literature, the group of the characters “嘔逆 ǒu nì (vomiting and rebellion of qi)” belongs to one of rhetoric, which called “省略 shěng lüè (omit).” It means when two characters are present, one of them does not bear the meaning it usually has, though it is recorded.[[</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-2a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T11:38:24.025+09:00">3.A tight pulse at yin and yang position means a tight pulse is felt on the distal, middle and proximal positions. Fang You-Zhi said that “yin refers to the position behind the middle position while yang to the position ahead of the middle position. A tight pulse appearing on all three positions is caused by the rigid attribution of cold.”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#CH1d0955_CHANT_005-2a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2020-12-03T11:39:18.701+09:00">next: l 2107</seg>
                </p>
                <availability status="3">This work has not been licensed for use in the TLS</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Comments</title>
                </bibl>
                <p>Comments and notes to <bibl corresp="#CH1d0955">
                        <title xml:lang="och">傷寒論</title>
                    </bibl>for translation <ref target="#CH1d0955-en-d0a29708"/>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#chris">Initially created: <date>2020-12-03T09:09:36.649+09:00</date> by chris</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Comments</head>
                <p xml:id="CH1d0955-start"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>