<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR1h0004-en-2ad22ec2" type="transl">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Understanding the Confucian Analects</title>
                <editor role="translator">Ni Peimin</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</ab>
                <availability status="4">The copyright status of this work is unclear</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Understanding the Confucian Analects</title>New York: Suny Press, 2017</bibl>
                <ab>Translation of <bibl corresp="#KR1h0004">
                        <title xml:lang="och">論語</title>
                    </bibl> into <lang xml:lang="en">English</lang>.</ab>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#CH">Initially created: <date>2024-01-25T19:45:39.154+09:00</date> by CH</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Translated parts</head>
                <p xml:id="KR1h0004-start">
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_005-14a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-01-25T19:46:01.481+09:00">Zigong said,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_005-14a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-01-25T19:46:07.819+09:00">“I do not wish others to impose on me,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_005-14a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-01-25T19:46:15.393+09:00">nor do Iwish to ever impose on others.”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_005-14a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-01-25T19:46:25.955+09:00">The Master said,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_005-14a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-01-25T19:46:30.439+09:00">“Ci [Zigong],</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_005-15a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-01-25T19:46:34.284+09:00">this is what you have yet to attain.”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_002-18a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-09T06:07:17.212+09:00">The Master said,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_002-18a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-09T07:41:02.744+09:00">“You [Zilu],</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_002-18a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-09T07:41:34.804+09:00">keep in mind (zhi 知) what I am about to teach you.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_002-18a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-09T07:43:08.813+09:00">and if you do not know then hold it as you don’t.I</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_002-18a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-09T07:41:51.164+09:00">f you know then hold it as you know,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR1h0004_tls_002-19a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2024-03-09T07:42:57.129+09:00"> That is wisdom(zhi 知).”    [The word zhi 知 can mean knowledge (or to know), wisdom (zhi 智), understanding, realization, and setting one’s heart-mind on something (and hence having aspiration). Of the six occurrences of the word in this passage, the first seems to mean aspiration (see the following quote from theXun Zi), the middle four are commonly taken as “know” or “knowledge” (although the Dingzhou text has all six written as zhi 智). The last one can be read either as “knowledge” or “wisdom,” but (again given the quote from the Xun Zi) it seems better to be taken as wisdom.The Master’s remark reminds us of Socrates’ “knowing one’s own ignorance is wisdom,” and Lao Zi’s “To know that you don’t know is knowledge/wisdom. To say that you know when you don’t know is an illness” (Lao Zi,chap. 71). While ordinarily people think that the more one learns the more one knows, interestingly and paradoxically, the more one learns the more one realizes how much one does not know. But there is more in Confucius’ teaching than simply knowing one’s ignorance—it is also an attitude toward life, as is illustrated in a fuller account of the story in the Xun Zi:Zilu dressed in fancy clothes when he came to see Confucius. Confucius said, “You [Zilu], what is the reason for the fanciness?Early on, when the Yangtze emerges from Mount Min, at its origin its flow is barely enough to overflow a goblet. But when it reaches the crossing point, then without tying together boats and avoiding the winds, you would not be able to cross it. Is this not simply because of the vast amount of water flowing own? Now your clothes are fancy and your countenance is puffed up. Who in the world would be willing to remonstrate with you like this?”</seg>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>