<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR3a0014-en-a7f8cdba" type="transl">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Offerings of Jade and Silk</title>
                <editor role="translator">Howard J. Wechsler</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</ab>
                <availability status="4">The copyright status of this work is unclear</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Offerings of Jade and Silk</title>New Haven: Yale University Press, 1985</bibl>
                <ab>Translation of <bibl corresp="#KR3a0014">
                        <title xml:lang="och">中說</title>
                    </bibl> into <lang xml:lang="en">English</lang>.</ab>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#CH">Initially created: <date>2025-02-09T23:07:33.446+09:00</date> by CH</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Translated parts</head>
                <p xml:id="KR3a0014-start">
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_010-9a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:14:36.002+09:00">p. 16 【Wang T'ung says that he compiled the Primal Classic in order to demonstrate the historical legitimacy (lit. t'ien-ming) of certain regimes, much, he said, as the Spring and Autumn Annals had been written to demonstrate the legitimacy of the Chou dynasty.  】"Was not my writing of the Continued Classics [Hsü-ching sic!] and Primal Classic all about knowledge of t'ien-ming?" 【he once asked rhetorically. From other comments made by Wang we can see that he traced a line of legitimate succession from theHan dynasty to Western Chin (265-317), Eastern Chin (317-420), Liu-Sung (420-79), Northern Wei (386-535), Northern Chou (557-81), andSui (581-618). This line seems a bit strange in light of the progressionfrom Liu-Sung, a southern Chinese regime, to Northern Wei, a “‘barbarian”’regime of the North, but it may have been conditioned in part byWang’s family background: His great-grandfather, who first lived underthe Liu-Sung, later decided to resettle under the Northern Wei.25 Wang’sgreat-grandfather’s transfer to the North, moreover, personified a muchwider trend of the times.】</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:20:27.743+09:00">p. 17  【Wang’s criteria for legitimacy are expressed most explicitly in relationto the Northern Wei, a dynasty from which he traced his own descent viahis great-grandfather, in a discussion with one of his disciples, TungCh’ang:】Tung Ch’ang inquired:</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:21:02.15+09:00">‘Why in the Primal Classic are Northern Wei [rulers]referred to as emperors [i.e. treated as legitimate]?’?</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:21:13.722+09:00">The Master replied:</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:21:26.422+09:00">““Amid such distress of disorder and dispersion,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:26:10.694+09:00">Whither can I betakemyself?’?</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:22:22.991+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:22:47.317+09:00">They who serve Heaven and Earth</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.10" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:23:01.254+09:00">and protect the living peopleare my sovereigns.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:23:14.967+09:00">As to they who occupy the land of the Former Kings</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:23:21.735+09:00">andreceive the Way of the Former Kings,</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR3a0014_tls_007-10a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2025-02-09T23:54:27.404+09:00"> how can I, being [one of] the people ofthese Former Kings, not also refer to them as such?’’38 【Wang thereby implies the existence of four criteria for the presence ofpolitical legitimacy. A regime must (1) serve Heaven and Earth, presumablyby means of the rituals dedicated to them; (2) nourish and protect thecommon people; (3) physically occupy the territory ruled by former legitimaterulers of China; and (4) follow the rituals and procedures of formerrulers.Unlike the Sung theorist Ou-yang Hsiu, Wang did not regard thepresence of a unified empire as a sine qua non ofl egitimacy. Also, unlikemost other Sung scholars, Wang seems to have been favorably disposed tonon-Chinese dynasts who maintained Chinese ritual and rules of etiquette.Legitimacy, then, was to be conferred even on “‘barbarians”’ as long asthey preserved and promoted traditional Chinese culture, a thought thatwould have been anathema to most Sung Neo-Confucians, intent as theywere on stressing native Chinese traditions.】</seg>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>