<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR5c0126-en-c4a7da35" type="comment">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Comments to 莊子</title>
                <editor role="creator">John Robert Williams</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</p>
                <availability status="1">This work is in the public domain</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by members of the TLS project</p>
                <p>Comments and notes to <bibl corresp="#KR5c0126">
                        <title xml:lang="och">莊子</title>
                    </bibl>for translation <ref target="#none"/>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#CH">Initially created: <date>2022-09-11T16:52:54.803+09:00</date> by CH</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Comments</head>
                <p xml:id="KR5c0126-start">
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-2a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-12T09:46:25.644+09:00">塞 is to "hinder/obstruct", surely not "boost"? I read this very differently than Lynn, the idea is that (following Cheng Xuanying) if one promotes 德 it hinders the natural functioning of one's 性. It appears he is following Wang Shumin's emendation. However, Cheng Xuanying and the earlier commentators straightforwardly read 塞.  He is letting the later textual scholarship guide his translation here, despite his claim to read it as Guo Xiang would have.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-2a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T14:10:58.217+09:00">NB: Lynn reads Zhuang Zhou as casting the blame on these figures, rather than seeing these figures as a cautionary tale of those who pursued 名 and thereby stifled their 性.  Zhuang Zhou is apparently casting blame rather than telling a cautionary tale for Guo Xiang: the masses emulate these figures and are thereby led astray. | LYM 91: 曾史，曾參, 史鰌也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T09:27:44.798+09:00">LXY: 涇, 濁也, 黃河之水, 驟至而濁, 拍滿兩岸, 故曰涇流之大兩涘, 非涇渭之涇也。(NB: LXY parses differently: 涇流之大两涘, 渚崖之間不辯牛馬。) | LYM: 涇，濁也，非涇渭之涇，須辨。 (JRW: "Jing 涇 is to be turbid, muddy. It is not the 'Jing 涇' of 'the rivers Jing 涇 and Wei 渭'. They must be distinguished.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.14" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-26T23:18:26.244+09:00">This seems peculiar.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-28T02:53:49.421+09:00">Is this about how many times one heard the dao, or the amount of daos one has heard?</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.18" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-26T23:21:32.856+09:00">More interpolations. Where does the "still" come in?</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T09:40:06.81+09:00">Common interpolation of "can't" | LYM: 是水大岸遠、見物模糊一段的景況。摹寫逼真，入手便奇。 (JRW: "The large/main bank of the river is distant and visible things appear indistinct/mixed up, this sets the scene of the whole section. The description is distinct/lifelike, and as a point of departure, it is remarkable.") (NB: 大 and 模糊 are the guiding themes of the entire section.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.23" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T09:31:30.691+09:00">The "my own eyes" implies that he has heard of the immensity of the Northern Sea before this occasion. This seems an unwarranted interpolation.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:52:03.598+09:00">More interpolations that are neither warranted by the text nor by GX's annotation. (Although later commentators basically agree with the interpretation, LYM: 大方，猶大道也。)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-26T23:30:07.857+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-26T23:31:28.159+09:00">"Just as" is another interpolation. Nothing GX says warrants it.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T17:52:40.973+09:00">LXY: 篤於時者, 言所知止一時也 (JRW: "'It is adapted to its season' means that what it understands stops with a single season.") (NB: The suggestion that GX is preferable to LXY often proves unwarranted. The summer insect's understanding is confined. This same point is made in chapter one. "Devotion" has odd connotations here.) </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T11:40:50.261+09:00">"bumpkin scholar" for 曲士 has its charm, though "provincial scholar" seems more accurate. "Bumpkin" has the unwarranted connotation of a hillbilly in the deep south of the US. </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-26T23:43:19.542+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:06:41.965+09:00">Unfortunate comma before "yet", sloppy copy editing. </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T15:30:33.01+09:00">LXY: 尾閭, 沃焦也, 出山海經, 言海永至此, 隨沃隨乾。以海比之天地, 但見其小, 豈知其大! 禪家所謂「任大也須從地起, 更高猶自有天來」, 便是此意。(JRW: "Weilü is Wojiao from the Classic of Mountains Seas...") (NB: Later commentators agree with this identification.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.18" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:53:33.719+09:00">I prefer it being Ruo himself that doesn't know here and in 不知何時止而不盈 above, it fits better with the recurrent themes of 知止其所不知 (ZZ 2?) and 不知吾所以然而然 (ZZ 19?). The general "it is not known" is not invited by GX's commentary. This stuff just happens without Ruo knowing how or why. Despite being grander than the Earl of the River, Ruo is not preoccupied with himself. NB: GX's annotation calls to mind WP's annotation on the Dismissive Quail vis-a-vis Phoenix (ZZ 1): the small should not resent the "largeness" of the large, and the large should not be haughty regarding their "largeness" vis-a-vis "the small". </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.31" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:23:13.457+09:00">LXY: 礨空, 小穴也 | LYM: 礨空，水穴也。 </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.32" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:12:04.235+09:00">Shifting rendering of 計 from the previous sentence. </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.36" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:23:25.669+09:00">LYM: 人處萬物之中，只爲一物之數。此合大虚之間凡可名者論之也。(JRW: "Man is situated amid the myriad creatures/things and only counts as one kind of creature/thing. Man is discussed together with all that is namable in this great void.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.35" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:43:24.931+09:00">had to combine 號物之數 here to accommodate Lynn's rendering. </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.40" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:25:01.765+09:00">Lynn shifts from "mankind" to "a man" | LYM: 人在九州之内，只算得做一件。此合鳥獸草木論之也。(JRW: "The men within the Nine Regions only count as a single item/thing. Man is discussed together with birds, beasts, plants, and trees.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.37" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:26:44.44+09:00">LXY: 人卒, 人眾也 (JRW: "'Ren zu' is the multitude of men.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.46" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:25:26.571+09:00">LYM: 任士，任事之人也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.43" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T16:30:41.8+09:00">LYM: 連，猶承接也。| I like "Thearchs for 帝. It seems an improvement over the standard translation.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:30:51.021+09:00">LYM: 此段言道之大，本無窮極。在世界中所爲自多者，皆自小耳，不足稱也。(JRW: "This section discusses the immensity of the Way:  it is basically infinite. Those in the world who regard themselves as 'large' are all merely 'small' themselves, they are unworthy of comment.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:33:31.542+09:00">LYM: 言小者既不可爲大，若此則吾於物大的還他大，小的還他小，何如？ </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T20:12:43.487+09:00">LXY: 物量無窮, 言物不可得而量度也。(JRW: "'When you assess the things of this world, they are inexhaustible' means that the things cannot be quantified.") | LYM: 量, 謂局量之大小 (JRW: "'Liang 量' refers to measuring 'large' and 'small'.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T18:35:51.376+09:00">LXY: 時無止, 言寒暑晝夜, 相尋無已也。(JRW: "'Times never stop' means that winters and summers and days and nights alternate each other without ceasing.")  | LYM: 時，謂所值之先後 </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T20:21:28.609+09:00">LXY: 分無常, 言有無得失, 人之分劑, 或先或後, 初無定也。(JRW: "'Divisions are never constant' means that 'there is' and 'there is not' and 'gain' and 'loss'... are originally indeterminate.") | LYM: 分，謂此生之得失 (JRW: "'Fen 分' refers to the gains and losses of this life.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.10" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:17:28.229+09:00">LYM: 終始，謂死生存亡之變。故，言物皆無一定，而各各自足也。(JRW: "'Beginning and end' (zhong shi) refers to the alterations between death and life, surviving and perishing. 'No fixed rule' (gu) means that things are all unfixed, yet each is sufficient to itself.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.34" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:39:29.544+09:00">LXY: 倪, 端也</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:38:08.035+09:00">LXY: 域, 方所也 | LYM: 此段言天下之理，大小本自無定，言大言小皆無有是處。(JRW: "This section discusses the principles of the world: 'large' and 'small' are basically themselves indeterminate, and talk of 'large' and 'small' is all without any set basis.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:41:21.678+09:00">LYM: 信情，實理也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T12:42:09.766+09:00">LYM: 垺 = 孚</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-2a.50" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T16:32:58.132+09:00">Savage!</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T13:50:20.744+09:00">The repeated "then asked" is perhaps bad storytelling. It makes everything conjunctive, whereas "replied" would give the sense of one thing following from another. </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:39:43.294+09:00">LYM: 惟不盡，故謂其不可圍; 惟不明，故謂其無形。 以此觀之，大小之勢異便有若然耳。* 細玩「自細視大」二語，虧他偏道得出。 (JRW: "One does not get to the bottom of it, thus he calls it 'uncircumscribable'; one does not get a clear view of it, thus he calls it 'its shapelessness'. From this perspective, the conditions of the 'large' and 'small' are merely separated for convenience in this way. * He is subtly playing with the phrase 'look at the small from the point of view of the large'...")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:40:04.418+09:00">LYM: 夫言精言粗，皆期其有形者而言之矣。若無形不可圍，則無此異便之勢也，故數所不能分不能窮也。(JRW: "Now when speaking of the 'quintessential' and the 'coarse', discussing them invariably depends on their having physical shapes. Supposing the shapeless cannot be circumscribed, then there is nothing in its circumstances for separating them [i.e., the 'quintessential' and 'coarse'] for convenience,  and that is why things which cannot be numerically cut up into parts cannot be exhausted.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.24" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T16:58:20.593+09:00">LYM: 分之窮之，所謂言與意也。可以言論意致，而物之精粗見焉，總不能離有形之相。若言與意皆無所用，方成極致，連精粗之名無從着落矣。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.27" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T11:55:54.479+09:00">LYM: 其行雖不害人，亦不以仁恩自多也。(JRW: "Although his conduct does not harm others, he still does not invoke 'benevolence' and 'generosity' to make boisterous claims about himself.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.29" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T12:06:34.084+09:00">LYM: 其動雖不爲利，亦不以門隸爲求利之人而賤之也。(JRW: "Although his initiatives do not aim at a profit, he still does not regard the servant at the gate as a profit-seeker and look down upon him.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.34" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:42:02.783+09:00">LYM: 雖不借人以舉事，亦不自食乎力以自多，且人有貪污之行者，亦不賤之。貪污，如借人舉事之類。(JRW: "Although he does not rely on others to tackle his own affairs, he still does not live by his own effort so as to make boisterous claims about himself. Moreover, when it comes to those men with corrupt conduct, he still does not look down upon them. The corrupt are like that class of men who rely on others to tackle their own affairs.")    | NB: LYM reads 貪污 for 貪汙 in his commentary, though the base text still reads 貪汙.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.36" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T11:29:15.327+09:00">LYM: 行殊乎俗，則多辟異之行，人皆多之而不以爲多。(JRW: "When one's conduct parts from that of the common crowd, then one makes boisterous claims about one's uniqueness. Men all make boisterous claims about it, but he does not think anything of it.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.38" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T11:28:37.971+09:00">LYM: 爲在從衆，則多佞諂之心，人皆賤之而不以爲賤。 (JRW: "When one's activities consist in following along with the mob, one engages in a lot of eloquent flattery. Men all despise it, but he does not think anything of it.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.42" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:11:51.607+09:00">LYM: 以上皆言玄同之德，自合如此。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T11:07:16.701+09:00">LYM: 約分，言收斂分量，以至於不聞不得無己地位，方是不期精粗處。* 此段言大道本無精粗，大人體道，亦惟於不期精粗之極而求之也。(JRW: ... * "This section maintains that the Great Way basically has no 'quintessential' versus 'coarse', and when the great man embodies the Way....")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:13:06.333+09:00">LYM: 又問於無分别中，忽至於有分别，從何而致？倪，緒之两頭者，蓋取以爲分别之義。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T13:17:57.952+09:00">LYM: 言其皆自貴而賤人也。 (JRW: "He means that they all honor themselves and despise others.") (Echoes of GX.) </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T14:50:07.575+09:00">LYM: 貴賤之權，本非己所能操，猶趙孟之所貴，趙孟能賤之也。 (JRW: "The scales of 'honor' and 'disgrace' are basically not something which one can control by oneself...") cf. the Nicomachean Ethics ranking the life of honor beneath the contemplative life, as the former requires others to bestow honors upon one, which is said to be out of one's control.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.33" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T10:42:25.962+09:00">LYM: 趣操，猶趣尚之操持也。此又因大小而及是非，見是非之各成其所適也。* 此段總言物之内外、貴賤、大小，原無定屬。筆筆生動，有生龍活虎之勢。 (JRW: "... Here he again reaches 'affirming' versus 'denying' on the basis of 'large' versus 'small', he shows each thing achieves what is suitable for it through affirming  and denying. * This section generally maintains that (the dichotomies between) 'inner' and 'outer', 'honor' and 'disgrace', and 'large' and 'small' of things are based on no fixed categories. The penmanship is vivid, it is lively and full of energy.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T14:47:26.488+09:00">LYM: 因人以爲大小，則無物不可爲大小矣。知其無不可爲大小，則物之差數見乎！言大小本可以相爲也。 (JRW: "Because if men regard these as 'large' or 'small', then anything can be 'large' or 'small'. When one understands anything can be 'large' or 'small', then the relativity of size is in view!  He means that 'large' and 'small'  basically can be used one for the other.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.26" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T10:41:32.374+09:00">LYM: 功分，猶功用之定分也。此又因大小而及有無，見有無之不可偏廢也。(JRW: "... Here he again reaches 'possessing' versus 'not possessing' on the basis of 'large' versus 'small', he shows one should not neglect one thing at the expense of another through possessing and not possessing.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-6a.10" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T16:07:25.475+09:00">LYM: 讓，美德也; 争，賤名也。然各有時不一焉。此舉古人以明貴賤、大小之無常者也。 (JRW: "To abdicate is a fine virtue; to contend is a despised name. However, each one is at times different. Here he mentions these men of antiquity in order to explain the lack of constancy between 'honor' and 'disgrace' and 'large' and 'small'.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-6a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:20:05.708+09:00">LYM: 梁麗，屋棟也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-6a.22" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T08:44:51.724+09:00">LYM: 此舉物理以見貴賤大小之無常也。 (JRW: "This mentions the principles of things in order to show the lack of constancy between 'honor' and 'disgrace' and 'large' and 'small'.")  </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-6a.27" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-05T14:53:13.263+09:00">LYM: 殊器、殊技、殊性，大有所能，小有所拙，用於此者或廢於彼，物理如此，猶之天下無常是之理，古今無常治之世也。然則倪貴賤，分大小，執有方之見，而不知無常之變者，皆爲不明天地之理，萬物之情者也。 (JRW: "'Different tools', 'different skills', and 'different inborn capacities': the 'large' ones have what they are capable of, and the 'small' ones have what they are incompetent at, what is useful for 'this' one is sometimes destructive for 'that' one, the principles of things are like this... That being the case, when it comes to our distinctions between 'honor' and 'disgrace' and 'large' and 'small',  one who holds onto a perspective with fixed borders and does not understand the inconstant alterations (between them) is invariably one who fails to understand the principles of Heaven and Earth and the basic natures of the myriad things.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-6a.40" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T14:52:02.921+09:00">LYM: 此又言貴賤本於時。當時、失時，使一事而貴賤分焉。時之難定，則貴賤之難定也。(JRW: "Here he again maintains that 'honor' and 'disgrace' are rooted in the times... If the times are difficult to determine, then 'honor' and 'disgrace' are difficult to determine.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-05T14:54:09.403+09:00">LYM: 「門」字「家」字俱當向裏面説，方與上面「倪」字呼應。* 此段言貴賤大小之名原無定在，亦因乎人强名之耳。若求其倪者，皆非也。 (JRW: "The words 'family' and 'household'....  * This section means that while the names 'honor', 'disgrace', 'large', and 'small' have nothing determinate in them, one still simply adapts to (yin) the imposed naming of things by man. If one seeks out their internal basis (ni), he will inevitably fail.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-05T14:55:12.328+09:00">LYM: 因前言。不生分别，則我之所爲似無所適從矣。(JRW: "This follows from the previous doctrine. If no divisions come about, then what one does seems to have nothing with which to suitably/comfortably (shi) comply.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:23:30.005+09:00">LYM: 衍者，廣平之地，反之則平復爲陂。平陂之分，未始有常，貴賤往反，豈異於是？慎毋以世情之見以拘爾志，與道乖蹇而不能通也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:24:00.822+09:00">LYM: 施者仁之用，謝之則賜予而不以爲仁，多少之數非所計也。慎毋執一而行，與道背馳而不能合也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:24:29.438+09:00">Input error? LYM has only one 嚴</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.26" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:25:16.445+09:00">LYM: 無拘無一，則無方之德也，故形容三段，總見其無方也。承翼，承接扶翼也。唯其無方，故能以萬物爲方，長短皆足也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.37" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-05T14:55:55.067+09:00">LYM: 夫道固無終始也，乃物則有生死焉，不能恃以爲常，惟見其一虚一實，不可守其定位於形迹之間。何也？四時之序，成功者退。去而不可追者，年也; 流而不可止者，時也。天地之化，消息盈虚，如循連環，終則有始也。大義，即大理。 (JRW: "Now if the Way definitely has no end or beginning, then only things have 'life' and 'death'. These cannot be relied on and taken as constant, one can only observe their waxing and waning. One cannot safeguard the determinate positions between the traces of the physical shapes.  Why? ...")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T13:53:35.387+09:00">LYM: 夫固將自化，言人不能出乎數之化，或爲或不爲，皆適如其化之自運耳。* 此段言人之所爲，當任其道之自然，無容其有爲有不爲於其間也。(JRW: "... * This section means that when what is wrought by man [ch. 6] appropriately complies with the nature of their way, then there is no place for 'acting' versus 'not acting' within this space/interval.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T14:07:15.949+09:00">LYM: 承上言。順其自化，則無物不在於化之中。然則何貴於道，而必以道物身也？此問極細極靈。  (JRW: "This supports the above statement. If one follows one's own transformations, then everything falls within the purview of these transformations. If this is so, then why honor the Way...? This question is extremely delicate.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T14:30:15.122+09:00">LYM: 理，謂消息盈虚之理。權，則所以善其用於不窮者也。不以物害己，言不以外物以傷其身，如死名死利之數，包括甚廣。(JRW: "'Principles' refers to the principles of growth and decay and waxing and waning. Quan 權 then is what one uses to be deft in his utilization of what is not exhausted by him. 'One does not harm oneself for the sake of (mere) things' means that he does not allow external things to harm his body/person, such as dying for titles or dying for advantages...")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T05:47:44.42+09:00">LYM: 不以害爲害，故莫之能害也。* 却説出實理來，不過是素位而行，不怨不尤工夫，何曾一字荒唐！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.28" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-09-27T21:28:25.203+09:00">LYM: 辨論不至徹底窮究，亦不休乎！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.34" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T15:33:56.25+09:00">LYM: 言天人相須以有成，不可相離也。(JRW: "He means that Heaven and man rely on each other in order to have success, they cannot be separated from each other.") NB: This is an interesting take, as many treat this vignette as offering a superficial distinction between Heaven and man. Cf. Brook A. Ziporyn (2009, 73 n. 7), whom many sheepishly follow: "It is worth noting the stark difference between this passage and the position put forth in the Inner Chapters, which makes the distinction between the Heavenly and the Human only to overturn it into unknowability (6:5) and even provisionally is only willing to say that neither should overpower the other (6:23). Here, on the contrary, the Heavenly definitively means the natural, while the Human means the deliberate and artificial; the two terms have definite contents, these can be unproblematically known, and “Virtuosity resides in the Heavenly.” Compare Chapters 8 and 9, which also offer a fixed definition of the content of the Heavenly inborn nature."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-9a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T06:36:16.145+09:00">LYM: 故者，有心而爲之謂。命，天命也。得，謂己德。殉名，喪於爲名也。反真，入道也。* 此段言入道之法，不可安排造作，以人勝天也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T09:37:33.74+09:00">LYM: 聞道僅百耳，不及萬分之一, 遂以人莫己若，此不知量之甚者矣。 (JRW: "To merely hear of the Way approximately a hundred times is less than one ten-thousandth, thus in taking no others as greater than himself, this one fails to understand the extreme/impressive kinds of measure.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T11:33:26.703+09:00">Lynn takes 物 as "people"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T16:20:13.617+09:00">Cf. Watson, who makes more sense to me here (as elsewhere): "These are merely what are called endless changes."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T16:22:28.01+09:00">Cf. Watson: "These are merely what are called boundless turnings."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-7a.28" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T16:29:10.439+09:00">物 as "people"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T16:36:49.282+09:00">權 as "incipiency"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-04T07:17:28.293+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-8a.22" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T16:44:04.996+09:00">人 as "Heaven", surely an error or unmarked substitution (NB: nothing said by GX or CXY warrants this.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-9a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T15:01:29.027+09:00">LYM: 夔一足，蚿多足，蛇無足，皆自能行，然猶有形似。風則無形而自行，目則不行而自至，雖無形，然猶以形用也。心則以神用，而古今宇宙無不周到， 故相羨也。| 絶頂異解，隨口出之，不顧天荒地老，所謂「不可無一，不可有二」者。(JRW: "The kui-dragon is one-legged, the millipede is many-legged, the snake is legless, they are all able to move of their own accord, yet they still have physical shapes. When it comes to the wind, it is physically shapeless but moves of its own accord...")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-9a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T16:54:59.765+09:00">LYM: 噴唾之喻，構思迥異常諦。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-11a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:01:47.128+09:00">LYM: 此段言天機所動，各有自然，彼之所難，此之所易，則難易不在於多少有無之間也。亦河伯問答一段餘意。| 心、目二語，不着疏解，文如半身美人圖，正於未畫處傳神。奇絶！奇絶！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-10a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:02:39.54+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-10a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:02:15.394+09:00">LYM: 有似，有形似也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-9a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:07:48.427+09:00">天機 as "celestial mechanism"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-11a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:40:19.658+09:00">惙 as "cease" | LYM: 「輟」同。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-12a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:37:56.62+09:00">LYM: 此段言聖人能以小不勝爲大勝也，承上面「物不能害」 來。|「諱窮」、「求通」等語，以擬聖人之言，恐覺不似，且筆頗平庸，非莊所作也。 (!!!)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-11a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:39:14.541+09:00">Cf. Watson: "the men of Sung surrounded him with several encirclements of troops,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-11a.26" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T17:46:04.464+09:00">Lynn's rendering demands I combine both lines here.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-13a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-03T12:41:20.926+09:00">LYM: 埳井，壞井也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-13a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T18:04:29.068+09:00">LYM: 井幹，井欄也。缺甃，井甃缺而成崖者。接掖持頤，鼃赴水則以两腋拍水，如接物者然。持頤，緊閉其口也。還，回顧也。虷，水中赤蟲。[...]</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-14a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-02T18:03:27.144+09:00">LYM: 商蚷，馬蚿也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-13a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-03T12:36:57.827+09:00">机 does have the mu radical here. Cf. chapter 2, where most editions do not (aside from Wang Xianqian's).</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-13a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-03T12:40:16.676+09:00">仰天 calls to mind the same passage from chapter 2 as the 隱机, the 敢問其方, and the 子獨不聞. These allusions seem to be a parody of sorts.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-13a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-03T12:48:14.143+09:00">GX makes the obvious link with the little creatures from chapter 1.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-3a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-08T10:35:27.976+09:00">LXY: 終始無故, 言無終無始, 無新無故也。是故大知者, 謂有大智之人, 而後有下面四知也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-17a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T12:21:50.362+09:00">NB: Lines are combined owing to Lynn's rendering. | LYM: 練實，竹實也。嚇，怒其聲，恐其奪己食也。千古鄙夫患失之態，只以一語寫盡矣！* 此段言貴者有貴之賤，而賤者有賤之貴，趣操不同，願各有極也。承上 「察乎安危」三句來。 (JRW: "... * This section discusses the lowliness of the honors of the honorable and the honorableness of the disgraces of the lowly...")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-14a.14" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T18:53:32.438+09:00">LYM: 跐，蹈也。奭然，釋然也。四解，四達也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-14a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T12:33:32.264+09:00">LYM: 玄冥，溟涬之先也。大通，大道也。(NB: LYM is in the camp of those who take 大通 as 大道, like GX and unlike CXY.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-14a.24" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T18:57:13.073+09:00">LYM: 未丁之夫曰餘子。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-14a.25" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T18:58:12.419+09:00">LYM: 國能，彼國之所能也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-14a.33" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T12:38:35.778+09:00">LYM: 此段言小勝者不能爲大勝也，無甚深旨，莊叟亦無貶人自譽至此，恐爲後人贋筆。(JRW: "This section maintains that a 'small' winner cannot be a 'large' winner. There is no deep point here. Our Old Zhuang for his part has nowhere denigrated others/the man in his own examples up till this point. I fear this is a forgery by latter-day persons.") (NB: An amusing criterion. It is neither philosophical nor philological grounds, but rather predicated on the grounds that Zhuang Zhou was not believed to be a jackass.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-16a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T19:01:42.889+09:00">LYM: 結韻悠然有致。* 此段言知道者安於賤而不知有貴，然即於賤而自得其貴也。承上「察乎安危」三句來。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-16a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-06T19:06:24.842+09:00">LYM: 當知此時莊子之見非打抽豐，惠子之搜非逐遊客也。可勝粲然！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-17a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T12:17:29.074+09:00">LYM: 两人機鋒絶唱，異樣辯才，真一時之勝事，難得！難得！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-17a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T12:10:51.695+09:00">LYM: 言我與女雖不相知，然爲人也，若魚則異類矣，故爲人不知之全。(JRW: "He means that even though you and me do not understand each other, nevertheless we are human. If you were fish, then you'd be of a different category/genus. Thus, qua human, you utterly fail to understand them.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-17a.22" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T11:57:07.852+09:00">LYM: 請循其本，言當反汝問我之本意也。「女安知魚樂」云者，是明知我之知而問我矣，我以身居濠上而樂，則在濠下者可知也。* 此段言人情物理，自可相推。魚遂其樂，亦自得其天者，故魚忘江湖，人忘道術， 其致一也。 (JRW: "'Please let us try to get back to the basics' means that we/they should return to the basic idea of your/his question to me/him. 'Whence you know the joys of the fish?' is clearly to know one knows this, and thus one asks this. When one is positioned above the river Hao and is joyous, then those who are in the river Hao below can be understood. * This section maintains that the basic feelings of man and the principles of things (&gt; non-human creatures) can themselves be extended to one another. Fish pursue their joy and, for their part, they themselves achieve what is natural to them. In this way when fish forget rivers and lakes and when men forget their methods of the Way, then their results are one and the same." ) (NB: This is a case where the interpretation of the first edition [before the astrics] is quite different than that of the second edition [after the astrics]. The second edition reading seems much better, in my view. Note also the Mengzian use of 推, like the ruler who understood the suffering of an ox, and Mengzi 推-ed that understanding/commiseration to others. Note the links between 忘, 其天者, and 其樂. The first edition reading renders the whole thing sophistical and merely charming at best.)   </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.3-h" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:23:12.894+09:00">歸曰:「一論大通之理，二論大勝之力，三論達命之事，四論至言之妙，五論全身之高，六論心知之道。」(藥地炮莊 ) (JRW: Guī [= Guī Yǒuguāng 歸有光 (1507-1571)] says: "First, he discusses the principles of the Great Thoroughfare. Second, he discusses the strength of 'large' victories. Third, he discusses the matter of thoroughly grasping fate. Fourth, he discusses the sublimity of fully-realized speech. Fifth, he discusses the loftiness of an intact/complete body/person. Sixth, he discusses the Way of conscious understanding.") (NB: A rough, provisional stab at breaking down the content of the sections, in case CJY waivers here. Note that 方以智 (1611-1671) says this is 歸有光 (1507-1571), yet FY (b. 1956) says it is 楊起元 (1547-1599)) |  王宗沐曰:《莊子》一部，惟此篇深言之，禪書萬卷，曾不出此。」愚則曰:「《莊子》一部，惟此篇淺言之。」(藥地炮莊 ) (JRW: Wáng Zōngmù 王宗沐 (1523-1591) says: "In this whole part of the Zhuangzi, only with this chapter does he speak profoundly. The myriad scrolls of Chan documents have never brought this out." I [ Fāng Yǐzhì 方以智 (1611-1671)] humbly reply: "In this whole part of the Zhuangzi, only with this chapter does he speak superficially.") (NB: The mixed reception of this chapter is not only a contemporary phenomenon!)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-1a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-07T14:45:19.213+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-2a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:32:46.426+09:00">Cf. Watson: "this is a stupid way to treat the body."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-2a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:34:38.778+09:00">Cf. Watson: "this is a superficial way to treat the body."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-2a.14" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:38:16.462+09:00">Cf. Watson: "a bitter lot indeed!"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-2a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:38:58.346+09:00">Cf. Watson: "This is a callous way to treat the body."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-3a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:45:01.596+09:00">Cf. Watson: "what they all make a mad dash for,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-4a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:50:48.889+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Let me try putting it this way."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-1a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T09:58:39.577+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-5a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-12T22:32:06.945+09:00">NB: Lynn never closes the quotation. | LYM 185: 芒，即混芒之義。芴，即沕穆之義。 職職，繁殖也。此總言無爲而無不爲，至樂活身皆由此也。* 此段是一篇之旨。步步相生，針線甚密，無一毫渗漏，恐非莊叟所作也。(JRW: "... This is broadly talking about 'doing nothing and leaving nothing undone' [ZZ 22, 23, 25, DDJ 37, 48]. The ultimate joy and a stable life both follow from this. * This section is the gist of the whole chapter. Step-by-step it is brought forth; the layout is very meticulous, without a single bit of minutiae left out.  I fear that it is not something our Old Zhuang would write.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-4a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-12T14:24:20.673+09:00">LYM 185: 無爲，所以無樂無譽，所以爲至樂至譽，與上富、貴、壽相應。至譽，與上争名相應。 (JRW: "He takes no deliberate action, that is why he is not preoccupied with joy or praise, and that is why he comes to have the ultimate joy and ultimate praise. This resonates the aforementioned 'wealth', 'honor', and 'longevity'.  The 'ultimate praise' resonates with the aforementioned 'contenting for titles'.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-2a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:14:23.091+09:00">LYM reads 烈士 for 列士.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-2a.25" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:15:48.253+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-3a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-12T11:30:03.953+09:00">LYM 184: 蹲循，逡巡退聽之貌。言忠諫不見聽，即當却去，不必與之争也。* 此段單貼「善」字，根「可以活身」句來。 (JRW: "'Dun xun 蹲循' is descriptive of hesitating and drawing back, yielding and listening. He means that if his faithful remonstrations go unheeded, then he ought to back off. It is unnecessary to contend with him. * ...")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-5a.23" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-14T12:29:00.867+09:00">Cf. Watson: "It's just like the progression of the four seasons, spring, summer, fall, winter." | LYM 186:  本是如此，目前常理，人皆不知，何也？(JRW: "Basically it is like this, this is the current commonsense....") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-5a.24" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-13T08:53:02.516+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Now she's going to lie down peacefully in a vast room." | LYM 186: 以死爲寢，絶無分别，驚人之談，虧他偏説得出。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-5a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:29:24.769+09:00">LYM 185: 盆，瓦缶也，鼓之所以節音也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-5a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:32:13.182+09:00">LYM 185: 莊子絶是近情之人，此句便自己道破。 (NB: LYM's text reads 槩 for 概, but he glosses「概」同.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-5a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:32:48.652+09:00">LYM 185: 生，指知覺運動而言。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-5a.25" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:37:07.123+09:00">LYM 186: 此等模樣果何爲邪？真個無謂。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-6a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:38:39.638+09:00">LYM 186: 命，天命之流行，即上面春夏秋冬相尋於無己，不必作命運説。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-6a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:47:29.772+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Uncle Lack-Limb and Uncle Lame-Gait were seeing the sights at Dark Lord Hill" | LYM 186: 冥伯，已死之稱，猶「冥漠君」之號。(NB: This is a crucial point: when they say they were observing transformations later in the section, the implication is that they are at the sight of those who had died.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-6a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T10:45:00.248+09:00">Cf. Watson: "To live is to borrow"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-6a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T11:47:34.131+09:00">LYM 186: 柳，瘍也。柳多X(illegible)腫，故以爲瘍癤之喻。(NB: Despite the illegible character, it is interesting that just as things get as surreal as the Inner Chapters, our best commentator explains it away!) | FY 797: 柳借為瘤。 (NB: ditto. 滑介叔 suddenly has a tumor: less surreal. Though LYM takes it as a metaphor for a cluster of boils, whereas FY takes it as a loan.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-6a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-13T11:22:24.488+09:00">LYM 186: 假借，即佛經所謂地、水、火、風四大假合是也。生既爲假，又假之而生生焉，是不過如塵垢之集耳。生生，謂身之所生，如瘍癤之類是也，諸解失之。(JRW: "As for 'on a loan', what the Buddhist Sutras call the four elements of earth, water, fire, and wind combining together is precisely a case in point. Since being born is to borrow, then borrowing it and being brought into life in this way is nothing but the gathering together of mere dust. 'Sheng sheng 生生' refers to what generates our bodies as though they were in the category of boils and pimples. The various explanations [of earlier commentators] miss this point." (NB: 假合: 佛教語。謂一切事物均由眾緣和合而成，暫時聚合，終必離散。Thoroughly Buddhist explanation, though not inappropriate in this case.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-7a.10" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T11:51:14.554+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Was your state overthrown"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-7a.25" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T11:56:44.504+09:00">NB: Lynn: 談 = "discourse"; Watson: 談 = "chatter"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-7a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T12:50:50.526+09:00">LYM's text (mistakenly?) reads 檄 for 撽</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-7a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-13T11:26:17.919+09:00">LYM 187: 五問錯落有致。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-7a.27" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T12:35:14.037+09:00">LYM 187: 諸子所言，謂子所問諸語也。* 就伊問語翻跌，極得鬬法。 (NB: I do not know what 鬬法 means... S.O.S.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-8a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-14T12:31:13.233+09:00">LYM 187: 此段齊生死之意，當看得活動。《淮南子》 曰：「始吾未生之時，焉知生之樂也？今吾未死，又焉知死之不樂也？」即此意。若説莊子有厭生歆死之心， 便是癡人説夢矣。 (JRW: "The idea of this section is equalizing life and death... The Huainanzi says: 'In the beginning before I was born, how could I have known the joy of being alive? Now in this moment when I have not yet died, how can I know that death is not also joyful?' (Major et al) It is precisely this idea. If one is to say Master Zhuang has a heart that is bored with life and delights in death, then it is the dream-like talk of an idiot")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-9a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T13:17:01.466+09:00">Cf. Watson: "The marquis will then look for similar greatness within himself"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-9a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T13:17:42.881+09:00">NB: the 之言 extends back to 燧人as well.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-9a.54" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T13:34:07.909+09:00">Cf. Watson: "concepts of right should be founded on what is suitable." </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.2" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T13:46:16.689+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-9a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T22:46:55.319+09:00">LYM 187-88: 人惑則死，若指顔回以攖暴人而死，則與上下文俱不相貫; 若指齊侯，恐世無惑言而死之人。此等拙筆，欲以擬《莊》，何不自量也？ (JRW: "If '人惑則死' refers to Yan Hui offending the tyrannical man and dying, then it is completely disconnected from the surrounding context; if it is referring to the Marquis of Qi, then he is a man who fears that the vulgar world has no perplexing sayings and dies (????). This is such clumsy writing. If he wishes to imitate the Zhuangzi, then why has he not assessed himself?")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-9a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T13:41:55.358+09:00">LYM 187: 褚，布袋也。綆，井繩也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-9a.50" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T21:35:49.038+09:00">LYM 188: 此處又竊《齊物論》篇内數語，改易字面填入，何苦乃爾？(JRW: "This is a place where he once again plagiarizes many words from the Inner Chapter 'A Disquisition that Levels All' [Chapter 2], changing around the wording and adding filler. Why bother if it is only this?")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-13T13:52:09.162+09:00">Cf. Watson: "This is what it means to have command of reason, and good fortune to support you." | LYM 188: 名止於實，各隨其情。義設於適，投人所安也。條達者通於人，福持者利於己。* 此段似指用世而言，攛掇於此，甚屬無謂。其文之平庸淺膚，不問而知其爲僞物也。 (NB: FY does not distinguish the first from the second edition of 莊子因 in 莊子纂要, thus the critical edition is to be preferred: 林雲銘 ​(清). 2011. 莊子因. (張京華 點校). 上海: 華東師範大學出版社.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T13:56:21.175+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T14:06:13.492+09:00">NB: The subjects of 未嘗死 and 未嘗生 do not strike me as entirely obvious. | LYM 188: 攓，扶也。*「惟予」一句十三字不可斷讀，看他説出「惟予與女」四字，妙絶！於大地世界中，只尋得此一副莫逆知己，舍此便無可與言矣！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-10T14:06:39.177+09:00">NB: 養 can mean "sad"(?).</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.10" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T20:41:28.678+09:00">NB: 藥地炮莊 reads 機 for 幾. 王夫之 (or his son 王敔? Alas, I am stupid so it is not always clear to me which one is talking in 莊子解...) notes that one edition reads 機. This fits with the end of the passage: 人又反入於機。萬物皆出於機，皆入於機。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T20:43:40.31+09:00">LYM 188: 言女果以死爲安養乎？予果以生爲歡樂乎？皆未可知。蓋死者不終死，而生者不終生，將變化無所終窮，以起下文之意。諸解失之。(JRW: "... It appears that the dead do not remain dead and the living do not remain living, they will change and transform endlessly. He uses this to raise the point of the following passage....") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T13:09:28.53+09:00">LYM 189: 繼，塵浮水面爲㡭。| NB: Lynn 2022, 338 n. 13: "Two traditions of interpretation have argued over this brief question for centuries; one exemplified by Guo Xiang and Cheng Xuanying takes zhong as zhonglei (species) and ji as “how many”; the other regards ji (how many) as a variant of ji (activating force, incipiency, spring)—that is, the potential spring of life that inheres in things. This tradition begins with Sima Biao, who glosses ji as zhaozhen (portent), the subtle and mysterious incipiency that sages discern in the workings of Heaven and Earth; see Zhuanzi jishi, 3: 625. However, the latter was the minority view during premodern times and came to prominence only in the modern era, with the likes of Ma Xulun (1884–1970), in Zhuangzi yizheng (Documentary evidence for meanings in the Zhuangzi), in which he glosses ji as zhong zhi jiwei er wanwu suoyou shengzhe (“the most minute of seeds from which the myriad things are generated”), 18: 6a; and Hu Shi (1891–1962), in Xian Qin mingxue shi (History of logic in the pre-Qin era), 113, where he glosses ji as jingwei de yuanzi (“most miniscule atom”) or peiya (“germ/gemmule”). Reading zhong as “seed” instead of “species” is also characteristic of this tradition."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.18" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T12:41:50.815+09:00">NB: 竈 = "stove" </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T12:52:28.324+09:00">LYM 189: 水土之際，水得土氣，漸凝漸厚，遂有體質，其色沉緑，名爲鼃蠙之衣。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T12:54:00.355+09:00">LYM 189: 青苔漸漸近土，生於陵屯，化爲陵舄。陵舄即車前草名也</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.14" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T12:54:58.47+09:00">LYM 189: 鬱棲，糞壤也。烏足，草名。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.24" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T13:09:41.221+09:00">LYM 189: 食醯，蠛蠓也。(NB: FY 816 agrees.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.25" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T13:14:42.454+09:00">NB: It appears Lynn mistakenly read the gloss for 食醯 as that for 頤輅. Legge's "pickle-eater" in any event is more amusing to me than Lynn's "vinegar eaters".</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.27" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T13:11:18.7+09:00">LYM 189: 欢。瞀芮，爛草。腐蠸，螢也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.26" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T13:08:04.231+09:00">LYM 189: 軦 = 況.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.29" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T19:21:57.415+09:00">LYM 189: 羊奚，草名，其根若比合於久不生筍之竹，則生青寧，青寧亦蟲也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.30" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-11T19:22:46.879+09:00">LYM 189: 程，或解作豹。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.32" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-14T12:33:53.307+09:00">LYM 189: 馬生人，按《搜神記》，秦孝公時有馬生人。蓋物類之變，難以致詰也。《楞嚴經》云:「人死爲羊，羊死爲人。」佛家亦不肯向人説謊。 (JRW: "As for horses begetting men, according to the 'Investigations into Deities', during the time of Duke Xiao of Qin [381-338 BCE] there were horses giving birth to humans. It appears that creatures transform in kind. This is difficult to investigate. The Shurangama Sutra says: 'Men die and become goats. Goats die and become men.' Buddhists for their part are unwilling to lie to others.") </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-10a.35" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-14T12:34:25.973+09:00">LYM 189: 出者，生也；入者，死也。機者，陰陽二氣之動也。* 此段説出許多物類相生，諸解無所攷據，姑存疑以俟後。大意謂人之生死皆造物化機所動也。(JRW: "'Emerging' (chu 出) is life and 'submerging' (ru 入) is death. The 'mysterious workings' (ji 機) are the movements of the Yin and Yang energy. * This section explains that very many kinds of creatures are born of one another. The various explanations have nothing which substantiates them... The general idea is men's lives and deaths are all moved by the mysterious workings of the Demiurge.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_018-1a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-13T14:31:50.829+09:00">FY 782: 活身者: 養活自然性命的方法，即無爲之道。 (NB: The link between 至樂 and 無爲 is everywhere in the commentaries. E.g., 王雱 (1044-1076): “Only when you can forget yourself and act non-deliberately, then the greatest joyousness exists of its own accord.”  (惟能忘己無為, 則至樂自有。) (南華真經新傳 apud FY 787). And 陸樹芝 (fl. 1796): “This chapter maintains that the greatest joyousness lies in non-deliberate action, whereas the wealth, honor, longevity, and excellence which are the joyousness of the vulgar world are all entanglements to one’s person.”  (此篇言至樂在於無為, 而世俗所樂之富貴壽善, 皆身之累也。) (莊子雪 apud FY 780). ZZ 18 itself establishes the link, so this is not too terribly surprising: “I rely on acting non-deliberately to be truly happy.” (吾以無為誠樂矣). The link will constantly rear its head.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-3a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:00:27.852+09:00">NB: Guo Xiang's commentary creeps into the main text in Lynn's translation here (p. 182). This is fairly common in his translation.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-3a.14" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T13:58:32.83+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Those would not be ways to get rid of troubles." NB: In this case, Lynn seems to be justified in his rendering given he is following GX's interpretation. | LYM 92: 此段言道德之正即性命之情，性命之情各有固然，不假於外之作爲，所以無憂也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-4a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:09:05.055+09:00">Cf. Watson's "Of these two,", which seems an elegant way of handling this worth keeping in the back of one's mind.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-4a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:10:23.825+09:00">Cf. Watson: "but in worrying about it they are identical."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-5a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T13:56:17.322+09:00">Cf. Watson: "what a lot of fuss and hubbub they have made in the world!" | LYM 92:  此段言仁義所以非人情者，以其多憂也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-5a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:19:13.815+09:00">NB: Untranslated by Lynn.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-5a.22" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:25:35.049+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Past and present it has been the same;"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-6a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:29:13.642+09:00">Cf. Watson: "all the men in the world have dashed headlong for benevolence and righteousness."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-6a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:38:17.342+09:00">NB: Lynn's rendering of the next three lines is a jumbled confusion: "Therefore, although the occupations of these several varied and theregard in which they are held was bruited about differently,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-6a.38" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:46:31.337+09:00">NB: shifting renderings of 小人 by Lynn in the same passage.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-6a.36" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T11:47:05.306+09:00">NB: "commonly" is not an ideal word choice.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-7a.37" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T13:42:40.483+09:00">LYM 94: 末仍歸道德之意。仁義、淫僻仍當作一串看。* 通篇以道德爲正宗，以仁義爲駢附，旨本老子。(NB: As is often the case, LYM already made many of the links and discoveries that are presented as innovations in the contemporary Anglo-American scholarship.)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-7a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T13:48:52.034+09:00">LYM 93: 此段言以身爲殉者不同，而同歸於傷性，無異同也。則惑於仁義，與惑於貨財等耳。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-6a.33" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T13:50:57.35+09:00">LYM 93: 絶頂快談，侏儒未免縮舌矣!</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-6a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T13:54:11.801+09:00">LYM 92-93: 此段言天下本有常然，以仁義用之，徒滋其疑擾也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-4a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T13:59:55.359+09:00">LYM 92 reads 仁義 for 仁人.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-2a.23" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T14:01:10.083+09:00">LYM 91-92: 此段言仁義本非道德之正也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-2a.20" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T14:04:05.184+09:00">LYM 91: 敝，疲也。跬，半步而行也。形容其勞之意。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_008-2a.18" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-10-31T14:06:34.462+09:00">LYM 91: 纍瓦結繩，言聚無用之語，如瓦之纍，如繩之結也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-01T12:29:41.372+09:00">NB: 毛 "hair" &gt; "coats" is preferable to "hair"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-01T12:30:34.43+09:00">Cf. Watson: "To munch grass, drink from the stream,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.8" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T11:58:24.375+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Though they might possess great terraces and fine halls," | LYM 96: 王者之居也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.23" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-01T12:36:25.999+09:00">NB: Lynn's translation does not cleanly fit line-for-line here.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-3a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-01T13:04:37.836+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Thus horses learn how to commit the worst kinds of mischief."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-3a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:30:36.26+09:00">NB: Lynn leaves this untranslated. This choice has no basis in GX's commentary. | LYM 98: 介倪，猶睥睨也。闉，曲也。鷙，抵也。曼，突也。詭，銜吐出銜也。竊轡，齧轡也。皆馬之知能至於盜也。言馬而不言埴、木，埴、木無知而馬有知也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T11:59:53.48+09:00">LYM 96: 燒，以火印烙也。剔，剪其毛。刻，削其甲也。雒，絡同。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:02:11.587+09:00">LYM 96: 的，絡首曰羈， 絡足曰馽。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:03:22.138+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.25" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:05:08.904+09:00">LYM 96: 馬銜曰橛，馬纓曰飾。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.41" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:08:15.274+09:00">LYM 96: 此亦治天下之過，言猶治天下者過用其情而傷民性，而反謂之善治也。此段喻爲治者不得民之常性，不足以爲善也。* 描寫治馬情形，備極逼真，忽插陶、 匠一段伴題，便覺文勢紆曲，此有意爲文者也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.48" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:10:02.813+09:00">LYM 96: 天放，曠蕩於天然自有之中，而己私一無所與也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-2a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:11:15.069+09:00">LYM 96-97: 填填，遲重也。顛顛，專直也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-2a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:12:25.94+09:00">LYM 97: 水陸之道不通，故各居其鄉，而自相連屬。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-2a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:14:32.496+09:00">LYM 97 reads 國 for 同.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-2a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:14:58.057+09:00">LYM 97: 民無機心，不相戕賊也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-2a.22" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:16:40.101+09:00">LYM 97: 此段言至德之世，民得其常性，所以爲善治也。* 寫出太古景象，千古在目，令人神 往。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-3a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:19:57.468+09:00">LYM 97: 此段言仁義本是造作出來，以致道德日漓，皆聖人之作俑也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-3a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:23:45.331+09:00">LYM 98: 月題，馬額上當顱(?)如月形者。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-3a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:31:01.855+09:00">LYM (rightly!?) reads 闉扼鷙曼 for 扼鷙曼.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-4a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:34:07.815+09:00">LYM 98: 縣跂，如懸物而使人跤足及之。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-4a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:35:54.446+09:00">LYM 98: 此段從上又推出一 段流弊出來，見得民之好利，皆聖人使之，則仁義禮樂果不足以治天下也。* 文勢疊而非複。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_009-1a.3-h" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T12:38:06.974+09:00">LYM 99: 此篇自首至末， 只是一意，其大旨從上篇「天下有常然」句生來，《莊》文之最易讀者。然其中之體物類情，筆筆生動。或以爲意不多而詞費，疑爲擬《莊》者所作，恐他手未易到此也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T14:48:32.169+09:00">Lynn does not close the quote</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.30" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T14:54:09.253+09:00">Lynn's translation demands a comnbination here.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.32" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T14:54:41.257+09:00">Lynn's translation demands a comnbination here.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-6a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-02T15:44:59.576+09:00">Cf. Watson: "At a time such as this,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:43:44.308+09:00">Cf. Watson: "As long as men in high places covet knowledge and are without the Way," | LYM 104: 有柄之網曰畢。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.15" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T08:57:31.877+09:00">NB: Lynn's rendering does not cleanly fit the line break here.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.32" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T09:12:54.278+09:00">LYM 105: 種種，淳厚也。役役，有爲人也。哼哼，多言者也。已亂天下，要説得緊一 層，言有悦之意，便足亂天下而有餘也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.31" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T09:58:48.471+09:00">LYM  104 glosses 啍 as 諄.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.29" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T10:00:16.705+09:00">LYM 104: 倒鎖(?)一句，遥應上面至德之世，作法甚奇。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-1a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T13:29:37.802+09:00">LYM 100: 胠，開也。* 凡作文起手最難，如此突如來如，奇峰陡起，若神龍變化，無處竟(check against FY)其首尾，蘇長公常得此法。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-1a.10" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T13:29:30.615+09:00">LYM 100: 此句警(check against FY)健有力。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-2a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T14:52:01.428+09:00">LYM 100: 從盜上閒閒寫過，忽落正意，下又忽入引証，文之 變化莫測。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-2a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:31:39.397+09:00">???? Cf. Watson: "the four seasons will not come as they should,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-2a.18" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:30:23.77+09:00">Lynn seems mistaken here. It is about the size of the world in this case, not its greatness.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-2a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:32:49.592+09:00">Cf. Watson: "to be constantly shifting from place to place,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-2a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:33:16.639+09:00">???? Cf. Watson: "to think up schemes that gain nothing,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-2a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:33:46.471+09:00">Cf. Watson: "to set out on roads that reach no glorious conclusion."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-2a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:34:53.077+09:00">Cf. Watson: "it cannot supply sufficient reward or punishment."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-2a.21" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:36:47.061+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-3a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-03T17:42:45.099+09:00">Cf. Watson: "they turn their backs on reason." NB: Chapter 11 is a strange case. Lynn seems to have been very off his game throughout it.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-3a.24" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T12:06:15.896+09:00">Cf. Watson: "And if on top of that the world begins to honor them and cherish them,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-3a.26" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T12:07:16.166+09:00">Cf. Watson: "You say these are only a fancy that will pass in time?"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-4a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T12:12:50.96+09:00">Cf. Watson: "then he will command corpse-like stillness and dragon vision,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.1" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T13:38:43.605+09:00">LYM 100-101: 田成以私量貸公量[another edition reads 公量收, as does LXY in the same connection]，便是借聖人之法以濟其竊國之私，後世王莽之《金滕》、惠卿輩之《周禮》皆挾此術，已被莊叟 一語道破。* 此段引田成事作證，留下面餘地，層層説去，此文字波瀾也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T13:39:00.614+09:00">LYM 101 mistakenly reads 山 for 世.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T13:42:30.204+09:00">LYM 101: 説出「至」字，方見 議論聖人正意，即將上面文法翻跌，有致！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.11" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T13:44:49.041+09:00">LYM 101: 胣，裂也。靡，爛也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-05T13:49:24.573+09:00">LYM 101: 四子有聖知，其爲身之緘縢扃鐍，可謂固矣，乃不足防盜，反以招盜。誠哉，聖知之不足恃也！</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-3a.37" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:20:23.985+09:00">LYM 101: 善人，承上龍逢四子來。但世之爲四子者少，爲跖者多，故利害之數者不敵也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-4a.5" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:22:25.563+09:00">LYM 102: 狠手！殺手！取古人之法而痛詆之，幾於髮指皆裂，吾不知其胸中有何憤懣，竟至於斯！切勿與韓退之見之， 便以常理較量，全不體其立言之意也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-4a.18" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:23:25.101+09:00">LYM 102: 一法立，一弊生。申明田成子一段意。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-5a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:25:33.717+09:00">LYM 102: 引此語見得「民可使由，不可使知」之意。 (JRW: He quotes this adage so one can see the meaning of '民可使由，不可使知'.")</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-5a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:26:49.222+09:00">LYM 102: 言此大盜非賞罰所能勸禁，皆由聖人利而使之，故聖人者，不可以明示天下也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-5a.17" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:28:05.03+09:00">LYM 102-103: 彈殘，盡去也。論議，論道也。此言遏亂盜源，當絶聖棄知也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-5a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:30:19.076+09:00">LYM 103: 鑠絕，焚而棄之也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-5a.30" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:32:46.944+09:00">LYM 103: 攦，折其指也。多着「大巧若拙」 四字，便覺文勢不排。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-5a.34" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:34:12.506+09:00">LYM 103: 仍是上面文法，顛倒出之，此化板爲活法也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-5a.47" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:37:06.345+09:00">LYM 103:爚，火光銷也。法之所無用，言於治天下之法皆用不着也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-6a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:39:59.181+09:00">LYM 103: 自結繩至此，語本《老子》。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.3" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:42:33.784+09:00">LYM 104: 好知，以知謀相尚也。相尚則高下相傾，長短相形，而天下日多事矣。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.27" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:48:36.646+09:00">LYM 104: 惴耍，微息而動之物，蝸牛之屬也。肖翹，輕飛之物，蝶蛾之屬也。此段言乖戾之氣，感召如此，實有此理，其效非誣。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.21" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:50:19.585+09:00">LYM 104: 此又推原天下大亂之由也。天下之所以大亂者，蓋求其所不知以異於人， 而不知求其所已知有本體之自同也；皆知非人之所不能，而不知己之所已能者亦未爲是也。此亂之所由生也。Very nice!</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.14" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:53:07.127+09:00">LYM 104: 頡滑，不正之語。解垢，詭曲之辭。此段備言好知之生亂也。機心生而機事起，機事起而機禍深，鳥魚人獸，其亂一也。 Very nice!</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_010-7a.9" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T11:59:50.229+09:00">LYM 104 on "削格羅落": 削格，木栅也，捕兔鹿者用之。 LYM 104 also glosses 削 as 峭. LYM 104 on "罝罘之知多":  鳥罟謂之羅，兔罟謂之買。罘，翻車也。</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-5a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T12:50:21.513+09:00">Cf. Watson: "then how can you improve men's minds?"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-5a.6" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T12:52:03.886+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Be careful - don't meddle with men's minds!" NB: Watson is often more literate and more accurate, and thus his translation is to be preferred. </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-6a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:01:55.556+09:00">Cf. Watson: "This shows that they could not make the world submit."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-6a.33" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:07:57.97+09:00">NB: WSM could have used this as further support for his contention that ZZ does not categorically advocate withdrawing society, but only hypothetically (given the times are too downtrodden). </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-7a.4" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:10:23.641+09:00">Cf. Watson: "the sufferers of punishment are never out of each other's sight."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-7a.7" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:12:49.561+09:00">Yikes!!!! To act shamefully is precisely to act without a sense of shame. Cf. Watson: "that they should be so brazen, so lacking in any sense of shame!"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-8a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:23:06.685+09:00">NB: Lynn regularly treats GX as though he were recommending translations. GX is telling us what the line means, not what the line says. </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-8a.19" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:24:34.759+09:00">Cf. Watson: "Ever since you began to govern the world,"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-9a.22" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:32:13.823+09:00">Cf. Watson: "enfold the spirit in quietude"</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_011-9a.45" xml:lang="en" resp="#jrwilliams" modified="2022-11-07T13:38:28.784+09:00">Cf. Watson: "and therefore I have kept myself alive for twelve hundred years,"</seg>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>