<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR5c0126-en-ca74cff3" type="transl">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Translation of 莊子 into (en)</title>
            <editor role="translator">TLS Project</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Created by members of the TLS project</p>
            <p>Translation of <bibl corresp="#KR5c0126">
                  <title xml:lang="och">莊子</title>
               </bibl> into <lang xml:lang="en">English</lang>.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>Initially created: <date>2019-12-16T19:07:51.967+09:00</date> by CH</creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Translated parts</head>
            <p xml:id="KR5c0126-start">
               <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_028-13a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="CH" modified="2019-12-16T19:07:53.772+09:00">                                    Now His Majesty </seg>
               <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_028-13a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="CH" modified="2019-12-16T19:07:54.891+09:00">                                    wishes to disregard the laws and break the precedents by granting me an audience.</seg>
            <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_001-1a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2020-08-07T17:04:05.19+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2021-04-07T20:36:41.339+09:00">Different as they are, each has its suitability, - according to their several conditions. (Legge 378) therefore their differentiation is for convenience Graham. it is a matter of the situation from which one is seeing. (Graham 220) Hence, their differences are suitable and in accord with their circumstances. (Mair 155)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.13" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2021-04-07T20:35:31.107+09:00"/>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.14" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2021-04-07T20:56:29.224+09:00">The quintessential and the massive we specify in thingswhich do have shape. (Graham 220)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.16" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2021-04-07T20:57:53.451+09:00">What has no shape at all, numbercannot divide; (G220)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-4a.22" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2021-04-07T20:58:59.03+09:00">As for what words cannot sort or ideas convey, we do not specify anything in it as quintessential or massive.’ (G220)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.12" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2021-04-08T20:49:45.642+09:00">Will man's vom Standpunkt der Relativitaet aus betrachten (Wilhelm 127) Looking at them in their differences from one another (Legge 379) Если цудить исцодя из принятых раличий (Позднеева 216) Observed in the light of gradations (Mair 155)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR5c0126_tls_017-5a.21" xml:lang="en" resp="#CH" modified="2021-04-09T16:33:16.598+09:00">if we grant whatever merit they have (Mair 155) If we consider something worthy because it achieves something (Ziporyn 137) Если судить исходя из заслуг и называть заслуженными тех, у кого признают заслуги...(Posdneeva 216) Considérés sous l'angle del'efficacité, tous les êtres en sont pourvus, si l'on s'attache à mettre en valeur les points où  ils la manifestent; tous les êtres en sont dépourcus, si' l'on s'attache à mettre en relief le terrain où elle leur fait défaut. (J.Lévi 135)</seg>
                </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>