<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="KR6t0288-en-d5377bbf" type="comment">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Comments to 正法眼藏</title>
                <editor role="creator"/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</ab>
                <availability status="3">This work has not been licensed for use in the TLS</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Notes</title>2023</bibl>
                <p>Comments and notes to <bibl corresp="#KR6t0288">
                        <title xml:lang="och">正法眼藏</title>
                    </bibl>for translation <ref target="#KR6t0288-en-sztp"/>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#chris">Initially created: <date>2025-02-11T11:14:01.478+09:00</date> by chris</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Comments</head>
                <p xml:id="KR6t0288-start">
                <seg corresp="#KR6t0288_HZ_13-10.p1.s5" xml:lang="en" resp="#CW" modified="2025-02-13T10:47:17.395+09:00">[@24]: I after I arises, and I after I ceases (ga ga ki, ga ga metsu 我我起、我我滅): A tentative translation of a cryptic passage, literally “I I arise; I I cease.” Depending on how one parses it, the passage could be interpreted to mean, “I arise again and again; I cease again and again,” or “Each I arises, each I ceases.”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR6t0288_HZ_13-10.p2.s3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CW" modified="2025-02-13T10:47:41.632+09:00">[@25]: we should give ourselves over to it and confirm it (kare ni ichinin shite benkō su beshi かれに一任して辦肯すべ し): Again, a tentative translation of an ambiguous remark, variously interpreted; taken here as meaning that we should master the saying.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR6t0288_HZ_13-10.p4.s3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CW" modified="2025-02-13T10:48:14.318+09:00">[@27]: “who’s arising and ceasing?” (ze sui ki metsu 是誰起滅): From Yantou’s 巖頭 response to Luoshan 羅山. See Note 23, above.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR6t0288_HZ_13-10.p5.s7" xml:lang="en" resp="#CW" modified="2025-02-13T10:48:48.774+09:00">[@28]: “those who can attain deliverance through this body” (ō i shi shin toku do sha 應以此身得度者); “manifesting this body” (soku gen shi shin 即現此身); “preaching the dharma for them” (ni i seppō而爲説法): Three phrases based on the Avalokiteśvara chapter of the Lotus Sūtra (Miaofa lianhua jing妙法蓮華經, T.262.9:57a23ff.), in which it said that, to those who can attain deliverance through contact with a particular body (a buddha, a pratyeka- buddha, a śrāvaka, etc.), Bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara appears as that body and preaches the dharma for them. See Supplementary Notes, s.v. “Manifesting a body to preach the dharma.”</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR6t0288_HZ_13-10.p5.s13" xml:lang="en" resp="#CW" modified="2025-02-13T10:49:28.057+09:00">[@29]: “the past mind cannot be got” (kako shin fukatoku 過去心不可得): From the Diamond Sūtra (Jingang jing 金剛 經, T.235.8:751b27). “you’ve gotten my marrow” (nyo toku go zui汝得吾髓); “you’ve gotten my bones” (nyo toku go kotsu汝得吾骨): From Bodhidharma’s comments to his disciples, introduced above, section 7.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#KR6t0288_HZ_13-10.p3.s3" xml:lang="en" resp="#CW" modified="2025-02-13T12:19:01.528+09:00">[@26]: It causes the severance and continuation (danzoku seshimu 斷續せしむ): The agent of this causative predicate is unexpressed; Shōbōgenzō monge 正法眼藏聞解 (SCZ:4:558) understands it as “arising and ceasing” respectively — i.e., “ceasing” severs and “arising” continues the time in which “arising and ceasing don’t stop.” It is also possible to take the agent as the “confirmation” (benkō辦肯) of the previous sentence. On this reading, the quality of our study of the words “don’t stop” determines whether Luoshan’s phrase, “when arising and ceasing don’t stop,” is severed or continues as the “vital artery” (meimyaku 命脈) of the buddhas and ancestors.</seg>
                    </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>