<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="T47n1998A-en-cf4325ce" type="comment">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Comments to </title>
                <editor role="creator"/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <ab>published electronically as part of the TLS project at https://hxwd.org</ab>
                <availability status="3">This work has not been licensed for use in the TLS</availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Created by members of the TLS project</p>
                <p>Comments and notes to <bibl corresp="#T47n1998A">
                        <title xml:lang="och"/>
                    </bibl>for translation <ref target="#T47n1998A-en-c54594ca"/>.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation resp="#chris">Initially created: <date>2025-02-26T21:45:40.902+09:00</date> by chris</creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Comments</head>
                <p xml:id="T47n1998A-start">
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b14.s1" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T21:46:39.183+09:00">1. Vice-Minister Zeng 曾侍郎 (name: Kai 開; style: Tianyou 天游; c. 1054-c. 1114) passed the civil service examinations in 1103 and rose to the position of Vice-Minister of the Board of Rites. He eventually attained awakening under Yuanwu's successor Lingyin Huiyuan 靈隱慧遠 (1103-1176). This letter probably dates from the same time as Dahui's reply, below, the year 1134, when Dahui lived in Fujian.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s1" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T21:46:50.865+09:00">2. Changsha 長沙 was the capital city of what is presently Hunan in southern China.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s2" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T21:46:59.053+09:00">3. Yuanwu Keqin 圜悟克勤 (1063-1135); see Introduction, note 11.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s3" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T21:47:16.449+09:00">4. Although Dahui was ordained at the age of fourteen and subsequently trained under several Chan masters, he was thirty-six years old when he joined the assembly under Yuanwu in 1125. At the time this was considered rather late in life to start under a new teacher.</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s9" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T21:48:49.821+09:00">⁵. "Wise teacher" translates 知識, a term that is more commonly written 善知識 (Skr., *kalyāņa-mitra*) and that I also translate as "awakened teacher" or "wise mentor" depending on the context. Meaning more literally "good friend," a *kalyāņa-mitra* is any person who guides others to the Buddhist teachings and helps them progress in their practice. // ⁶. "This Matter" translates 此事, and has the same meaning as "the One Great Matter" 一大事 or "the One Great Cause" 一大事因緣, the *Lotus Sutra*'s term for the one central purpose that all buddhas come into this world for, that is, to guide sentient beings to the same awakening as the buddhas themselves experienced (T 9:1a).</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s24" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T21:54:49.478+09:00">⁷. These talks are found, in part, in *The Essential Teachings of Chan Master Yuanwu* 圓悟禪師心要(x 69: </seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s26" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T21:56:19.772+09:00">⁸. Yunmen Wenyan 雲門文偃 (864–949); see Introduction, note 18. Yunmen was known for his terse answers, many of which consisted of one word only and came to be known as "Yunmen's one-word barriers." One of these "barriers" is the koan "Yunmen's 'Mount Sumeru': "A monk asked Yunmen Wenyan, 'Is anything amiss when not a singlethought arises?' Yunmen replied, 'Mount Sumeru!'" (In the original Chinese Yunmen'sreply is, in fact, one word.)In Indian cosmology Mount Sumeru is the enormous mountain at the center of eachworld-system in the universe. Various descriptions exist, but Mount Sumeru is commonlysaid to stretch from 84,000 yojana below the surface of the sea to 84,000 yojana above it(a yojana is variously defined as between six and twenty kilometers in length). It is sur-rounded by seven concentric golden mountain ranges, each separated by a sea of freshwater. Beyond these is a saltwater ocean containing the four continents of our world-system: Pūrvavideha to the east of Sumeru, Aparagodānīya to the west, Uttarakuru to thenorth, and Jambudvīpa (the human realm) to the south. Surrounding the entirety are tworanges of iron mountains. This comprises one Sumeru world. (E.g., SGDB: 639)</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s27" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T22:00:09.855+09:00">9. Zhaozhou Congshen 趙州從諗(778-897), one of the greatest of all Chinese Chanmasters, was a Dharma successor of Nanquan Puyuan (see Letter 14, note 4), with whomhe remained for nearly forty years. At the age of sixty he set out on a twenty-year pil-grimage that took him to many of the most eminent Chan masters of that time. Then,at the age of eighty, he became abbot of the temple Guanyin yuan 觀音院 in the city ofZhaozhou. He employed neither the staff nor the shout in his teaching, but relied insteadon his penetrating utterances. Many of his exchanges later became koans, one of which is"Zhaozhou's 'Drop it!': "Yanyang Shanxin 嚴陽善信 (n.d.) asked Zhaozhou, 'If I comewith nothing, what then?' 'Drop it!' replied Zhaozhou. 'But I've come with nothing,'answered Yanyang. 'How can I drop it?' 'Then go on carrying it!' said Zhaozhou. At thisYanyang was deeply awakened."</seg>
                    <seg corresp="#T47n1998A_CBETA_025-0916b1501.s30" xml:lang="en" resp="#chris" modified="2025-02-26T22:00:27.834+09:00">10. "Grandmotherly kindness" translates 老婆心切, a Chan term that means greatkindness, sometimes (though not in this case) with the connotation of excessive kindnessthat ends up doing more harm than good.</seg>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>