<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-3eff002c-3fad-45d2-b6e3-fd6b9d22181c" subtype="PC">
  <head>月蝕</head>
  <div type="definition">lunar eclipse</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="yueshi-61021" n="yueshi月蝕">
      <form>
        <orth>月蝕</orth>
        <pron>Yue shi</pron>
        <usg n="25">[25]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>lunar eclipse</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>Pathological Condition of chuang 瘡， sores developing on the ears, nose, face, and to the side of the orifices in the anal and genital region. Various explanations of this disease may be found in pre-modern medical literature. For example, this disease affects children who were conceived when their parents had intercourse during a lunar eclipse. Other reasons given are: drinking during a lunar eclipse, or a child pointing its finger towards the moon. Still others explain the name as reflecting a parallel between the waxing and waning of the moon, and the development of these ulcers, or between the shape of the ulcers below or behind the ears and the shape of a crescent moon. LSZ suggested that these ulcers develop at the time of the new moon. They abound during the full moon, and they weaken when the moon is waning. As these ulcers develop near the ears of children and are difficult to cure, they may eventually result in gan 疳 , gan-illness . Qian jin bei ji fang 千金備急方 5 ：治小兒月蝕 瘡，隨月生死方：以胡粉和酥敷之，五日瘥 , “Recipe to cure lunar-eclipse sores with surviving and dying in accordance with the [waxing and waning of the] moon: Mix hu fen with butter and smear this [on the sores]. They will be cured within five days”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>