<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-f01caece-502c-405f-9cae-ce502c805f91" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>魏</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-822e8fad-d0bc-4356-a6cc-45cb8233b352" n="5">
            <form corresp="#uuid-c594f343-5936-415e-85a9-957028a67b33">
<orth>魏</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wèi</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋɡuls</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋɨi</pron>
            </form>
            <def>1. Wèi 魏 (also called Liáng 梁)

Clan: According to the Wèi shìjiā chapter of SHI, Wèi Iineage was of the same surname as the Zhōu kings, i.e. Jī 姬.

Rank: In the beginning, the rulers of Wèi were formally of dàfū 大夫 rank, but in 403 B.C. they were raised to the rank of zhūhóu 諸侯 by the Zhōu king. Thereafter, they were usually referred to as hóu 侯. In 344 B.C., the ruler of Wèi adopted the title of wáng 王 (as the first among the rulers of the Warring states period excepts Chǔ).

Founded: The state of Wèi was one of the three states which emerged after the split of Jìn in 453 B.C. In 403 B.C., it was recognized by the Zhōu king.
The Wèi lineage is said to descent from the Duke Gāo of Bì 畢公高, who was an important person in the early Zhōu period. Its descendants entered the service in the state of Jìn, and when Jìn in 660 B.C. conquered the state of Wèi (see section 2 of this entry), it gave it as a fief to its dàfū Bì Wàn 畢萬 who was the real founder of the Wèi lineage. Wèi gradually grew in power in Jìn, and since the beginning of the sixth century BC, it became one of the most powerful lineages in Jìn which in fact usurped real power in the state.  

Destroyed: In 225 BC by Qín 秦.

Location: Wèi basically controlled the area of northeastern Henan and southwestern Shānxī (this two areas were connected by the corridor in central Shānxī. The first capital was Ānyì 安邑 (modern Yúwángcūn 禹王村 in the northwestern part of the Xià district, southwestern Shānxī). In 361 BC, the capital shifted to Dà Liáng 大梁 (modern Kāifēng 開封).

History: In the second half of the fifth and in the first part of the fourth century, Wèi was the strongest state among three Jìn, and in fact the strongest state in China in that period. It was mainly due to the reforms introduced during the reign of marquis Wén 魏文侯 (ca 445-396 B&gt;C&gt;) by Lǐ Kuī 李悝 and Wú Qǐ 吳起. In 344 B.C. ruler Huì 魏惠侯王 (369-319 B.C.) adopted the title of king. However, in the 40ties of the fourth century Wèi suffered serious defeat from Qí and Qín and became a secondary power. In the end of the fourth and in the beginning of the third century, the state was pressed between two superpowers, the states of Qín and Qí. In 225 B.C., Wèi was eventually conquered by Qín.

2. Wèi 魏 (CHEN PAN 1969, 408-410)

Clan: Jī 姬 (according to the ZUO, Xiang 29).

Rank: Unknown.

Founded: Unknown.

Destroyed: In 660 B.C. (Min 2) by Jìn 晉 (according to the ZUO).

Location: In the area of modern Ruìchéng 芮城, southwestern Shānxī province (according to the Hàn zhì, Kuò dì zhì, and to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì).

History: Wèi was a small and unimportant state, which appears in the ZUO for the first time in 708 B.C. (Huan 4). After its conquest by Jìn, the area was given as a fief to Bì Wàn 畢萬, the descendant of the Duke Gāo of Bì 畢公高 (according to the Shǐ jì, Wèi shìjiā). He was the founder of the Wèi 魏 lineage, which gradually obtained great power in the state of Jìn, and in 453 B.C. was one of three lineages which divided that state.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-242a4220-692e-48ea-b439-d9be76c5bd62" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0626d6c5-e14f-49b7-a6d6-c5e14f09b76e" resp="#dsehnal" tls:created="2020-05-10T05:49:33.41+09:00" n="3">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>N</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-af99c48b-0543-4b6e-99c4-8b0543eb6ee9">npr.adN</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>of Wei; belonging to Wei</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
</superEntry>