<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-f90dfdd0-b0d4-4aa8-8dfd-d0b0d4aaa871" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>淨修</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="ZEN MONKS" tls:concept-id="uuid-9c34821d-5c94-4128-96d8-9a46f9471f92" xml:id="uuid-48197a22-69b2-43f4-9677-1998e0b9460b" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-4021cd08-570c-4775-855e-2fc3984096e8 #uuid-ef8eb44d-db8a-4f3b-8eaf-a0dec0116c4a">
<orth>淨修</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">jìng xiū</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhreeŋ sqlɯw</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">dziɛŋ sɨu</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-91cce1db-78cb-4b26-80cc-55ad3d26b0cf">ANDERL 2004B</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zǔtáng jí 祖堂集</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">13-15</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>Wa2ng Ya2nbi1n 王延彬61 built inside the Ka1iyua2n 開元 monastery the Qia1nfo2 千佛 temple (yua4n 院) and invited She3ngde1ng 省人＋登 to reside there as abbot. She3ngde1ng filled this position for a period of approximately ten years before he moved to the Zha1oqi4ng 招慶monastery. Because of his long stay at the Ka1iyua2n monastery he was sometimes referred to as Ba2ilia2n 白蓮 ('White Lotus') or Qia1nfo2 千佛 ('Thousand Buddhas'). Among the Du1nhua2ng manuscripts preserved at the library of London (Stein collection), the eulogy Qua2nzho1u Qia1nfo2 xia1n zhuo2 zhu1 zu3-shi1 so4ng 泉州千佛新著諸祖師頌 (QUANZHOU QIANFO)62 was discovered, a text which She3ngde1ng probably wrote during the time he spent at the Qia1nfo2 monastery.</p>
<p> The Zha1oqi4ng monastery dates back to the mid-Tang period. Wa2ng Ya2nbi1n renovated the monastery and installed Xue3fe1ng's 雪峰 disciple Hui4le2ng 慧棱 (854-932)63 as abbot in 906 A.D.64 Afterwards Hui4le2ng followed the invitation by the King of Mi2n, Wa2ng She3nzhi1 王審知,65  and moved to the Cha2ngqi4ng monastery.  The abbot at this time was Da4o Kua1ng 道匡.66</p>
<p> In 944 A.D.67 She3ngde1ng was invited to move from the Ka1iyua2n monastery to the Zha1oqi4ng monastery and was given the honorary name Mi2ngjue2 明覺. Shortly afterwards the Zha1oqi4ng monastery was destroyed in warfare. Liu2 Co2ngxia4o, the laster ruler of the Southern Tang, donated a section of his estate and erected on it a monastery (Na2ncha2n 南禪 monastery) and installed She3ngde1ng as its abbot.68</p>
<p> He also bestowed the purple robe on him and gave him the appellation Cha2n master Ji4ngxiu1 淨修. At the beginning of the Song period, the ruler of the Southern Tang proclaimed himself subject to the State of Song. She3ngde1ng was also a popular Cha2n master during the early Song and eventually the court of Song gave him the honourary name Cha2n master Zhe1njue2 真覺. She3ngde1ng died in the fifth year of the ka1i-ba3o 開寶 era of the So4ng (972 A.D.). According to the Qua2n-zho1u Ka1iyua2n-si4 zhi4 泉州開元寺志 and the Wa4n li4 cho2ng-xiu1 Qua2n-zho1u fu2 zhi4 萬歷重修泉州府志, the three monks who served as abbots of the Zha1oqi4ng monastery were Hui4le2ng, Da4okua1ng and She3ngde1ng.</p>
<p> It is actually not clear what kind of relationship the two compilers of ZTJ had to She3ngde1ng (We2nde1ng), the author of the preface. According to Yanagida Seizan's opinion the two monks were direct disciples of She3ngde1ng. Yang Zengwen observes that She3ngde1ng refers to the two monks using the honorific term 'Cha2n Worthies' (Cha2n-de2 禪德), a term which is usually not used for one's own disciples. Possibly the two monks were not his direct disciples but rather Cha2n scholars living at the Zha1oqi4ng monastery.69</p>
<p/>
<p>After each biographic entry on the seven Buddhas, the Indian and Chinese patriarchs, the masters Na2nyue4 Hua2ira4ng 南岳懷讓, Ji2zho1u Xi2ngzi1(si1) 吉州行司(思), Hui4zho1ng 惠忠, Shi2to2u Xi1yu4n 石頭希運, and Ma3zu3 Da4oyi1 馬祖道一, there are 'eulogies by Cha2n master Ji4ngxiu1' (Ji4ngxiu1 cha2n-shi1 za4n 淨修禪師贊) added, consisting of eight verses with four graphs each. As mentioned above Ji4ngxiu1 is the honorary appellation of She3ngde1ng. This verses have their origin in the above mentioned QUANZHOU QIANFO. In this work the verses are introduced by a short preface written by a monk called Hui4gua1n 慧觀.70</p>
<p/>
<p>Two of the monks mentioned in QUANZHOU QIANFO, Na2nyue4 Ta4igo1ng 南岳泰公 and Le4pu3 樂浦,71 belong to the lineage of Shi2to2u 石頭. Xia1ngya2n 香岩 is a member of the lineage of Ma3zu3. Na2nyue4 Ta4igo1ng 南岳泰公 refers to Na2nyue4 Xua2nta4i 南嶽玄泰.72 He was the author of several gaathaas, songs, etc., for example the She1-sha1n ya2o 畬山謠 ('Ballad of Mt. She1') and some verses recorded in ZTJ.</p>
<p> Le4pu3 alias Luo4pu3 落浦 (834-898)73 was a disciple of Jia2sha1n 夾山.74 In ZTJ several poems are recorded, for example the She2n jia4n ge1 神劍歌75 ('Song about the Divine Sword'), and the Fu2-o4u ge1 浮漚歌76 ('Song on the Impermanence of Human Life').</p>
<p> Xia1ngya2n 香岩 (香嚴; ?-898)77 was a disciple of Gui1sha1n Li2ngyo4u 溈山靈祐 and also the author of a number of gaathaas. </p>
<p> All the above mentioned monks were known for their poetic expressions and She3ngde1ng's verses were probably influenced by the literary works of these people. The compilers of ZTJ attached the gaathaas recorded in QUANZHOU QIANFO  after the biographic entries on the respective patriarchs and were also added to the biographies of a few masters.78</p>
<p> Besides the above mentioned gaathaas, the JDCDL in addition mentions She3ngde1ng as author of the following poems: Shi4-zhi2 zuo4-cha2n zhe3 示執坐禪者; Shi4 zuo4-cha2n fa1ng-bia4n 示坐禪方便.79</p>
<p> The Cha2n school was very concerned with the patriarchical lineage system and during the Late Tang/Five Dynasties periods the dharma lineages of Xue3fe1ng were flourishing in Fu2, Qua2n and Zha1ng provinces. Xue3fe1ng himself belongs to the lineage of Shi2to2u Xi1yu4n 石頭希遷, a lineage which was not very much in focus prior to the composition of ZTJ. This was probably the reason why the authors of ZTJ first record the biographies of 96 members of Shi2to2u's lineage and only afterwards give an acount of the lineage of the famous Jia1ngxi1 Ma3zu3 江西馬祖.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-41f74f72-80b6-4f4e-a3b2-d2bee512dfcf">ISHII 1986</ref>
<title>泉州福先招慶院の淨修禪師省僜と《祖堂集》 Zenshū Fukusaki Shokei-in no Joshū zenji Shoto to Sodōshū [Chán Master Jìngxiū Shěngdēng of the Zhāoqìng Monastery of Quánzhōu and the Zǔtáng jí 駒澤大學佛教學部研究紀要 Komazawa Daigaku Bukkyōgaku kenkyū kiyō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">169</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>See QUANZHOU FUZHI</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-8d17a8f3-d898-45e5-a63a-896350e61c19">JINGDECHUANDENGLU</ref>
<title>景德傳燈錄 Jǐngdé chuándēng lù The Record of the Transmission of the Lamp Published in the Jǐngdé Era Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">382a20-b27</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-00dc9032-bf12-4268-9ff8-0c3d728c9226">QUANZHOU FUZHI</ref>
<title>泉州府志 Quánzhōu fǔzhì</title>
                        <note>
<p>釋省人＋登，仙遊人，姓院氏。出家泉之開元。去遊吳楚，遍叩宗匠。已而往漳見保福展。因人殿次，展指佛問曰：“佛恁麼意作麼生？”師曰：“和尚也是橫身。”展曰：“一橛我自收取。”師曰：“和尚非惟橫身。”展然之。遂為其嗣。梁天成間，刺史王延彬，造千佛院，致師住持。十餘年，足不踰臬。普開運初，黃紹頗守郡，遷主招慶。閩侯文進。秦昇明覺師號。未幾州亂，招慶火于兵。留從效建節清源寺。其別墅名南禪，歸招慶業，延師為第一世法徒景附，成大法席。宋興徐相為藩表開。太祖嘉之。賜真覺師號。開寶五年，遷化，塔號瑞光。</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-f1a703bf-a64c-4101-bb32-4635e7d48c3f">YANG ZENGWEN 1999</ref>
<title>唐五代禪宗史 Táng Wǔdài Chánzōng shǐ A History of the Chán School of the Tang and Five Dynasties Periods</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">596</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
            <def>Jìngxiū
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-dbb720ab-5fc1-4894-973f-cb0484181568" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: an appellation (canonical name) of Preceptor Shěngdēng 省人＋登 or Wéndēng 文人＋登 (?-972), a Zen master in the lineage of Xuěfēng Yìcún (Xuefeng Yicun) 雪峰義存 (822-908), and the teacher of the compilers of ZTJ. At the time of the composition of ZTJ he was the abbot of the Zhāoqìng 招慶 monastery. He After having studied the vinaya, he engaged in Zen studies and eventually became a successor of Bǎofú Cóngzhǎn 寶福從展 (867-928)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>