<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-08008509-595e-41f2-be96-674d06854776" subtype="IS">
  <head>舌出</head>
  <div type="definition">tongue protrusion</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="shechu-54278" n="shechu舌出">
      <form>
        <orth>舌出</orth>
        <pron>She chu</pron>
        <usg n="8">[8]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>tongue protrusion</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>Illness Sign of a tongue that is stretched out of the mouth and cannot be retracted. Qian jin bei ji fang 千金備急方 10: 故督郵顧子獻得病已瘥未健，請華佗視脈。曰：雖瘥尚虛未得復， 陽氣不足，慎勿勞事。余勞尚可，女勞則死，當吐舌數寸。其婦聞其夫 瘥，從百餘里來省之，經宿交接，中間三日發熱口噤，臨死舌出數寸。 病新瘥未滿百日，氣力未平復，而犯房室略無不死 , “Former local inspector Gu Zixian had been cured of a disease but he did not feel healthy. He asked Hua Tuo to examine [the movements in] his vessels. [Hua Tuo] told him: Although you have been cured, there is still a depletion that has not been restored to normal yet. Your yang qi is insufficient. You must be careful not to exhaust yourself. While other types of exhaustion may be possible, exhaustion [through intercourse] with women will kill you. Your tongue will protrude several cun . When his wife learned that her husband had been cured, she came from a hundred miles away to have intercourse with him. They met for an entire night. Three days later he effused heat and developed a clenched jaw. Close to his death his tongue protruded several cun . If a disease has not been cured for one hundred days, and if [aperson’s] strength has not been restored to normal, and if contrary to a warning one enters the bedroom [for intercourse], there is hardly a chance he will not die”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>