<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-1d5da216-20a1-46da-a8bb-f03ce95479b8" subtype="AN">
  <head>無辜</head>
  <div type="definition">; [lit: “innocent”]</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="wugu-65725" n="wugu無辜">
      <form>
        <orth>無辜</orth>
        <pron>Wu gu wu gu</pron>
        <usg n="lit: “innocent”">[11]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>; [lit: “innocent”]</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>Alternative Names wu gu gan 無辜疳 , wu gu with gan-illness. Pathological Condition of gan 疳 , gan- illness, accompanied by scrofula affecting the head and neck. This is often associated with emaciation of the body, desiccation of the hair, with the head and neck affected by nodes that are glossy and pliable in their early stages and fester and bleed incessantly at a later stage. Authors in pre-modern literature have traced this disease to children’s clothing left to dry under a clear sky overnight. When a bird crying ‘ wugu , wugu ’ flew over these garments and a child was given them to wear the next day, it would develop this disease. Beginning with the Song era, this explanation lost its appeal. Zhu bing yuan hou lun 諸病源候論 48 ：小 兒面黃髮直，時壯熱，飲食不生肌膚，積經日月，遂致死者，謂之無辜 , “Now, when children have a yellow facial complexion, when their hair stands up straight, when they repeatedly develop strong heat, when beverages and food fail to generate muscles and flesh, and if this continues for days and months, and eventually ends in death, then this is called wu gu ”.</def>
      </sense>
      <pb n="537"/>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>