<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-a40ad5fb-87d3-4936-8ad5-fb87d3a9363d" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>虢</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-eac5874f-7d9f-4c74-b0cb-be81f8ad8fb9" n="4">
            <form corresp="#uuid-65c6750a-7699-4de6-8753-ffc5ad4175c2">
<orth>虢</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">guó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">kʷraaɡ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">kɣɛk</pron>
            </form>
            <def>1. Xī Guó 西虢 (written also as 郭) (CHEN PAN 1969, 341-349)

Clan: Jī姬.

Rank: Gōng 公 (occurs both in the CQ and ZUO).

Founded: There are uncertainties concerning the founder of Xī Guó, what is particularly due to the fact that there were at least two states bearing the name Guó. Their rulers belonged to the same lineage (the different branches of which were obviously dispersed throughout the Zhōu realm, from the Shǎnxī province to the eastern part of Central Henan), and there is a general consensus that both were the sons of the Zhōu pre-dynastic king Wáng Jì 王季, and younger brothers of his successor King Wén 周文王 (what is attested by the record in the ZUO, Xi 5; 655 B.C.). The record in the ZUO mentions two sons of Wáng Jì 王季 - Guózhòng 虢仲 and Guóshū 虢叔 - as founders of the both states of Guó. However, there is a disagreement among scholars which one was the founder of the Eastern Guó and which one of the Western Guó.

Destroyed: In 655 B.C. (Xi5) by Jìn 晉.

Location: The former state of Xī Guó was located in the West (probably in the area of the modern Bǎojī 寶雞 district; according to another opinion, it was in the modern Shǎn 陝 district). According to the Shuǐ jīng zhù, the state shifted to the East during the reign of King Píng of Zhōu 周平 (770-720 B.C.); on the other hand, Current Zhúshū jǐnián dates the shift into the reign of his predecessor King Yōu of Zhōu 周幽王 (781-771 B.C.). Shàngyáng 上陽, the new capital of Xī Guó, was obviously located in the area of the modern Sānménxiá 三門峽, Henan province, where the remarkable cemetery belonging to the aristocracy of Guó was excavated.
This Xī Guó was sometimes also referred to as Běi Guó 北虢. The part of the Guó lineage remained in the area of Shǎnxī province, and was referred to as Xiǎo Guó 小虢. Xiǎo Guó was (according to the Qín běnjì chapter of the Shǐ jì) conquered by Qín 秦 in 687 B.C. (in the eleventh year of the reign of Duke Wǔ of Qín 秦武公).
There was also Nán Guó 南虢 (probably in the southern part of the modern Pínglù 平陸, Shānxī province), which belonged to the another branch of the Guó lineage. It should be noted that the names for the states ruled by the different branches of the Guó lineage are quite confused in the texts.

History: Although Guó was a small state, it was located within royal domains both during the Western Zhōu and Eastern Zhōu periods, and the dukes of Guó usually held high positions in the Zhōu royal court, being mainly charged with the leadership of important royal military enterprises. However, since the 70ties of the 7th century B.C., Guó was exposed to the pressure from the side of the powerful state of Jìn (seeking to win a control over crossings over the Yellow river) and was eventually subdued in 655 B.C. The story about the downfall of Guó, and the role played in it by its neighbor, the state of Yú 虞, became quite famous in Chinese tradition. Guó is also remarkable for the large cemetery in Shàngcūnlǐng 上村嶺, mentioned above, which yielded a lot of data concerning the development of the bronzes in the Early Chunqiu period.  


2. Dōng Guó 東虢 (CHEN PAN 1969, 311-317)

Clan: Jī 姬.

Rank: Uncertain. In the Current Zhúshū jìnián (in the record for the third year of King Lì of Zhōu 周厲王), the ruler of Guó (presumably this Dōng Guó) is referred to as gōng 公. The same designation is used in the Shuǐ jīng zhù, where it clearly refers to the rulers of Dōng Guó.

Founded: There are uncertainties concerning the founder of Dōng Guó, what is particularly due to the fact that there were at least two states bearing the name Guó. Their rulers belonged to the same lineage (the different branches of which were obviously dispersed throughout the Zhōu realm, from the Shǎnxī province to the eastern part of Central Henan), and there is a general consensus that both were the sons of the Zhōu pre-dynastic king Wáng Jì 王季 and younger brothers of his successor King Wén 周文王 (what is attested by the record in the ZUO, Xi 5; 655 B.C.). The record in the ZUO mentions two sons of Wáng Jì 王季 - Guózhòng 虢仲 and Guóshū 虢叔 - as the founders of both states of Guó. Among scholars, there is a disagreement which one of those two founded Eastern Guó and which one Western Guó.

Destroyed: Dōng Guó was conquered by Zhèng 鄭 in the beginning of the Eastern Zhōu period, most probably during the reign of Duke Wǔ of Zhèng 鄭武公 (770-744 B.C.).

Location: In the northern part of the modern Zhèngzhōu 鄭州 area, Henan province.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-81354737-df69-422c-b39b-4bd2551c6c36" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Name of an archeologically very important state, destroyed in 656 BC.</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>