<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-a2862d66-3829-440a-862d-663829040af1" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>真如</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="FEATURE" tls:concept-id="uuid-f4929979-c290-4ace-9f53-0e91c298690a" xml:id="uuid-ac67ba5f-6ea5-4878-87bb-267e4fa1cdc8" n="4">
            <form corresp="#uuid-d4d66e15-3f6d-47b1-adf9-2fee6a70c68e #uuid-b70766fd-8fa3-4174-9134-d39d5f504d70">
<orth>真如</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhēn rú</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">tjin nja</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">tɕin ȵi̯ɤ</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-498d85c4-d730-4ae0-bcd2-e2f3a58da628">ANDERL 2004C</ref>
<title>Studies in the Language of Zu-tang Ji 祖堂集</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">626, fn. 1863</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>zhe1nru2 真如: skr. bhuua-tathataa; tathataa; 'Suchness; all pervading truth'; often used a syn. or near-syn. to terms like ru2ru2 如如, ru2shi2 如實; fa3jie4 法界; fa3xi4ng 法性; shi2ji4 實際, shi2xia1ng 實相; ru2-a2iza1ng 如來臧, fa3she1n 法身, fo2xi4ng 佛性, zi4xi4ng qi1ngji4ng she1n 自性清淨身, yi1xi1n 一心, etc. In early translations often tr. with be3nwu2 本無. Zhe1nru2 is one of the fundamental concepts in Mahaayaana Buddhism, referring to the true nature of all things (wa4n yo3u zhi1 be3nti3 萬有之本體). The term is interpreted in different ways depending on in which scripture and by which school it is used. It often refers to the 'real' nature of things, which is beyond differentation and unchangable, cannot be imagined nor expressed. In China the term and its meaning was vividly discussed and in the sixth century Di4lu4n 地論 school zhe1n-ru2 was associated with the 8th concsiousness, the a1la4iye2 shi2 阿賴耶識 which was considered to be perfectly pure. However, for the Cha2n school the usage of the term in the QIXINLUN was most influential where it is explained as the essense of the mind of sentient beings. For a thorough explanation of the term see in Foguang: 4197a-4199b. In ZTJ zhe1nru2  appears 15 times, ru2ru2 如如 seventeen times: ‘凡聖情盡，體露真性常住。事用不二，即是如如佛。’(then common and holy sentiments are exhausted, then the essence is exposed and the true nature resides permanently. Phenomena and function are the same, that is the Buddha of Suchness.' ZTJ 5.072; WU: 409);</p>
<p>狸奴白牯卻知有。’何以如此？他卻無如許多般情量，所以喚作如如。 ('Patriarchs and Buddhas do not have any knowledge, but leopards and wild cows (buffalos) on the contrary do have.' Why is that so? They do not have any kind of discriminating thinking therefore they are called '[being in a state of] Suchness'; ZTJ 4.107,02; WU: 351).</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-d0734b75-6182-4796-96ac-bf283d4df4a2">AVATAMSAKA(A)</ref>
<title>大方廣佛華嚴經 Dà fāngguǎng Fó huāyán jīng Avataṃsaka sūtra Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">426c</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-2389c812-8053-4187-8f7a-19f6e856050f">FOGUANG</ref>
<title>佛光大辭典 Fóguāng dàcídiǎn The Foguang Dictionary of Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">4197a-4199b</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-e724bbf3-e475-4757-ae1c-b3e91bcf79bd">HAKEDA 1967</ref>
<title>The Awakening of Faith -  Attributed to Asvaghosha</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">23-24</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"'Suchness' is a synonym of the Absolute, 真如 zhenru [...], which may be translated literally as 'Real Suchness', 'True Suchness', 'the state that is really so', etc.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-042f1088-8ef5-4e1e-be35-1d8ff1785655">LANKA(A)</ref>
<title>楞伽阿跋多羅寶經 Léngqié ābáduōluó bǎo jīng Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">511a</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-be7d5897-5698-4129-9d0a-5908fdc44d57">NAKAMURA</ref>
<title>佛教語大辭典 Bukkyōgo daijiten Encyclopedic Dictionary of Buddhist Terms</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">785d, 1063a</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-d7f58d33-a761-4df2-8817-ecdded9fa689">QIXINLUN(A)</ref>
<title>大乘起信論 Dàshèng qǐxīn lùn Treatise on the Awakening of Faith in the Mahāyāna Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">580a, 581a</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-de72bd03-d709-459a-a9ea-9ba8c75643a6">SUZUKI 1973</ref>
<title>The Lankavatara Sutra</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">405</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>'thusness', 'suchness'</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-e7f906d1-28bd-4380-ba49-56327a023e17" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-db0698e7-db2f-4ee3-9a20-0c2b2e0cebf0">NPab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-887fdec5-f18d-4faf-8602-f5c5c2f99a1d">metaphysical</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: Thusness, the way things really are, the true state of things. Truly-So (sometimes concretely referring to dependent co-arising 緣起) (see also zhēnrú 如如); SANSKRIT tathā, tathatā</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>