<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-ae75b266-8eca-4d6b-b5b2-668eca4d6ba7" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>邾</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-b3440883-9bec-4ae3-8339-b8dbfd938758" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-6138cebe-22d3-4bab-babb-202d3f0b13ef">
<orth>邾</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhū</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">to</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈi̯o</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Zhū 邾 (also called Zhūlóu 邾婁; changed its name to Zōu 鄒 in the Zhanguo period) (CHEN PAN 1969, 262-270)

Clan: Cáo 曹. Recorded in the ZUO, Guó yǔ (Zhèngyǔ), and Shì běn.

Rank: Zǐ 子 (used in the both CQ and ZUO). In the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts, rulers of Zhū refer to themselves as gōng 公 or bó 伯.

Founded: According to the tradition recorded in the Shǐ jì (Chǔ shìjiā), the Cáo clan belonged to the descendants of the mythical ruler Zhuānxú 顓頊. The inscription on the Zhū gōng zhōng 邾公鐘 mentions as an ancestor of the rulers of Zhū Lùzhōng 陸終, who is in the Shǐ jì mentioned as one of the descendants of Zhuānxú in the list of predecessors of the Zhū rulers. It is in accordance with the Wéi's commentary to the Guó yǔ (Zhèng yǔ). According to the Tōng diǎn, Xié 挾, the ruler of Zhū received his fief from King Wǔ of Zhōu 周武王, but the basis for this statement is unknown. 

Destroyed: The date of the destruction of Zhū (Zōu) and the state which conquered it are unknown. By the end of the period recorded in CQ, the state was still in existence. Later, it changed its name to Zōu 鄒, and still existed by the time of Mencius. According to the Zhànguó cè (Xī Zhōu cè), Zōu was later conquered by Qí 齊; according to the Bao's commentary to the Zhànguó cè, Zhū was destroyed by Chǔ 楚.

Location: The first capital of Zhū was called Zhū 邾, and it was probably located to the southeast of the modern Qūfù 曲阜, Shandong province. In 614 B.C. (Wen 14), the capital of the state was shifted by Duke Wén 邾文公 to Yì 譯, which, according to the Du's commentary, was located in the modern Zōu 鄒 district, Shandong province.
According to the Chén Qǐ shìjiā zhēng yì, the capital of Zhū shifted more times: from the earliest Zhūchéng 邾城 (which is by the commentary located to the modern Huángāng 黃岡, Hubei province; however, it is probable that in the Chunqiu period there was another state of the same name, located in that area) to Qí 蘄 (supposedly in the modern Xúzhōu 徐州, Anhui province), and later to the modern Téng 滕 district, Shandong province. Eventually, the capital of Zhū was established in Zōu 鄒 (the modern Zōu 鄒 district, Shandong province). However, it is not known on what is this description based. 

History: Zhū was a small, but not completely unimportant old state, which was generally conceived by other states (at least by Lǔ 魯) as barbarian, belonging to the Eastern barbarians  (Dōng Yí 東夷). Some of its customs are criticized in the ZUO: for instance sacrificing of the captured ruler of the small state of Zēng by Zhū in 641 B.C. (Xi 19). Particularly since the 20ties of the 6th century, Zhū was repeatedly invaded by its powerful neighbor, the state of Qí 齊, and gradually became its dependant state. Later, Zōu became famous as the place of Mencius' origin.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4b68ee72-8ab6-4266-ad0a-a503ec132a33" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>State of Zhu1</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>