<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-ac1394bc-2ace-4bc1-9394-bc2ace6bc17d" n="3">
    <form>
        <orth>羅</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="NET" tls:concept-id="uuid-bfa67505-49aa-4a49-8614-3b1e80fa8b5f" xml:id="uuid-39d6da6c-e996-49c0-8ee4-111e27763aa6" n="4">
            <form corresp="#uuid-73b6e4e2-147a-4ead-8d0b-386283e2a333">
<orth>羅</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">luó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">b-raal</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">lɑ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Luó 羅 , wǎng 罔／網, bì 畢, fú 罘, and jū 罝 (small) are current words for bird nets which can also be used to catch small animals like hares. [Bì 畢 was probably of Y-like shape, and consisted of small net and long handle (HUANG 1995: 447 - 448). The word wǎng 罔／網 is probably only archaic variant of wǎng 网 [WANG 1993: 238]. In SHIJING, the word is used also for a fish net (XIANG 1997: 665). Fú 罘 can be also used to catch large animals like deers. [HUANG 1995: 448]
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-4746d0de-d7ca-4fb9-ab3f-0a235e966710" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>net for catching birds</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-26cbedf0-9b6d-4afc-ae80-f9af48c87e1a">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-f55cff2f-f0e3-4f08-a89c-5d08fcf3fe89">act</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>use bird nets for hunting</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="SILK" tls:concept-id="uuid-03c4dc56-8dd0-4fd6-adfa-d5d97f87be83" xml:id="uuid-31378a9c-c7d2-46f0-af05-ddc8a6a61c31" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-73b6e4e2-147a-4ead-8d0b-386283e2a333">
<orth>羅</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">luó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">b-raal</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">lɑ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-abcd0725-2b94-4a3e-897a-77c9ac7218b8">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-e917a78b-5500-4276-a5fe-156b8bdecb7b">nm</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>gauze; thin silk</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-a4204681-ce10-4d4e-965f-2f7f7c18ae51">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a51b30e7-dffc-4a3d-b4f7-2dccf9eee4a9">nmadN</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>made of thin gauze</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-856f85c7-baa3-4b1b-8868-23a5c48ff3d4" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-73b6e4e2-147a-4ead-8d0b-386283e2a333">
<orth>羅</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">luó</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">b-raal</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">lɑ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Luó 羅 (CHEN PAN 1969, 487-490)

Clan: Probably Xióng 熊 (according to the Shì běn, Du's commentary, and to the Tōng zhì). According to the Xìng xī, the rulers of Luó belonged to the Yún 妘 clan.

Rank: Unknown. According to the Shuǐ jīng zhù and Xìng xī, the rulers of Luó were of hóu 侯 rank. According to the Hàn zhì and Tōng diǎn, they had zǐ 子 rank.

Founded: Unknown. According to the Shì běn, the rulers of Luó were of the Chǔ 楚 clan Xióng 熊.

Destroyed: After 699 B.C. (Huan 13), Luó does not appear in the CQ and ZUO. In 635 B.C. (Xi 25), the area already belonged to Chǔ 楚.

Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, to the Shuǐ jīng Jiāng shuǐ zhù, and to the Tōng zhì Shìzú kǎolyè, Luó was located in the modern Yíchéng 宜城 district in the northern part of Hubei. According to the same sources, it later shifted to Zhījiāng 枝江. After its defeat by Chǔ, King Wén of Chǔ 楚文王 (689-677 B.C.) is said to shift it to the area of the modern Luó district in the neighborhood of Chángshā 長沙, Hunan province (what is stated in the Hàn zhì and Shuǐ jīng zhù). However, I found this statement late and rather problematic, because it is by no means certain that in that early period Chǔ had a control over this remote area. But probably by the end of the Warring states period, Luó was located in the area of Chángshā, as is mentioned in the Tōng zhì.

History: Luó was a small and unimportant state, which is remarkable only for its victory over the invading Chǔ army in 699 B.C. (Huan 13).
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-02d7d392-b9ea-49f8-b385-b26f739a1519">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Luó 羅 (CHEN PAN 1969, 487-490)Clan: Probably Xióng 熊 (according to the Shì běn, Du's commentary, and to the Tōng zhì). According to the Xìng xī, the rulers of Luó belonged to the Yún 妘 clan. Rank: Unknown. According to the Shuǐ jīng zhù and Xìng xī, the rulers of Luó were of hóu 侯 rank. According to the Hàn zhì and Tōng diǎn, they had zǐ 子 rank.Founded: Unknown. According to the Shì běn, the rulers of Luó were of the Chǔ 楚 clan Xióng 熊. Destroyed: After 699 B.C. (Huan 13), Luó does not appear in the CQ and ZUO. In 635 B.C. (Xi 25), the area already belonged to Chǔ 楚.Location: According to the Du's commentary to the ZUO, to the Shuǐ jīng Jiāng shuǐ zhù, and to the Tōng zhì Shìzú kǎolyè, Luó was located in the modern Yíchéng 宜城 district in the northern part of Hubei. According to the same sources, it later shifted to Zhījiāng 枝江. After its defeat by Chǔ, King Wén of Chǔ 楚文王 (689-677 B.C.) is said to shift it to the area of the modern Luó district in the neighborhood of Chángshā 長沙, Hunan province (what is stated in the Hàn zhì and Shuǐ jīng zhù). However, I found this statement late and rather problematic, because it is by no means certain that in that early period Chǔ had a control over this remote area. But probably by the end of the Warring states period, Luó was located in the area of Chángshā, as is mentioned in the Tōng zhì. History: Luó was a small and unimportant state, which is remarkable only for its victory over the invading Chǔ army in 699 B.C. (Huan 13).</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>