<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-1b753297-94e2-4832-b532-9794e2d8327d" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>鄖</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-bacf73f7-4e1c-45a8-b482-ef4687bcfff5" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-45bd18dc-a2ff-4393-bdd7-b0ad946c95e1">
<orth>鄖</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">yún</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ɢun</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɦi̯un</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Yún 鄖 (also written as 云, 雲, 伝, 妘, 溳, 運, 員) (CHEN PAN 1969, 469-476)

Clan: Uncertain. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì and to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, the rulers of Yún belonged to the Yún 妘 clan. According to the Shì zú pǔ, they were of Yíng 嬴 surname.

Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the ZUO, Xuān 4).

Founded: Unknown.

Destroyed: Unknown. In 584 B.C. (Cheng 7), the area of Yún already belonged to Chǔ 楚.

Location: Uncertain. Several possible locations of the state were suggested by the traditional Chinese historiography. According to the Ménghuì tú, to the Shuǐ jīng Yúnshuǐ zhù, to the Yuánhé zhì, to the Tōng diǎn, and to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, Yún was located in the modern Ānlù 安陸 district, Hubei province. On the other hand, Hàn zhì, Dìlì zhì, and Yītǒng zhì suggested its location in the modern Yún 溳 district in the same province. Commentary to the Hàn zhì and commentary to the Xù Hàn shū Jūn guó zhì located it into the modern Jīngshān 京山 district, Hubei province. In any case, the state of Yún was located somewhere in the northern part of Hubei.
It should be noted that there were more places of that name also in the Henan area (one in the state of Wèi 衛). The place name Yún already appears in the oracle bone inscriptions together with Hé 河 and Diàn 奠 (Zhèng 鄭), what suggests that it was located somewhere in the eastern part of the central Henan. Whether there was any relationship between those place-names and the state of Yún is not known.  

History: Yún participated in the coalition of the small states located in the area of the northern Hubei and southern Henan, which was in 701 B.C. (Huan 11) badly defeated by Chǔ 楚. Maybe rather quaint is the fact that Zǐwén 子文, the famous Chǔ minister (lìngyǐn 令尹) of the 7th century B.C., was born of an illegal relationship of the Chǔ minister Dòu Bóbǐ 鬥伯比 with a daughter of the ruler of Yún (see ZUO, Xuan 4).
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-f7a7f4fd-7766-487f-92f2-38cdeeade20b">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Yún 鄖 (also written as 云, 雲, 伝, 妘, 溳, 運, 員 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 469-476)Clan: Uncertain. According to the Lù shǐ Hòu jì and to the Lù shǐ Guó míng jì, the rulers of Yún belonged to the Yún 妘 clan. According to the Shì zú pǔ, they were of Yíng 嬴 surname. Rank: Zǐ 子 (according to the ZUO, Xuān 4). Founded: Unknown.Destroyed: Unknown. In 584 B.C. (Cheng 7), the area of Yún already belonged to Chǔ 楚. Location: Uncertain. Several possible locations of the state were suggested by the traditional Chinese historiography. According to the Ménghuì tú, to the Shuǐ jīng Yúnshuǐ zhù, to the Yuánhé zhì, to the Tōng diǎn, and to the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, Yún was located in the modern Ānlù 安陸 district, Hubei province. On the other hand, Hàn zhì, Dìlì zhì, and Yītǒng zhì suggested its location in the modern Yún 溳 district in the same province. Commentary to the Hàn zhì and commentary to the Xù Hàn shū Jūn guó zhì located it into the modern Jīngshān 京山 district, Hubei province. In any case, the state of Yún was located somewhere in the northern part of Hubei.It should be noted that there were more places of that name also in the Henan area (one in the state of Wèi 衛 ). The place name Yún already appears in the oracle bone inscriptions together with Hé 河 and Diàn 奠 (Zhèng 鄭 ), what suggests that it was located somewhere in the eastern part of the central Henan. Whether there was any relationship between those place-names and the state of Yún is not known. History: Yún participated in the coalition of the small states located in the area of the northern Hubei and southern Henan, which was in 701 B.C. (Huan 11) badly defeated by Chǔ 楚. Maybe rather quaint is the fact that Zǐwén 子文, the famous Chǔ minister (lìngyǐn 令尹 ) of the 7th century B.C., was born of an illegal relationship of the Chǔ minister Dòu Bóbǐ 鬥伯比 with a daughter of the ruler of Yún (see ZUO, Xuan 4). </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>