<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-cc361c0a-c33a-47ae-b61c-0ac33ad7ae7a" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>楚文王</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="RULERS OF CHU" tls:concept-id="uuid-6461352c-c806-402a-a524-4929879d25a3" xml:id="uuid-e8fda2b7-06f1-4441-a0ec-9a6504dfd10f" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-850113bb-f039-441a-8638-9b5a54e01112 #uuid-9bad1e6b-8012-44fa-9361-adf5aa491542 #uuid-3b611bc0-1264-4fb0-b354-69ff386f2094">
<orth>楚文王</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">chǔ wén wáng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">skhraʔ mɯn ɢʷaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʈʂhi̯ɤ mi̯un ɦi̯ɐŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-69225b84-dbaf-4401-9210-359c7a5dbb33">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e377e0e-02e8-437f-86ce-f041186bc7aa">human</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def resp="#CH" updated="2020-04-18T00:15:08.057+09:00">Chŭ Wén Wáng 楚文王 (r. 689 – 675) was the son of King Wu of Chu 楚武王 and it was under his reign that the capital of Chu was moved to Ying 郢. He is also known his use of the 板築法 method of fortification. He managed to greatly expand the territory controlled by the state of Chu. In 684 he invaded the state of Cai 蔡 and captured the Duke of Qi who recommended to him Xi Gui 息妫 as the most beautiful woman in the world. King Wen promptly attacked the state of Xi, captured Xi Gui, married her. He did have to sons by her. King Wen was the third king to whom &gt;Mr He 和氏 presented his famous jade, and he was the one who accepted the offer. On the occasion he is said to have issued a law: “盗所隐器，与盗同罪。”. SY 14.16 reports on King Wen’s campaign against Deng 鄧 in 678, in which he employed two of his sons. In 675 he died having contracted an illness. He had suffered a series of disappointing military campaigns and died outside his country. His loyal aide, Yu Quan 鬻拳, committed loyal suicide to follow his master into his grave. HNZ 9 reports that King Wen liked to sport fancy hats 獬冠. SY 1.34 reports a conversation on his sickbed. [ZUO Zhuang 6, 10, Xi 7; SY 15.3]　Father of &gt;Chǔ Chéng wáng 楚成王</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>