<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-c520f7e0-e3cd-4b9e-a0f7-e0e3cd4b9e2e" n="2">
    <form>
        <orth>吳</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="SHOUT" tls:concept-id="uuid-43301ee0-76a6-4734-a758-7be4ded906f5" xml:id="uuid-606dfdf0-4e3a-4c0b-8103-50c961b95da0" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-c7266f09-7684-46c4-ad10-fe2d2f463700">
<orth>吳</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wú</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋʷaa</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋuo̝</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d062cb31-a7a1-408a-8d49-f982721aaef7">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-f55cff2f-f0e3-4f08-a89c-5d08fcf3fe89">act</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>rare, archaic, SHU: shout</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-aefd7669-3adb-44d2-949e-aba1fe08d181" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-c7266f09-7684-46c4-ad10-fe2d2f463700">
<orth>吳</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wú</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋʷaa</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋuo̝</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Wú 吳 (also called Yú 虞, Gān 干, Jù Wú 句吳, or Yú Gān 禺干) (CHEN PAN 1969, 143-153) 

Clan: According to tradition ruled by the Jī 姬 clan. (However, this matter is not uncontroversial, since the state of Wú is supposed to have been established even before the fall of the Shāng, and since there was intermarriage between the Wú and Lǔ ruling clans, these cannot very plausibly both have been Jī clans, althouth there is evidence that intermarriage taboos were occasionally set aside for political reasons.)

Rank: According to the Zhōu hierarchy, the rulers of Wú were of Zǐ 子 rank (and they are ussually referred to by this title in CQ). However, they themselves declared themselves to be kings (wáng 王), as was also the case of some of the other non-Zhōu states. This title appears in ZUO and in the bronze inscriptions.

Founded: According to the tradition (maybe fabricated by the Wú rulers and recorded already in ZUO and MENG, but mainly in SHI), the founder of the state was &gt;Tàibó 太伯, the son of the Zhou pre-conquest king &gt;Tàiwáng 周太王. This person is said to leave Zhōu even prior to the conquest of Shāng and to establish the state of Wú far in the southeast. However, this tradition is very suspicious.

Destroyed: In 473 B.C. (Ai 22) by the state of &gt;Yuè 越.

Location: Located in modern Jiangsu Province, renowned for its many lakes, marshes and waterways. Like their arch-enemies, the people of Yuè 越 , the people of Wú were light-heartedly regarded as "amphibious" creatures.
According to the traditional Chinese historigraphy, the first capital was at Méilǐ 梅里 (located by Kuò dì zhì and Chūnqiū dì míng kǎo lyè to the modern Méicūn 梅村 in Wuxī 無 , Jiangsu). Then it (according to the Xù Hàn Jùn guó zhì) moved to Wú 吳 (modern Sūzhōu 蘇州). Thus the city of Suzhou regards itself even today as as something of a cultural capital in the south of China.

History: The state of Wú was - in spite of its proclaimed Zhōu origin - conceived as barbarian by the states belonging to the Zhōu realm. However, Wú itself strived to establish itself as a part of the Zhū Xià 諸夏 and even seeked for the hegemeny among Chinese atates. The state is for the first time mentioned in ZUO in the entry for 601 BC (Wen 26). Particularly after 584 BC when the army of Wú was trained by &gt;Jìn 晉 instructors, the state gradually rose to power, and competed with the neighbouring state of &gt;Chǔ 楚. In 506 (Ding 4) Wú even occupied the capital of the much larger state of Chǔ. In the end, Wú was overextended itself, and in 473 it was destroyed by its southern neighbour and recurrent arch-enemy, the state of &gt;Yuè 越.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-544995bc-0c0d-4db9-a2d6-29f5241d721b" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of  a state</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>