<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-c5892bf2-4a49-49aa-892b-f24a49b9aadd" n="2">
    <form>
        <orth>趙</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="CUT" tls:concept-id="uuid-8fc0e3c9-f12b-4c37-9254-34df515d6a17" xml:id="uuid-fa3fa7db-a697-4a18-8198-a7585f7c0497" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-95cccfbd-389e-4e95-970c-f2b468ef2439">
<orth>趙</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhào</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">rlewʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖiɛu</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-45517bb2-6632-4a36-9ac3-cc5c488f44ef">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">1</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>cut; pierce</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-75fabdd0-bb95-48d5-ba7f-6867ae4858a2" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-95cccfbd-389e-4e95-970c-f2b468ef2439">
<orth>趙</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">zhào</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">rlewʔ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɖiɛu</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Zhào 趙

Clan: Ruled by the Yíng 贏 clan (according to the Zhào shìjiā chapter of SHI).

Rank: In the secong half of the fifth century B.C., rulers of Zhào were still of dàfū 大夫 rank. In 403 B.C. they were raised to the rank of zhūhóu 諸侯, and were then usually referred to as hóu 侯. In 323 B.C., the rulers of Zhào adopted the title of wáng 王.

Founded: Established in 453 BC after the split of Jìn, and in 403 BC recognized by the Zhōu king.

Destroyed: In 228 BC destroyed by &gt;Qín.

Location: Located in modern Shanxi and in southwestern part of Hebei. The first capital was Jìnyáng 晉陽 (modern Tàiyuán 太原 in Shanxi), in 424 it was moved to Zhōngmóu 中牟(in modern Zhōngmóu 中牟 district in northeastern Henan), and definitely, in 386 to Hándān 邯鄲 (modern Hándān 邯鄲 in southwestern Hebei). 

History: Zhào was established in 453 BC when three families divided the state of &gt;Jìn , and in 403 it was recognized by the Zhou king. In 323 the ruler of Zhào accepted the title of wáng 王. After the military reforms of &gt;king Wǔlíng (趙武靈王 325 - 299 BC) when the cavalry in a fashion of nomad tribes was introduced, Zhào grew in power and became one of the most powerful states in China. However, in 260 B.C. the Zhào army was completely destroyed by &gt;Qín 秦 at Chángpíng 長平, and in 228 BC the state was eliminated by Qín.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-ca01fdd1-f56b-4120-84bc-6203d035c9fa" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a state</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-40df8939-0b1a-4ff8-82ac-8d37a1497c4a">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos/>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-2dc23af9-ac81-4a01-9bf7-0f6644145476">npr{2}</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def/>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>