<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-cfa1f5b3-b34a-4454-a1f5-b3b34aa454c0" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>五無間</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="OFFEND" tls:concept-id="uuid-9944ce13-74d9-4e33-9a35-c7a074c69c9c" xml:id="uuid-dcec30e1-ea8b-4a34-8d5f-fe0219becd15" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-51845144-3245-439c-9701-95c63f8e4500 #uuid-5de002ac-c1a1-4519-a177-4a3afcc155bb #uuid-5a5cc212-2b69-406e-b138-775d40828e55">
<orth>五無間</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">wǔ wú jiān</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">ŋaaʔ ma kreen</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ŋuo̝ mi̯o kɣɛn</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-042f1088-8ef5-4e1e-be35-1d8ff1785655">LANKA(A)</ref>
<title>楞伽阿跋多羅寶經 Léngqié ābáduōluó bǎo jīng Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">498a</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"Now what is meant by the mother of all beings? It is desire which is procreative, going together with joy and anger and upholding all with motherliness. Ignorcance representing fatherhood brings about one's rebirth in the six villages of the sense-world. When there takes place a complete destruction of both roots, fatherhood and motherhood, it is said that father and mother are murdered. When there is a complete extermination of the subordinate group of passions such as anger, etc. which are like an enemy, a venomous rat, the murdering of the Arhat is said to take place. What is meant by breaking up the brotherhood? When there is a complete fundamental break-up of the combination of the Skandhas whose characterstic mark is a state of mutual dependence among dissimilarities, it is said that the Brotherhood is split up. [...] Mahaamati, when the body of the eight VijNNaanas, which erroneously recognises individuality and generality as being outside the Mind -which is seen [by the ignorant] in the form of an external world - is completely exterpiated by means of faulty discriminations, that is, my means of the triple emancipation of the non-outflows, and when thus the faulty mentality of the VijNNaana-Buddha is make to bleed, it is know as immediacy-deed. These, Mahaamati, are the five iner immediacies, and when they are experienced by a son or a daughter of a good family, there is an immediacy -deed or realisations regarding the Dharma." (tr. SUZUKI 1973: 120-121)</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-042f1088-8ef5-4e1e-be35-1d8ff1785655">LANKA(A)</ref>
<title>楞伽阿跋多羅寶經 Léngqié ābáduōluó bǎo jīng Taishō</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">498b11-14</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>貪名為母，無明則為父，覺竟識為佛，諸使為羅漢，陰集名為僧，無間次第斷，謂是五無間，不入無擇獄 "Desire is said to be the mother, and ignorance the father. The VijNNaana which recognizes an objective world [is compared] to the Buddha. The sccondary group of passions is the Arhat. The amassing of th five Skandhas the Brotherbood. As they are destroyed immediately. they are known as immediacy-deeds [[and do lead to the hell of continuous suffering]]. (tr. SUZUKI 1973: 121)</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-de72bd03-d709-459a-a9ea-9ba8c75643a6">SUZUKI 1973</ref>
<title>The Lankavatara Sutra</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">121</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-200aa218-05fa-432a-b5b4-da0dfc85d81d">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-db0698e7-db2f-4ee3-9a20-0c2b2e0cebf0">NPab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-f55cff2f-f0e3-4f08-a89c-5d08fcf3fe89">act</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: the five major offences; the five cardinal sins (which entail an endless existence in hell; defined as killing the father, killing the mother, killing of a sage (arhat), destroying the harmony of the sangha, shedding the blood of a Buddha; 無間 refers to the fact that these acts entail uninterrupted suffering in hell; In the LANKA and especially texts of the early Chán Schools, the cardinal sins are reinterpreted in terms of mental activities; see also wǔnì 五逆)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>