<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-5b893c32-e1b0-4664-893c-32e1b03664f1" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>身生</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="PENIS" tls:concept-id="uuid-d7158159-74c5-4463-a85a-2e27a4104944" xml:id="uuid-0468d03a-202f-4010-95fc-68e26eb7bbc0" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-3fea944e-3a8d-4a16-a19d-850444d49e0c #uuid-de384d51-47f4-44d9-8910-20aef1caaded">
<orth>身生</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">shēn shēng</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qhjin sraaŋ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ɕin ʂɣaŋ</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d163526f-7ff7-4b33-852b-3a87e8c3f225">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>penis (frequently used in BUDDH. translations from the Eastern Jin onwards)  汝愚癡人，寧以利刀割截身生 ignorant persons, you better cut your penis off with a sharp knive 若著蛇口中，若狂狗口中，若大火中，若灰炭中，不應與女人共行婬欲 (T.22/1425: 229b24) 爾時有比丘從異方來，身生長大，自於後道行欲，行欲已，然後疑悔，具白世尊。佛告比丘： “ 汝不知佛制戒不得行婬耶？ ”“ 世尊，我知制戒，謂為制他，不謂自己。 ” 佛言： “ 於自己行欲，亦犯波羅夷。 ”At that time there came a monk from foreign region, whose penis had grown big, and after that he engaged with himself in desires (i.e. masturbated), after he finished masturbating, he regreted and told everything to the Buddha. Buddha told the monk: "Don't you know about the commandment not to engage in licentious (sexual) activities ?" "World-honoured One, I know the monastic rules (commandments), and they say that they apply to others (i.e. sexual intercourse with others) and not to oneself." The Buddha said: "Engaging with oneself in sexual activities (i.e. masturbating), is also a violation of the Perfections." (T.22/1425: 234á2) 身生起 refers to the rising of the penis: 我於一時晝日眠，覺身生起，手觸，即失不淨，失不淨已，得眠安隱，病得除愈。 Once, during daytime, I fall asleep, and felt that my penis rose, I touched it with my hands and masturbated (?); after having masturbated (?), I could sleep peacefully and was able to cure my sickness (T.22/1425: 262b21) 身生起，有五事因緣。欲心起，大行起，小行起，風患起，若非人觸起，是為五事因緣。 (T.22/1425: 263b20) (LI WEIQI 2004: 271) 妒者，見他行婬事，然後身生起，是名妒，不能南。 (T.22/1425: 418ā) 作身生 'make a penis' refers to the masturbation of women using dildo-like objects. Note the ellaborate description of dildos below. It must have been a big industry at that time (some made of copper, lead, tin, ivory, wax, etc.)! 佛言：從今日後，不聽作胡膠形，胡膠形者，若胡膠作，若銅，鉛，錫，白鑞，若牙，若蠟蜜，如是比，作身生，以歇欲心者，偷蘭遮，是名胡膠形。 (T.22/1425: 545c14)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>