<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-567ce769-8cd6-46c9-bce7-698cd686c909" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>羅剎</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="BUDDHIST DEITIES" tls:concept-id="uuid-99966339-0ca3-4191-b8be-a2c84711be95" xml:id="uuid-9c303833-575b-47d1-9f77-44d0c73a2f21" n="2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-73b6e4e2-147a-4ead-8d0b-386283e2a333 #uuid-e1791e85-d9d9-4c57-b687-54c2af84c511">
<orth>羅剎</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">luó chà</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">b-raal tshraad</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">lɑ ʈʂhɣat</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-2389c812-8053-4187-8f7a-19f6e856050f">FOGUANG</ref>
<title>佛光大辭典 Fóguāng dàcídiǎn The Foguang Dictionary of Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">6673a-6674b</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p/>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-8acb78cf-6616-43bb-8af7-d124014190fd" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e7204ae-4771-435b-82ff-310068296b6d">buddhist</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: evil demon (also 羅剎婆, 羅叉婆, 羅乞察婆, 阿落剎婆); skr. rākṣasa; the female version of these demons is referred to as 羅剎女, 羅叉私, 羅剎斯; skr. rākṣasī); the male demons are often described as having a black body, red hair, and green eyes, whereas the female demons can assume very attractive bodies and can be endowed with much charm and sexappeal; having attracted a person they suck his blood and feed on his body; in Buddhist texts they sometimes are situated on Sri Lanka (楞伽島, skr. Rākṣī-dvipa, in this context also referred to as 羅剎女國); on these demons see for example FOBEN XINGJI JING,, fasc. 49;  occasionally these demons are also described as officers of hell where they torture delinquents; in hell they assume various forms, such as having the heads of sheep or oxen. In some Buddhist texts such as the AVATAMSAKA they figure as guardians of the Buddha and in this positive function are referred to as 羅剎天; in this function they are often depicted as powerful warriors riding on the back of lions; in Tantric Buddhism female and male demons are often depicted on mandalas)</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>