<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-5bc791df-3d94-4745-8791-df3d94f7450c" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>薛</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-4bdadfb6-2afe-4525-b490-ea3e27b91447" n="3">
            <form corresp="#uuid-869d8833-2be2-4eec-89c9-4d4fc574aadb">
<orth>薛</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xuē</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">sŋed</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">siɛt</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Xuē 薛 (CHEN PAN 1969, 256-261)

Clan: Rèn 任 (mentioned in the inscriptions on the bronze vessels, as well as in the ZUO, Shì běn and Guó yǔ).

Rank: Bó 伯 (according to the CQ; in the ZUO the rulers of Xuē are usually also referred to as bó). In the inscriptions on the bronze vessels, the rulers of Xuē refer to themselves as hóu 侯 (the same designation is used in the ZUO, Yin 11).

Founded: According to the tradition (recorded in the ZUO, Ding 1 - 509 B.C.), the rulers of Xuē were descendants of Xīzhòng 奚仲 (the offspring of the mythical Yellow emperor 黃帝) who was given a fief in Xuē during the reign of the legendary Xià 夏 dynasty. It should be noted that the name of Xuē is known already from the Shāng oracle bones.

Destroyed: Date of the destruction of Xuē and the state which conquered it remain unknown. The state was still in the existence by the end of the period recorded in the CQ. Later, it was most probably conquered by Qí 齊, as by the end of the 4th century B.C. the Qí noble Tián Yīng 田嬰 and his son Tián Wén 田文 (Mèngcháng jūn 孟嘗君) had their fief in Xuē.

Location: The first capital of Xuē, called Xuēchéng 薛城, was located in the modern Téng 滕 district, Shandong province. According to the Zhūshū yìzhèng, the capital of state shifted several times: first into Pī [written as 丕 with the radical 邑 on the left] (also called Xià Pī 下), which is supposed to be located in the eastern part of the modern Pī district (Jiangsu province), and later to Shàng Pī 上 (again in the modern Téng district, just thirty kilometers to the West from the first capital of the state). After the Chunqiu period, the capital of Xuē is supposed to shift again to Xià Pī, but in the Zhanguo period, Xuē had its capital in Xuēchéng. It is difficult to say how reliable this description is; basically, Xuē was located in the modern Téng district. One of the small walled cities excavated there, and dating from the end of the Shāng till Chunqiu period, is supposed to be the capital of Xuē.

History: Xuē was a small and weak state, which is for the first time mentioned in CQ and the ZUO under Yin 11 (712 B.C.). Throughout most of its history, it was exposed to the attacks of its neighbors, mainly of Qí. One of the earls of Xuē is noticeable for his debate over the precedence in the Zhōu royal audience with the the Marquis of Téng 滕, recorded in the ZUO in the entry for Yin 11 (712 B.C.) .



1. Located in modern Shāndōng province, in the southern part of the modern Téng 滕county.
2. The precise date of an establishment of the state is unknown, but it probably existed already in Shang times. Also the date of elimination of the state remains unknown, but it still existed by the beginning of the Warring states period. Later it was destroyed by the state of &gt;Qí 齊. A terminus ante quem is the end of the fourth century when Qís politician Mengchangjun was apppointed as a duke of Xuē.
3. Ruled by the Rèn 任 clan.
4. The capital was Xuē 薛 in the southern part of the modern Téng 滕county, southwestern Shandong.
5. According to the tradition, the rulers of Xuē 薛 were descendants of &gt;Huángdì 黃帝, the Yellow emperor. The state probably existed already in Shang times, and some of the archaeological finds uncovered in the Téng 滕county and dating from that period can be related to this state. In written sources, Xuē 薛 was for the first time mentioned in the Chunqiu and Zuozhuan in the entry for the eleventh year of the duke Yin &gt;Lǔ Yin gōng , when its ruler had a remarkable disputation on the
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-16c15a38-5094-418c-a120-d119ddf47aa3" n="3">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>name of a small state, became part of Qí</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>