<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-56f6ec2b-8c68-4e07-b6ec-2b8c684e07a9" n="1">
    <form>
        <orth>阿賴邪識</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="AWARE" tls:concept-id="uuid-493c2644-5dda-4f7b-9ae5-8665715a0fea" xml:id="uuid-0ed15646-abdd-45db-83bb-3da3f57ac45a" n="1">
            <form corresp="#uuid-762e3a6a-fc87-4da9-8563-ebe3159e36ad #uuid-7579b6ac-7ba1-4727-b63a-269db5dbeca0 #uuid-724ba4a2-8b6e-4d50-97be-800a29d2944d #uuid-434af956-d9d4-4729-a19a-e389aae89fa1">
<orth>阿賴邪識</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">ā lài yé shí</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">qlaal b-raads la qhljɯɡ</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">ʔɑ lɑi jɣɛ ɕɨk</pron>
                <listBibl>
<bibl>
                        <ref target="#uuid-a8099af3-8899-4cb8-9f19-ae2f6cecb3b6">TAKASAKI 1987</ref>
<title>An Introduction to Buddhism</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page">206-207</biblScope>
                        <note>
<p>"However, in the AvataMmsaka-suutra the identification in the doctrines of the Abhidharma of vijNNaana, citta, and manas with the one one and the same 'mind' had been accepted without any modification. But in the case of the doctrine of cognition-only [we2ishi2 唯識, vijNNapti-maatrataa] it was held that a number of functional aspects could be differentiated in this single 'mind', and these functionally different aspects were termed citta, manas, and vijNNaana. What we refer to as the 'mind' may first of all be divided into that aspect of it functioning in the present moment, that of the past, and that of the future. Strictly speaking, the aspects of the future and the past represent those aspects of which the appearance in the present will occur in the future or has already been concluded at some point in the past. As had already been elucidated by the theories of the Abhidharma, our existence is nothing other than a stream of consciousness ('the continuance of mind') extending from the past into the future, in which elements of the future are continuously appearing in the present and disappearing into the past. But this stream of consciousness contains another latent stream which does not appear on the surface, and this too exerts influence on the stream of consciousness appearing on the surface. If this were not the case, it would be impossible to explain the workings of karma. The karma-creating faculty was sought in the functions of the 'mind', and likening the mind to a storehouse of latent formative forces (biija,  zho3ngzi3 種子: seeds; = saMmskaara = karma), it was called the 'storehouse-consciousness' (aalayavijNNaana, ca2ngshi2 藏識, also transliterated as a1la4iye2shi2 阿賴耶識，a1li2ye2shi2 阿黎耶識).</p>
<p>The mind which is functioning in the present leaves behind an impression. This impression influences the mind of the following moment, but at the same time part of this impression may be stored as it is in the mind and manifest itself after a certain period of time. These impressions include not only those of the mind itself but also impressions of the objects of the mind's activity. The impressions of both subject and object are impressed upon the store-consciousness and determine the characteristics and workings of the mind thereafter. When considered in regard to its aspect as impression, this function is called 'perfuming (or infusing) of habit' (xu1nxi2 熏習) and the impression itself 'habitual energy' (xi2qi4 習氣; both these terms represent Chinese renderings of the SANSKRIT vaasanaa, which is usually derived from the verb 'to perfume' [vaasayati] and used in the sense of residual mental impressions which are compared to the scent which lingers on indefinitely in clothing after it has been perfumed with incense). Since this same impression determines the ensuing state of mind, it is in this sense also called a 'seed' (biija, zho3ngzi3 種子; needless to say, this appellation derives from the fact that insofar as the impression produces a result, it resembles the seeds of plants which, falling to the ground, later put forth shoots). It was held that the stream of consciousness's condition of being burdened down by past karma could be explained by such a mechanism. Consequently, the store-consciousness constitutes the stream of consciousness of individual beings, each of whom is burdened with past karma, and the mode of being which this store-consciousness assumes varies from one individual to another.</p>
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-14966438-f6a5-46f4-bab2-d0d08a6e8402" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-db0698e7-db2f-4ee3-9a20-0c2b2e0cebf0">NPab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-2e7204ae-4771-435b-82ff-310068296b6d">buddhist</tls:sem-feat>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>BUDDH: the eighth consciousness or 'storehouse' consciousness, skr. ālayavij%nāna</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>