<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-535532b2-7f5e-49d1-9532-b27f5ef9d191" n="2">
    <form>
        <orth>聃</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="EAR" tls:concept-id="uuid-cfec8c6f-06c5-479d-96a4-5ea48af644f2" xml:id="uuid-7c490e24-ccd6-4abc-8e66-39db13e94b1a" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-e94e9acb-76d1-4687-a34f-cc7246095797">
<orth>聃</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">dān</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">nʰaam</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">thɑm</pron>
            </form>
<sense xml:id="uuid-1e1d3a32-0ba4-4fde-a76b-3b12c16233d2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-8717712d-14a4-4ae2-be7a-6e18e61d929b">n</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>exceedingly rare, except as proper name of Laozi: long, pendulous ears</def>
            </sense>
</entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-915ecaf9-938a-48d6-ab98-15ba9b1c84fb" n="0">
            <form corresp="#uuid-e94e9acb-76d1-4687-a34f-cc7246095797">
<orth>聃</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">dān</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">nʰaam</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">thɑm</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Dān 聃 (also written as Rǎn 冉, Nán 南, Dān 耽) (CHEN PAN 1969, 647-650)

Clan: Jī 姬.

Rank: Unknown.

Founded: According to the Xìng jiě, the first ruler of Dān was Jì Zài 季載, the son of the Zhōu king Wén 周文王.

Destroyed: Unknown. According to the traditional Chinese historiography, Dān was conquered either by Chǔ 楚 or Zhèng 鄭 (the latter opinion seems to be more probable; see Location).

Location: Unknown. According to some opinions, the former capital of Dān was Nàchù 那處, which is mentioned in the ZUO (Zhuang 18; 676 B.C.) as belonging to Chǔ; if so, the former state of Dān must have been located somewhere in the neighborhood of Chǔ. In the ZUO, Xi 2 (658 B.C.), there is mentioned Zhèng 鄭 aristocrat Dān bó 聃伯, what would point to the fact that Dān was conquered by Zhèng and that it was located somewhere in the area of the latter state; Dì lǐ kǎo shí locates it into the area of modern Kāifēng 開封. This opinion seems more probable than the location of Dān to the neighborhood of Chǔ. Guǎng yùn mentions that the first fief of Dān was in the area of the western Zhōu royal capital, close to the modern Xī'ān 西安. This opinion sounds quite reasonable.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-8bfe1533-313e-4842-a63a-a6a35d2855e1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c43c0bab-2810-42a4-a6be-e4641d9b6632">NPpr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>Dān 聃 (also written as Rǎn 冉, Nán 南, Dān 耽 ) (CHEN PAN 1969, 647-650)Clan: Jī 姬.Rank: Unknown.Founded: According to the Xìng jiě, the first ruler of Dān was Jì Zài 季載, the son of the Zhōu king Wén 周文王. Destroyed: Unknown. According to the traditional Chinese historiography, Dān was conquered either by Chǔ 楚 or Zhèng 鄭 (the latter opinion seems to be more probable; see Location). Location: Unknown. According to some opinions, the former capital of Dān was Nàchù 那處, which is mentioned in the ZUO (Zhuang 18; 676 B.C.) as belonging to Chǔ; if so, the former state of Dān must have been located somewhere in the neighborhood of Chǔ. In the ZUO, Xi 2 (658 B.C.), there is mentioned Zhèng 鄭 aristocrat Dān bó 聃伯, what would point to the fact that Dān was conquered by Zhèng and that it was located somewhere in the area of the latter state; Dì lǐ kǎo shí locates it into the area of modern Kāifēng 開封. This opinion seems more probable than the location of Dān to the neighborhood of Chǔ. Guǎng yùn mentions that the first fief of Dān was in the area of the western Zhōu royal capital, close to the modern Xī'ān 西安. This opinion sounds quite reasonable. </def>
            </sense>
</entry>
</superEntry>