<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<superEntry xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uuid-588b9bd4-69ec-4287-8b9b-d469ec3287be" n="2">
    <form>
        <orth>徐</orth>
    </form>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="SLOW" tls:concept-id="uuid-41672630-f2c9-4525-8173-8dd61f5131d0" xml:id="uuid-7618a0b6-ef3b-4463-8fc7-8c561e7ec2b4" n="30">
            <form corresp="#uuid-0b34e21a-662f-4951-82dd-f82b87fe5eb4">
<orth>徐</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xú</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lja</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">zi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>The most generally used word for slowness is probably xú 徐 (ant. jí 疾 "fast"), which refers to an indifference on the part of the agent concerning the speed he is making, and the word has no negative connotations, indeed the reference is often to pleasant sauntering slow insouciance.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-7727f13a-7e87-4fea-9152-db49bfc35acb" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-76be1df4-3d73-4e5f-bbc2-729542645bc8">nab</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-f55cff2f-f0e3-4f08-a89c-5d08fcf3fe89">act</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>slowing down</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d0a185cd-c6d7-4511-89ff-62d55a78ed75" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a7e8eabf-866e-42db-88f2-b8f753ab74be">v[adN]</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-f8182437-4c38-4cc9-a6f8-b4833cdea2ba">nonreferential</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">2</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>the slow</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-0dec278c-923a-4ceb-b516-42a8d0c4e422">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fed035db-e7bd-4d23-bd05-9698b26e38f9">vadN</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>gentle (wind etc), slow</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-cca03b73-a774-4743-baaf-ff82a9593ccb" n="16">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-2a0ded86-3b04-4488-bb7a-3efccfa35844">vadV</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">4</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>slowly, softly, gently; with slow emphasis; at one's own pace, gradually</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-7f3e0a26-1294-49f0-96b7-775ad7f71014">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-cda1c3c1-e292-40d5-83be-7d4c3ae41a32">vi.red:adV</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>slowly, at one's convenience, without any hurry</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-eb4f0fa3-ba5a-450b-a37b-f3396a2aa4b6" n="2">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-e627d1e1-0e26-4069-9615-1025ebb7c0a2">vi.red</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>proceed very gently, slowly; going along gently</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-c4d6c3c7-e6e9-4123-848d-bd4b77b455c0" n="4">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">4</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>be slow and comfortable; be mild</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-278046f0-f733-45e2-9b5f-42d3016fa36c" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-3d95d354-0c16-419f-9baf-f1f6cb6fbd07">change</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>slow down</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-3da2a4ec-30d3-4e42-be78-4c3558996406" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>V</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-fbfb2371-2537-4a99-a876-41b15ec2463c">vtoN</tls:syn-func>
  <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-fac754df-5669-4052-9dda-6244f229371f">causative</tls:sem-feat>
                    <usg type="warring-states-currency">3</usg>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>slow down, calm down, stabilise</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-db616ac0-954b-4b01-a16a-c0954b8b018f" resp="#CH" tls:created="2021-03-24T21:37:11.415+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>V</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-c20780b3-41f9-491b-bb61-a269c1c4b48f">vi</tls:syn-func>
                <tls:sem-feat corresp="#uuid-4dc972a9-3436-4b68-8972-a934360b680e">comparative</tls:sem-feat>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>move too slowly</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
    <entry xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" tls:concept="STATES" tls:concept-id="uuid-7fd842b0-a38a-40b0-8332-f9bf6b059650" xml:id="uuid-51982e24-a322-4791-aa4a-4690521cf65b" n="2">
            <form corresp="#uuid-0b34e21a-662f-4951-82dd-f82b87fe5eb4">
<orth>徐</orth>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-Latn-x-pinyin">xú</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-oc">lja</pron>
                <pron xml:lang="zh-x-mc">zi̯ɤ</pron>
            </form>
            <def>Xú 徐 (also called Xúfāng 徐方, Xú Yī 徐夷, Xú Róng 徐戎; written also as Chá 茶 or Shū 舒, in some inscriptions on the bronzes as Yú 余) (CHEN PAN 1969, 535-547)

Clan: Yíng 嬴, which can be also written as 盈 or Yǎn 偃 (according to the Shì běn and to the ZUO). In the Shǐ jì (Qí shìjiā chapter), Xú Jī 徐姬 is mentioned among the consorts of the Lord Huán of Qí 齊桓公 (685-643 B.C.). It seems that it is either a mistake (note that the same person is in the ZUO, Xi 17, called Xú Yíng 徐嬴) or the word Jī 姬 is used as a general term for a consort.

Rank: Zǐ 子 (occurs in the CQ and ZUO under Zhao 4, 16, and 30). The rulers of Xú, which did not belong to the Zhōu realm, often referred to themselves as wáng 王 in the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts. This title also appears in other texts (Shǐ jì, Lǐ jì, Xúnzǐ, Hán Fēizǐ, Mù tiānzǐ zhuàn). In some of the inscriptions on the bronzes, the rulers of Xú are also referred to as hóu 侯 or bó 伯. The latter title is used in the Current Zhúshū jìnián in the entry for the sixth year of the King Mù of Zhōu 周穆王. 
Founded: According to the tradition recorded in the Tōng zhì Shìzú lyè, the rulers of Xú were descendants of Ruòmù 若木, the son of Bóyì 伯益 who was an advisor of the mythical emperor Yǔ 禹. Obviously, Xú was an ancient non-Zhōu state; note that Yú 余 (Xú 徐) is mentioned as a place-name already in the oracle bone inscriptions (however, it does not necessarily point to the Xú in the Anhui province, as there were more places of this name; see Location).

Destroyed: In 512 B.C. (Zhao 30) by Wú 吳.

Location: According to the Du's commentary, to the Kuò dì zhì, and to the Dì lǐ kǎo shí, the capital of Xú was located in the modern Sì 泗 district, Anhui province.
It should be noted that the place-name Xú was found also in other areas. In the state of Qí, there were perhaps two places called Xúzhōu 徐州: one approximately in the area of the modern Téng 滕 district, and another in the northwestern part of Qí 齊, on the borders with the state of Yàn 燕. Another Xú 徐 or Xúzhōu 徐州 (and mentioned for instance in the Shū jīng, the Bì shì chapter) was located on the eastern borders of Lǔ 魯. Again different Xú is mentioned in the Zhèng yǔ chapter of the Guó yǔ, which states that it was located to the north of the Zhōu eastern capital Chéng Zhōu 成周 (modern Luòyáng 洛陽). If there was any relationship between these place-names (pointing for instance to the spread of some closely related barbarian groups, as is suggested for example by the Dōng Yí zhuàn chapter of the Shǐ jì) is difficult to say.   

History: Xú was an ancient, strong, and highly civilized state which was never subdued by the Zhōu kings. The state and its inhabitants were closely related to the Eastern (Dōng) Yí 東夷 and to the Huái Yí 淮夷, and were probably one of their branches. Throughout the Western Zhōu period, Xú (called also Xú Róng 徐戎 or Xú Yí 徐夷) was a dangerous enemy of the Zhōu and eastern Zhōu states. Some of the inscriptions on the bronze artifacts record attacks from the side of Xú, and the same is recorded in some chapters of the Shū jīng (mainly in the Bì shì chapter; however, in this case, it is by no means certain that the record refers to the Anhui Xú; Xú mentioned in Bì shì was more probably located to the east of Lǔ). According to the Shǐ jì (Dōng Yí zhuàn), as well as to the Mù tiānzǐ zhuàn, Yǎn, the King of Xú 徐王偃, was a powerful rival of King Mù of Zhōu 周穆王 (but the story is rather legendary). Since 645 B.C. (Xi 15) when armies of Xú were defeated by Chǔ 楚 at Lóulín 婁林, Xú was exposed to the attacks from the side of Chǔ. In the second half of the 6th century B.C., the states of Chǔ and Wú strived to conquer Xú in order to gain a control over the lower reaches of the Huái 淮 river. Eventually, in 512 B.C. (Zhao 30), Xú was conquered by Wú.
</def>
<sense xml:id="uuid-d12eaf33-9e88-430a-a368-4e3cfc20e653" n="1">
<gramGrp>
                    <pos>N</pos>
  <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-bdf5c789-bfd8-4a3d-b6f7-2123f345d770">npr</tls:syn-func>
                </gramGrp>
  <def>A state, older even than that of Zhōu, a powerful state at the early stage that was able to challenge the Zhōu, but finally destroyed in 512.</def>
            </sense>
<sense xml:id="uuid-05e3930f-37f5-4264-a393-0f37f522641a" resp="#zadrapa" tls:created="2020-12-18T05:15:09.805+09:00" n="1">
            <gramGrp>
                <pos>N</pos>
                <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-af99c48b-0543-4b6e-99c4-8b0543eb6ee9">npr.adN</tls:syn-func>
            </gramGrp>
            <def>that of Xú</def>
        </sense>
    </entry>
</superEntry>