<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-fdf38722-58d3-4c4e-b2ec-4add0dae7cb4" subtype="PC">
  <head>氣噎</head>
  <div type="definition">qi[-induced] gullet occlusion</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="qiye-49777" n="qiye氣噎">
      <form>
        <orth>氣噎</orth>
        <pron>Qi ye</pron>
        <usg n="-induced">[7]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>qi[-induced] gullet occlusion</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>① Pathological Condition a) Alternative Names ye qi 噎氣 , gullet occlusion qi. A gullet occlusion disease brought forth by cold that has entered chest and diaphragm region, with panting, palpitation, and pain in the chest and back as characteristic signs. Zhu bing yuan hou lun 諸病源候論 20: 此由陰 陽不和，臟氣不理，寒氣填於胸膈，故氣噎塞不通，而謂之氣噎。令人 喘悸，胸背痛也 , “This is caused by a yin-yang disharmony, by a disregulation of depot qi, when cold qi fills the chest and diaphragm region. As a result there is a qi gullet occlusion and blocked passage, which is called ‘ qi[-induced] gullet occlusion .’ It causes a person to pant and have palpitations, as well as feel pain in the chest and back”.b) Identical with mei he ge qi 梅核膈氣 , plum-pit occlusion qi. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Bai bing zhu zhi yao 百病主治藥：氣噎，咽中如有物，吞 吐不出 , “ Qi[-induced] gullet occlusion , this is as if there were an object in thes gullet that cannot be removed by swallowing or vomiting”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
        <def>② Illness Sign of an inability to move food down, and of food that is thrown up as soon as it has been consumed. Ben cao gang mu 本草綱目 Substance Entry ding xiang 丁香 quotes De sheng tang jing yan Recipe book. Yuan era. fang 德生堂經驗方 : 反胃關 格：氣噎不通 , “Turned over stomach and blockage, that is qi[-induced] gullet occlusion closing the passage”.</def>
      </sense>
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>