<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tls="http://hxwd.org/ns/1.0" type="topic" xml:id="uuid-f33b0005-ad01-49ca-a090-f963c74a4fdc" subtype="IS">
  <head>瀉利</head>
  <div type="definition">unimpeded free-flux</div>
  <div type="pointers">
    <list type="hypernymy">
      <item/>
    </list>
  </div>
  <div type="source-references">
    <listBibl>
      <bibl>
        <ref target="#zhangBenCaoGang2015">Zhang and Unschuld 2015</ref>
        <title>Ben cao gang mu dictionary Vol1</title>
      </bibl>
    </listBibl>
  </div>
  <div type="words">
    <entry xml:id="xieli-49714" n="xieli瀉利">
      <form>
        <orth>瀉利</orth>
        <pron>Xie li</pron>
        <usg n="4">[4]</usg>
      </form>
      <def>unimpeded free-flux</def>
      <sense>
        <gramGrp>
          <pos>N</pos>
          <tls:syn-func corresp="#uuid-a8e89bab-49e1-4426-b230-0ec7887fd8b4">NP</tls:syn-func>
        </gramGrp>
              <def>Illness Sign identical with with xie xie 泄瀉① , outflow. Z BYHL 45: 傷寒，是寒氣 客於皮膚，搏於血氣，使腠理閉密，氣不宣洩，蘊積毒氣，頭痛、體疼 而壯熱也。其熱歇後而利者，是熱從表入裏故也。表熱雖得解，而裏熱 猶停腸胃，與水穀相併，腸胃虛則泄利。其狀，利色黃。若壯熱不止， 則變為血利。若重遇冷，則冷熱相加，則變赤白瀉利也 , “ ‘Harm caused by cold’ is to say: cold qi settles in the skin and strikes the blood and qi. It causes the interstitial structures to close so that the qi cannot flow off. This leads to accumulations of poison qi, with headaches, a painful body and strong heat. When the heat has ended and free flow is possible again, this is so because the heat has moved from the body’s outer sections into its interior. The external heat mayappear to have been resolved, but now the heat stagnates internally in the intestines and the stomach where it unites with water and grain. In the case of intestinal and stomach depletion, this leads to unimpeded outflow, as is indicated by a yellow color of the free flow. When the heat is strong and does not end, then a change occurs to bloody free flow. When [patient] is exposed to cold again, then cold and heat add to each other, and a change occurs to red-white unimpeded free-flux ”.</def>
            </sense>
      
      
    </entry>
  </div>
</div>